<all><change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 3 of the Data Protection Act 2018</subject>

   <quote>In section 3 of the Data Protection Act 2018 (referred to in this Act as “the 2018 Act”) (terms relating to the processing of personal data)—
(a) in subsection (3) (definition of “identifiable living individual”), after
paragraph (b) insert—
“(and see section 3A for provision about when information relates to
an identifiable living individual).”, and
(b) after that subsection insert—
“(3A) An individual is identifiable from information “directly” if the
individual can be identified without the use of additional
information.
(3B) An individual is identifiable from information “indirectly” if 
the individual can be identified only with the use of additional
information.”</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 3 of the Data Protection Act 2018 to provide more clarity on when an individual is considered identifiable from information. It introduces the concepts of "directly" and "indirectly" identifiable, with the former meaning the individual can be identified without additional information, and the latter meaning the individual can only be identified with the use of additional information.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">
      This amendment provides more clarity on the definition of identifiable information, which is a key concept in data protection and privacy laws. It could potentially affect how data is collected, processed, and shared, and could have implications for both individuals' privacy rights and businesses' data practices.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Article 4 of the UK GDPR</subject>

   <quote>In Article 4 of the UK GDPR (definitions)—
(a) the existing text becomes paragraph 1, 
(b) in paragraph 1(1) (definition of “personal data”)—
(i) for “identifiable natural person”, in both places it appears,
substitute “identifiable living individual”,
(ii) for “that natural person” substitute “the individual”, and
(iii) at the end insert “(and see paragraph 2)”,
(c) in paragraph 1, after point (1) insert— 
“(1A) an individual is identifiable from information “directly” if the
individual can be identified without the use of additional
information;
(1B)
an individual is identifiable from information “indirectly” if
the individual can be identified only with the use of additional
information;”</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Article 4 of the UK GDPR to align its definitions with those proposed for the Data Protection Act 2018. It replaces the term "identifiable natural person" with "identifiable living individual" and introduces the concepts of "directly" and "indirectly" identifiable.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">
      This amendment aligns the UK GDPR with the proposed changes to the Data Protection Act 2018, providing more clarity on the definition of identifiable information. This could potentially affect how data is collected, processed, and shared under the GDPR, and could have implications for both individuals' privacy rights and businesses' data practices.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 33 and 40 of the 2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>“(1A) “Consent” of the data subject to the processing of personal data means a freely given, specific, informed and unambiguous indication of the data subject’s wishes by which the data subject, by a statement or by a clear affirmative action, signifies agreement to the processing of the personal data (and see section 40A).”</quote>
   <quote>“40A Conditions for consent
(1) This section is about processing of personal data that is carried out in reliance on the consent of the data subject.
(2) The controller must be able to demonstrate that the data subject consented to the processing.
(3) If the data subject’s consent is given in writing as part of a document which also concerns other matters, the request for consent must be made—
(a) in a manner which clearly distinguishes the request from the other matters,
(b) in an intelligible and easily accessible form, and
(c) in clear and plain language.
(4) Any part of a document described in subsection (3) which constitutes an infringement of this Part is not binding.
(5) The data subject may withdraw the consent at any time (but the withdrawal of consent does not affect the lawfulness of processing in reliance on the consent before its withdrawal).
(6) Processing may only be carried out in reliance on consent if—
(a) before the consent is given, the controller or processor informs the data subject of the right to withdraw it, and
(b) it is as easy for the data subject to withdraw the consent as to give it.
(7) When assessing whether consent is freely given, account must be taken of, among other things, whether the provision of a service is conditional on consent to the processing of personal data that is not necessary for the provision of that service.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the 2018 Act to provide a clear definition of "consent" in the context of data processing. It also outlines the conditions for consent, including the requirement for the controller to demonstrate that the data subject has given consent, the need for clear and plain language in consent requests, the right of the data subject to withdraw consent at any time, and the requirement for the controller or processor to inform the data subject of the right to withdraw consent before it is given.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">The proposed changes strengthen the rights of individuals by providing a clear definition of consent and outlining the conditions for its validity. This could potentially enhance the protection of personal data and ensure that individuals have more control over their data.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The amendments provide a clear framework for obtaining consent for data processing, which could potentially enhance digital privacy by ensuring that individuals are fully informed and have given explicit consent before their data is processed.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>UK GDPR Article 6</subject>
   <quote>In Article 6(1) (lawful processing)—
(a) in point (e)—
(i) after “task” insert “of the controller”, and
(ii) after “or” insert “a task carried out”,
(b) after that point insert—
“(ea) processing is necessary for the purposes of a recognised legitimate interest;”, and
(c) in the words after point (f), for “Point (f)” substitute “Points (ea) and (f)”.</quote>
   <quote>“5. For the purposes of paragraph 1(ea), processing is necessary for the purposes of a recognised legitimate interest only if it meets a condition in Annex 1.
6. The Secretary of State may by regulations amend Annex 1 by—
(a) adding of varying provisions, or
(b) omitting provisions added by regulations made under this paragraph.
7. The Secretary of State may only make regulations under paragraph 6 where the Secretary of State considers it appropriate to do so having regard to, among other things—
(a) the interests and fundamental rights and freedoms of data subjects which require protection of personal data, and
(b) where relevant, the need to provide children with special protection with regard to their personal data.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to Article 6 of the UK GDPR to include processing necessary for the purposes of a recognised legitimate interest as a lawful basis for processing. It also provides for the Secretary of State to amend the conditions for processing based on a recognised legitimate interest by regulations, taking into account the interests and fundamental rights and freedoms of data subjects and the need to provide children with special protection with regard to their personal data.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">The proposed changes could potentially impact human rights by expanding the lawful bases for data processing to include processing necessary for the purposes of a recognised legitimate interest. This could potentially lead to more data processing activities, which could impact the rights of individuals.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The amendments could potentially impact digital privacy by expanding the lawful bases for data processing. However, the requirement for the Secretary of State to consider the interests and fundamental rights and freedoms of data subjects when making regulations could potentially enhance the protection of digital privacy.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Processing of personal data for a new purpose</subject>

   <quote>Processing of personal data for a new purpose is to be treated as processing in a manner compatible with the original purpose where—
(a) the data subject consents to the processing of personal data for the new purpose and the new purpose is specified, explicit and legitimate,
(b) the processing is carried out in accordance with Article 84B—
(i) for the purposes of scientific research or historical research,
(ii) for the purposes of archiving in the public interest, or
(iii) for statistical purposes, 30
(c) the processing is carried out for the purposes of ensuring that processing of personal data complies with Article 5(1) or demonstrating that it does so,
(d) the processing meets a condition in Annex 2, or
(e) the processing is necessary to safeguard an objective listed in 35 Article 23(1)(c) to (j) and is authorised by an enactment or rule of law.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that personal data can be processed for a new purpose if it is compatible with the original purpose under certain conditions. These conditions include the data subject's consent, the processing is for scientific, historical, or statistical purposes, the processing ensures compliance with Article 5(1), the processing meets a condition in Annex 2, or the processing is necessary to safeguard an objective listed in Article 23(1)(c) to (j) and is authorised by law.</summary>
   
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">This change could potentially impact digital privacy as it allows for the processing of personal data for new purposes under certain conditions. This could lead to increased data collection and usage, potentially impacting individuals' privacy rights.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change could potentially impact human rights, particularly the right to privacy, as it allows for the processing of personal data for new purposes under certain conditions.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Amendment of Annex 2 by the Secretary of State</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State may by regulations amend Annex 2 by—
(a) adding or varying provisions, or
(b) omitting provisions added by regulations made under this paragraph.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that the Secretary of State may amend Annex 2 by adding, varying, or omitting provisions. This gives the Secretary of State the power to make changes to the conditions under which personal data can be processed for a new purpose.</summary>
   
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">This change could potentially impact digital privacy as it gives the Secretary of State the power to amend the conditions under which personal data can be processed for a new purpose. This could lead to changes in data protection regulations, potentially impacting individuals' privacy rights.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially impact political power as it gives the Secretary of State the power to amend the conditions under which personal data can be processed for a new purpose. This could lead to changes in data protection regulations, potentially impacting the balance of power between the government and individuals.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Vexatious or excessive requests by data subjects</subject>

   <quote>1. Paragraph 2 applies where a request from a data subject under any of Articles 15 to 22 or 34 is vexatious or excessive.
2. The controller may—
(a) charge a reasonable fee for dealing with the request (see section 15 12 of the 2018 Act), or
(b) refuse to act on the request.
3. In any proceedings where there is an issue as to whether a request is vexatious or excessive, it is for the controller to show that it is.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that if a request from a data subject is deemed vexatious or excessive, the controller may charge a reasonable fee for dealing with the request or refuse to act on the request. In any proceedings where there is an issue as to whether a request is vexatious or excessive, it is for the controller to show that it is.</summary>
   
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">This change could potentially impact digital privacy as it allows controllers to charge a fee or refuse to act on requests from data subjects that are deemed vexatious or excessive. This could potentially limit individuals' ability to access or control their personal data.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change could potentially impact human rights, particularly the right to privacy, as it allows controllers to charge a fee or refuse to act on requests from data subjects that are deemed vexatious or excessive. This could potentially limit individuals' ability to access or control their personal data.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>UK GDPR Article 12 (transparent information, communication and modalities for the exercise of rights of the data subject)</subject>
   <quote>In Article 12 (transparent information, communication and modalities for the exercise of rights of the data subject)—
(a) in paragraph 3, for “within one month of receipt of the request” substitute “before the end of the applicable time period (see Article 12B)”,
(b) in paragraph 4, for “without delay and at the latest within one month of receipt of the request” substitute “without undue delay, and in any event before the end of the applicable time period (see Article 12B),”,
and
(c) in paragraph 6—
(i) after “may” insert “—
(a)”, and
(ii) at the end insert “, and
(b) delay dealing with the request until the identity is confirmed.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Article 12 of the UK GDPR, changing the time limit for responding to data subject requests from "within one month of receipt of the request" to "before the end of the applicable time period". It also allows for a delay in dealing with the request until the identity of the requester is confirmed.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change could potentially impact the rights of individuals to access their personal data in a timely manner, depending on the length of the "applicable time period". The ability to delay responses until identity is confirmed could also impact the speed of data access.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">This change directly impacts digital privacy, as it pertains to individuals' rights to access their personal data.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>UK GDPR Article 12B</subject>
   <quote>After Article 12A (inserted by section 7 of this Act) insert—
“Article 12B
Meaning of “applicable time period”
1. In Article 12, “the applicable time period” means the period of one month beginning with the relevant time, subject to paragraph 3.
2. “The relevant time” means the latest of the following—
(a) when the controller receives the request in question;
(b) when the controller receives the information (if any) requested in connection with a request under Article 12(6);
(c) when the fee (if any) charged in connection with the request under Article 12A is paid.
3. The controller may, by giving notice to the data subject, extend the applicable time period by two further months where that is necessary by reason of—
(a) the complexity of requests made by the data subject, or
(b) the number of such requests.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to insert a new Article 12B into the UK GDPR, which defines the "applicable time period" for responding to data subject requests. This period is one month from the latest of several possible times, and can be extended by two months if necessary due to the complexity or number of requests.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change could potentially impact the rights of individuals to access their personal data in a timely manner, depending on the length of the "applicable time period".</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">This change directly impacts digital privacy, as it pertains to individuals' rights to access their personal data.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 43 (overview and scope of Chapter 3 of Part 3: rights of the data subject in connection with law enforcement processing)</subject>
   <quote>(2) In section 43 (overview and scope of Chapter 3 of Part 3: rights of the data
subject in connection with law enforcement processing)—
(a) in subsection (1)(a), for “section 44” substitute “sections 44 and 45A”, 25
and
(b) in subsection (1)(b), for “section 45” substitute “sections 45 and 45A”.</quote>
   <summary>The amendment changes the references in section 43 from section 44 to sections 44 and 45A, and from section 45 to sections 45 and 45A.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 45A</subject>
   <quote>(6) After that section insert—
“45A Exemption from sections 44 and 45: legal professional privilege
(1)
35
Sections 44(2) and 45(1) do not require the controller to give the data
subject—
(a) information in respect of which a claim to legal professional
privilege or, in Scotland, confidentiality of communications
could be maintained in legal proceedings, or
16 Data Protection and Digital Information (No. 2) Bill
Part 1—Data protection 
(b) information in respect of which a duty of confidentiality is
owed by a professional legal adviser to a client of the adviser.</quote>
   <summary>The insertion of section 45A provides an exemption from sections 44 and 45 for legal professional privilege and confidentiality of communications.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 51 (exercise of rights through the Commissioner)</subject>
   <quote>(7) In section 51 (exercise of rights through the Commissioner)—
(a) in subsection (1), after paragraph (b) (but before the “or” at the end 25
of that paragraph) insert—
“(ba) relies on the exemption from sections 44(2) and 45(1)
in section 45A (legal professional privilege),”</quote>
   <summary>The amendment to section 51 adds a new provision that allows the controller to rely on the exemption from sections 44(2) and 45(1) in section 45A (legal professional privilege).</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>substitution</type>
   <subject>Article 22 of the UK GDPR (automated individual decision-making, including profiling)</subject>
   <quote>(1) For Article 22 of the UK GDPR (automated individual decision-making,
including profiling) substitute—
“Section 4A 5
Automated individual decision-making
Article 22A
Automated processing and significant decisions</quote>
   <summary>The substitution replaces Article 22 of the UK GDPR with a new provision on automated individual decision-making, including a definition of automated processing and significant decisions.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>substitution</type>
   <subject>Sections 49 and 50 (law enforcement processing: automated individual decision making)</subject>
   <quote>(3) For sections 49 and 50 (law enforcement processing: automated individual
decision making) substitute—
“50A Automated processing and significant decisions</quote>
   <summary>The substitution replaces sections 49 and 50 with a new provision on automated processing and significant decisions.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Automated decision-making safeguards</subject>

   <quote>The safeguards must consist of or include measures which—
(a) provide the data subject with information about decisions 35
described in subsection (1) taken in relation to the data subject;
(b) enable the data subject to make representations about such
decisions;
(c)
40
enable the data subject to obtain human intervention on the
part of the controller in relation to such decisions;
(d) enable the data subject to contest such decisions.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the introduction of safeguards for automated decision-making. These safeguards include providing the data subject with information about decisions taken in relation to them, enabling the data subject to make representations about such decisions, enabling the data subject to obtain human intervention on the part of the controller in relation to such decisions, and enabling the data subject to contest such decisions.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">The proposed change enhances the rights of individuals in relation to automated decision-making, providing them with more control and transparency.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The proposed change strengthens digital privacy by ensuring human intervention in automated decision-making and providing individuals with the ability to contest such decisions.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulatory powers of the Secretary of State</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State may by regulations provide that, for the
purposes of sections 50A(1)(a) and 50C(3)(c), there is, or is not, to be
taken to be meaningful human involvement in the taking or
reconsideration of a decision in cases described in the regulations.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to grant the Secretary of State the power to regulate the extent of human involvement in automated decision-making.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">The proposed change grants significant regulatory powers to the Secretary of State, potentially affecting the balance of power between the government and individuals or businesses.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The proposed change could impact digital privacy, depending on how the Secretary of State chooses to regulate human involvement in automated decision-making.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Technical and organisational measures</subject>

   <quote>In Article 24(1) (responsibility of the controller), for “appropriate technical
and organisational measures” substitute “appropriate measures, including
technical and organisational measures,”.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to amend the language around the responsibility of the controller, replacing "appropriate technical and organisational measures" with "appropriate measures, including technical and organisational measures".</summary>

   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The proposed change could potentially broaden the scope of measures that controllers are required to take to protect data, although the impact is likely to be minor.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Requirement for representatives for controllers outside the UK</subject>

   <quote>Omit Article 27 of the UK GDPR (representatives of controllers or processors
not established in the United Kingdom).</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to remove the requirement for representatives of controllers or processors not established in the United Kingdom.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The proposed change could potentially weaken the protections for UK data subjects when their data is processed by controllers or processors outside the UK, as there would no longer be a requirement for a representative in the UK.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">The proposed change could potentially make it easier for foreign businesses to operate in the UK, as they would no longer need to appoint a representative in the UK.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>UK GDPR</subject>
   <quote>The UK GDPR is amended in accordance with subsections (2) and (3).</quote>
   <quote>Before Article 28 insert—
“Section 1A
Senior responsible individual
Article 27A
Designation of senior responsible individual</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend the UK GDPR to include a new section and article that mandates the designation of a senior responsible individual within an organization.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Corporate Governance">This change would require organizations to have a designated individual responsible for data protection, which could significantly impact their governance structures and processes.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change would likely enhance data protection by ensuring that there is a designated individual responsible for overseeing and ensuring compliance with data protection laws.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>UK GDPR</subject>
   <quote>Article 27B
Senior responsible individual’s tasks
1. The senior responsible individual designated by a controller must be responsible at least for performing the tasks listed in paragraph 2 or securing that they are performed by another person.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to add a new article to the UK GDPR that outlines the tasks of the senior responsible individual, including monitoring compliance with data protection laws, ensuring the development and implementation of compliance measures, and dealing with complaints and data breaches.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Corporate Governance">This change would require organizations to have a designated individual responsible for a range of data protection tasks, which could significantly impact their governance structures and processes.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change would likely enhance data protection by ensuring that there is a designated individual responsible for overseeing and ensuring compliance with data protection laws.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>UK GDPR</subject>
   <quote>Article 27C
Senior responsible individual’s position
1. A controller or processor must support its senior responsible individual in the performance of the individual’s tasks, including by providing the individual with appropriate resources.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to add a new article to the UK GDPR that outlines the position of the senior responsible individual, including the requirement for the controller or processor to support the individual in performing their tasks.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Corporate Governance">This change would require organizations to support their designated senior responsible individual, which could significantly impact their governance structures and processes.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change would likely enhance data protection by ensuring that the senior responsible individual is adequately supported in their role.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>UK GDPR</subject>
   <quote>Omit Articles 37 to 39 (designation, position and tasks of data protection officer) and the section heading before Article 37.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to delete Articles 37 to 39 of the UK GDPR, which relate to the designation, position, and tasks of the data protection officer.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Corporate Governance">This change would remove the requirement for organizations to have a designated data protection officer, which could significantly impact their governance structures and processes.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change could potentially weaken data protection if the role of the data protection officer is not adequately replaced by the new senior responsible individual.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Senior responsible individual's tasks and position</subject>

   <quote>The senior responsible individual designated by a processor must be responsible at least for performing the tasks listed in subsection (4) or securing that they are performed by another person.</quote>
   <quote>A controller or processor must support its senior responsible individual in the performance of the individual’s tasks, including by providing the individual with appropriate resources.</quote>
   <quote>A controller or processor must not dismiss or penalise its senior responsible individual for performing the individual’s tasks.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the responsibilities and protections of the senior responsible individual designated by a data processor. This individual is tasked with monitoring compliance, cooperating with the Commissioner, and acting as a contact point for issues related to data processing. The bill also stipulates that the controller or processor must support this individual by providing appropriate resources and not penalizing them for performing their tasks.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Corporate Governance">
      This change could potentially increase accountability and transparency in data processing activities, as it mandates a specific individual to oversee compliance and cooperate with regulatory authorities.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      This change could potentially enhance the protection of personal data, as it ensures that there is a dedicated individual responsible for overseeing data processing activities and compliance with data protection laws.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Records of processing of personal data</subject>

   <quote>The UK GDPR is amended in accordance with subsections (2) to (4).</quote>
   <quote>The controller must maintain appropriate records of processing of personal data carried out by or on behalf of the controller.</quote>
   <quote>A controller or processor must make the records maintained under this Article available to the Commissioner on request.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the UK GDPR to require controllers and processors to maintain appropriate records of personal data processing. These records must be made available to the Commissioner upon request.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Corporate Governance">
      This change could potentially increase transparency and accountability in data processing activities, as it mandates the maintenance of detailed records and their availability to regulatory authorities.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      This change could potentially enhance the protection of personal data, as it ensures that there is a record of all data processing activities that can be reviewed by regulatory authorities.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Assessment of high risk processing</subject>

   <quote>In the heading of Section 3 of Chapter 4, for “Data protection impact assessment” substitute “Assessment of high risk processing”.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to amend the UK GDPR to replace the term "Data protection impact assessment" with "Assessment of high risk processing".</summary>

   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Corporate Governance">
      This change could potentially increase the focus on high-risk data processing activities, leading to more stringent assessments and potentially better data protection.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      This change could potentially enhance the protection of personal data, as it emphasizes the need for assessments of high-risk data processing activities.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Article 35 (data protection impact assessment)</subject>

   <quote>(3) In Article 35 (data protection impact assessment)— 15
(a) for the heading substitute “Assessment of high risk processing”,
(b) in paragraph 1, for “natural persons” substitute “individuals”,
(c) omit paragraphs 2 to 5,
(d) for paragraph 7 substitute—
“7 The controller must produce a document recording 20
compliance with this Article which includes at least—
(a) a summary of the purposes of the processing,
(b) an assessment of whether the processing is necessary
for those purposes,
(c) an assessment of the risks to individuals referred to 25
in paragraph 1, and
(d) a description of how the controller proposes to
mitigate those risks.”,
(e)
30
in paragraph 8, for “, in particular for the purposes of a data protection
impact assessment” substitute “for the purposes of an assessment
required by paragraph 1”,
(f) omit paragraph 9,
(g) in paragraph 10—
(i)
35
for “a data protection impact assessment” substitute “an
assessment of the envisaged processing operations on the
protection of personal data”, and
(ii) omit “for the processing”, and
(h) in paragraph 11—
(i) omit “Where necessary,”, and
32 Data Protection and Digital Information (No. 2) Bill
Part 1—Data protection 
(ii) for “to assess if processing is performed in accordance with
the data protection impact assessment” substitute “of an
assessment pursuant to paragraph 1 where necessary and”.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Article 35, changing the title from "data protection impact assessment" to "Assessment of high risk processing". It also changes the term "natural persons" to "individuals" and omits several paragraphs. The controller is required to produce a document recording compliance with the article, including a summary of the processing purposes, an assessment of necessity and risks, and a description of risk mitigation strategies. The term "data protection impact assessment" is replaced with "an assessment of the envisaged processing operations on the protection of personal data".</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">
      This amendment refocuses the assessment process on high-risk processing, potentially increasing the protection of individuals' data by requiring a more detailed risk assessment and mitigation strategy.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      The change from "natural persons" to "individuals" could potentially broaden the scope of data protection, as the term "individuals" may include entities such as corporations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Article 57(1) (Information Commissioner’s tasks)</subject>

   <quote>(4)
5
In Article 57(1) (Information Commissioner’s tasks), for paragraph (k)
substitute—
“(k) produce and publish a document containing examples of types
of processing which the Commissioner considers are likely to
result in a high risk to the rights and freedoms of individuals
(for the purposes of Articles 27A, 30A and 35);”.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to insert a new task for the Information Commissioner in Article 57(1). The Commissioner is to produce and publish a document containing examples of processing types that are likely to result in a high risk to the rights and freedoms of individuals.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">
      This insertion could enhance data protection by providing clear examples of high-risk processing, potentially helping entities to better understand and avoid such practices.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      By highlighting processing types that pose a high risk to individuals' rights and freedoms, this change could help protect those rights.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 68A (Codes of conduct)</subject>

   <quote>(6) After section 68 insert— 30
“Codes of conduct
68A Codes of conduct
(1) The Commissioner must encourage expert public bodies to produce
codes of conduct intended to contribute to compliance with this Part.
(2) Under subsection (1), the Commissioner must, among other things, 35
encourage the production of codes which take account of the specific
features of the various processing sectors.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to insert a new section, 68A, which mandates the Commissioner to encourage expert public bodies to produce codes of conduct that contribute to compliance with this Part. The Commissioner is also required to encourage the production of codes that consider the specific features of various processing sectors.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">
      The introduction of codes of conduct could enhance data protection by providing clear guidelines for compliance, particularly as these codes are to consider the specific features of various processing sectors.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">
      The production of sector-specific codes of conduct could impact tech companies by providing clearer compliance guidelines, potentially reducing regulatory uncertainty.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Article 84C</subject>
   <quote>This Article makes provision about when the requirement under Article 84B(1) for processing of personal data to be carried out subject to appropriate safeguards is satisfied.</quote>
   <quote>The requirement is not satisfied if the processing is likely to cause substantial damage or substantial distress to a data subject to whom the personal data relates.</quote>
   <quote>The requirement is only satisfied if the safeguards include technical and organisational measures for the purpose of ensuring respect for the principle of data minimisation (see Article 5(1)(c)), such as, for example, pseudonymisation.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces Article 84C, which outlines the conditions under which the processing of personal data is considered to be carried out with appropriate safeguards. These conditions include the absence of substantial damage or distress to the data subject and the inclusion of technical and organisational measures for data minimisation, such as pseudonymisation.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Article 84D</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may by regulations make further provision about when the requirement for appropriate safeguards under Article 84B(1) is satisfied.</quote>
   <quote>Regulations under this Article are subject to the affirmative resolution procedure.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces Article 84D, which gives the Secretary of State the power to make further regulations about when the requirement for appropriate safeguards under Article 84B(1) is satisfied. These regulations are subject to the affirmative resolution procedure.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Article 89</subject>
   <quote>Omit Article 89 (safeguards and derogations relating to processing for archiving purposes in the public interest, scientific or historical research purposes or statistical purposes).</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the deletion of Article 89, which pertains to safeguards and derogations relating to processing for archiving purposes in the public interest, scientific or historical research purposes or statistical purposes.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>RED</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 26(2)(f)</subject>
   <quote>In section 26(2)(f) (national security and defence exemption), before sub-paragraph (i) insert—“(zi) Article 77 (right to lodge a complaint with the Commissioner);”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes an amendment to Section 26(2)(f), adding a new provision that exempts the right to lodge a complaint with the Commissioner from the national security and defence exemption.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 4 of the 2018 Act (intelligence services processing)</subject>

   <quote>“(A1) This Part—
(a) applies to processing of personal data by an intelligence 30
service, and
(b) applies to processing of personal data by a qualifying
competent authority where the processing is the subject
35
of a designation notice that is for the time being in force
(see sections 82A to 82E).”</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to extend the application of Part 4 of the 2018 Act to include processing of personal data by a qualifying competent authority, provided that the processing is the subject of a designation notice that is currently in force.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security">This change could potentially increase the scope of intelligence services' data processing capabilities, which could have implications for national security.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">The extension of data processing to competent authorities could potentially impact individuals' privacy rights, depending on the nature and extent of the processing.</pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 4 of the 2018 Act (intelligence services processing)</subject>

   <quote>“82A Designation of processing by a qualifying competent authority
(1) For the purposes of this Part, the Secretary of State may give a notice 15
designating processing of personal data by a qualifying competent
authority (a “designation notice”) where—
(a) an application for designation of the processing is made in
accordance with this section, and
(b) the Secretary of State considers that designation of the 20
processing is required for the purposes of safeguarding national
security.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to allow the Secretary of State to designate processing of personal data by a qualifying competent authority for the purposes of safeguarding national security.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security">This change could potentially enhance national security by allowing the Secretary of State to designate certain data processing activities for this purpose.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">The designation of data processing activities by competent authorities could potentially impact individuals' privacy rights, depending on the nature and extent of the processing.</pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 82B Duration of designation notice</subject>
   <quote>A designation notice ceases to be in force at the earliest of the following times—
(a) at the end of the period of 5 years beginning with the day on
which it comes into force;
(b) (if relevant) at the end of a shorter period specified in the
notice;
(c) when the notice is withdrawn under section 82C.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that sets the duration of a designation notice. The notice will cease to be in force at the earliest of the following times: at the end of 5 years from when it comes into force, at the end of a shorter period specified in the notice, or when the notice is withdrawn under section 82C.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 82C Review and withdrawal of designation notice</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State must at least annually—
(a) review each designation notice that is for the time being in
force, and
(b) consider whether designation of the processing which is the
subject of the notice continues to be required for the purposes
of safeguarding national security.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that requires the Secretary of State to annually review each designation notice in force and consider whether the designation of the processing, which is the subject of the notice, continues to be required for the purposes of safeguarding national security.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="National Security"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 82D Records of designation notices</subject>
   <quote>Where the Secretary of State gives a designation notice—
(a) the Secretary of State must send a copy of the notice to the
Commissioner, and
(b) the Commissioner must publish a record of the notice.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that requires the Secretary of State to send a copy of the designation notice to the Commissioner, and the Commissioner must publish a record of the notice.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Freedom of Information"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 82E Appeal against designation notice</subject>
   <quote>A person directly affected by a designation notice may appeal to the
Tribunal against the notice.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that allows a person directly affected by a designation notice to appeal to the Tribunal against the notice.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 120A Principal objective</subject>
   <quote>It is the principal objective of the Commissioner, in carrying out
functions under the data protection legislation—
(a) to secure an appropriate level of protection for personal data,
having regard to the interests of data subjects, controllers and
others and matters of general public interest, and
(b) to promote public trust and confidence in the processing of
personal data.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that sets the principal objective of the Commissioner in carrying out functions under the data protection legislation. The Commissioner is to secure an appropriate level of protection for personal data and promote public trust and confidence in the processing of personal data.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Public Health"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 120C Strategy</subject>
   <quote>The Commissioner must prepare a strategy for carrying out the
Commissioner’s functions under the data protection legislation in
accordance with the Commissioner’s duties under—
(a) sections 120A and 120B,
(b) section 108 of the Deregulation Act 2015 (exercise of regulatory functions: economic growth), and
(c) section 21 of the Legislative and Regulatory Reform Act 2006
(exercise of regulatory functions: principles).</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that requires the Commissioner to prepare a strategy for carrying out the Commissioner’s functions under the data protection legislation in accordance with the Commissioner’s duties under sections 120A and 120B, section 108 of the Deregulation Act 2015, and section 21 of the Legislative and Regulatory Reform Act 2006.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Public Health"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 120D</subject>
   <quote>The Commissioner must, at such times as the Commissioner considers appropriate, consult the persons mentioned in subsection (2) about how the manner in which the Commissioner exercises functions under the data protection legislation may affect economic growth, innovation and competition.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new duty for the Commissioner to consult with certain individuals about how the Commissioner's actions under the data protection legislation may impact economic growth, innovation, and competition.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially influence the economic landscape by ensuring that data protection measures do not stifle economic growth, innovation, and competition.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 120E</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may designate a statement as the statement of strategic priorities for the purposes of this Part if the requirements set out in section 120H are satisfied.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that allows the Secretary of State to designate a statement of strategic priorities for data protection, provided certain requirements are met.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially increase the power of the Secretary of State in shaping the strategic direction of data protection.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 120F</subject>
   <quote>The Commissioner must have regard to the statement of strategic priorities when carrying out functions under the data protection legislation.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new duty for the Commissioner to consider the statement of strategic priorities when carrying out functions under the data protection legislation.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially influence the Commissioner's actions and decisions in enforcing data protection legislation.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 120G</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State must review the statement of strategic priorities if a period of 3 years has elapsed since the relevant time.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that requires the Secretary of State to review the statement of strategic priorities every three years.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially ensure that the strategic priorities for data protection are regularly updated and remain relevant.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 120H</subject>
   <quote>Before the Secretary of State designates a statement as the statement of strategic priorities, the Secretary of State must lay the statement before Parliament.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that requires the Secretary of State to present the statement of strategic priorities to Parliament before it can be designated.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially increase the transparency and accountability of the Secretary of State's actions in setting strategic priorities for data protection.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 124A of the 2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>The Commissioner must prepare appropriate codes of practice giving guidance as to good practice in the processing of personal data if required to do so by regulations made by the Secretary of State.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a new section 124A in the 2018 Act, which mandates the Commissioner to prepare codes of practice for the processing of personal data, if required by regulations made by the Secretary of State.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change could potentially enhance data protection by providing clear guidelines on the processing of personal data.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 124B of the 2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>The Commissioner must establish a panel of individuals to consider the code.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a new section 124B in the 2018 Act, which mandates the Commissioner to establish a panel of individuals to consider the code of practice.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change could potentially enhance data protection by ensuring that the code of practice is thoroughly reviewed by a panel of experts.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 124C of the 2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>Where a code is prepared under section 121, 122, 123, 124 or 124A, the Commissioner must carry out and publish an assessment of— (a) who would be likely to be affected by the code, and (b) the effect the code would be likely to have on them.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a new section 124C in the 2018 Act, which mandates the Commissioner to carry out and publish an assessment of the likely impact of the code of practice.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change could potentially enhance data protection by ensuring that the impact of the code of practice is thoroughly assessed and made public.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 124D of the 2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>Where a code is prepared under section 121, 122, 123, 124 or 124A, the Commissioner must submit the final version to the Secretary of State.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a new section 124D in the 2018 Act, which mandates the Commissioner to submit the final version of the code of practice to the Secretary of State.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change could potentially enhance data protection by ensuring that the final version of the code of practice is reviewed by the Secretary of State.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 135 of the 2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>In section 135 (manifestly unfounded or excessive requests made to the Commissioner)—
(a) in the heading, for “Manifestly unfounded” substitute “Vexatious”,
(b) in subsection (1)—
(i) for “manifestly unfounded” substitute “vexatious”, and
(ii) after “excessive” insert “(see section 204A)”,
(c) omit subsection (2), 20
(d) in subsection (3), for “manifestly unfounded” substitute “vexatious”,
(e) omit subsection (4), and
(f) after that subsection insert—
“(5)
25
Article 57(3) of the UK GDPR (performance of Information
Commissioner’s tasks generally to be free of charge for data
subject) has effect subject to this section.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 135 of the 2018 Act, changing the term "manifestly unfounded" to "vexatious" in the context of requests made to the Commissioner. It also proposes to omit subsections (2) and (4) of the same section.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially affect how requests made to the Commissioner are evaluated and handled, possibly leading to a stricter interpretation of what constitutes a "vexatious" request.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>“139A Analysis of performance
(1)
35
The Commissioner must prepare and publish an analysis of the
Commissioner’s performance using key performance indicators.
(2) The analysis must be prepared and published at least annually.
Data Protection and Digital Information (No. 2) Bill 57
Part 1—Data protection 
(3) In this section, “key performance indicators” means factors by reference
to which the Commissioner’s performance can be measured most
effectively.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to insert a new section (139A) into the 2018 Act, requiring the Commissioner to prepare and publish an annual analysis of their performance using key performance indicators.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Public Health">This change could potentially increase transparency and accountability in the Commissioner's performance, which could have implications for public trust in data protection measures.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Sections 142, 143, 145, 148, 160 of the 2018 Act and Schedule 17</subject>
   <quote>In section 142 (information notices)—
(a) in subsection (1)—
(i) in paragraph (a), after “information” insert “or documents”, 10
and
(ii) in paragraph (b), after “information” insert “or documents”,
(b) in subsection (2)(b), after “information” insert “or documents”,
(c) in subsection (3)—
(i) in paragraph (a), after “information”, in both places it occurs, 15
insert “or documents”,
(ii) in paragraph (b), after “information” insert “or documents”,
(iii) in paragraph (c), after “information” insert “or documents”,
and
(iv) in paragraph (d), after “information” insert “or documents”, 20
(d) in subsection (5), after “information”, in the second place it occurs,
insert “or documents”,
(e) in subsection (6), after “information”, in the second place it occurs,
insert “or documents”, and
(f) in subsection (7)— 25
(i) in paragraph (a), for “is” substitute “or documents are”, and
(ii) in the words after paragraph (b), after “information” insert “or
documents”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend several sections of the 2018 Act (142, 143, 145, 148, 160) and Schedule 17, inserting the term "or documents" after "information" in various subsections. This expands the scope of these sections to include not just information, but also documents.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially broaden the scope of information requests and notices, affecting how data protection laws are enforced.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>In section 146 (assessment notices)—
(a) in subsection (2), after paragraph (i), insert—
“(j)
25
make arrangements for an approved person to prepare
a report on a specified matter;
(k) provide to the Commissioner a report prepared in
pursuance of such arrangements.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to insert new provisions into section 146 of the 2018 Act, allowing for the arrangement of an approved person to prepare a report on a specified matter and provide it to the Commissioner.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially affect how assessments are conducted, possibly leading to more thorough and expert evaluations.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 146A</subject>
   <quote>“(11A) Where the Commissioner gives an assessment notice that requires the controller or processor to make arrangements for an approved person to prepare a report, the controller or processor is liable for the payment of the approved person’s remuneration and expenses under the arrangements.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that makes the controller or processor responsible for the payment of an approved person's remuneration and expenses when they are required to prepare a report following an assessment notice from the Commissioner.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially increase the financial burden on controllers or processors, as they are now liable for the costs associated with preparing a report in response to an assessment notice.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 146A</subject>
   <quote>“(2) The controller or processor must, within such period as is specified in the assessment notice, nominate to the Commissioner a person to prepare the report.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new requirement for the controller or processor to nominate a person to prepare a report within a specified period following an assessment notice.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Bureaucratic Processes">This change introduces a new procedural requirement for controllers or processors, potentially increasing their administrative responsibilities.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 148A</subject>
   <quote>“(2) For the purpose of investigating the suspected failure or offence, the Commissioner may, by written notice (an “interview notice”), require an individual within subsection (3) to— (a) attend at a place specified in the notice, and (b) answer questions with respect to any matter relevant to the investigation.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that allows the Commissioner to issue an "interview notice" requiring an individual to attend a specified location and answer questions relevant to an investigation into a suspected failure or offence.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially increase the powers of the Commissioner in investigating suspected failures or offences, potentially impacting the legal processes involved.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 148B</subject>
   <quote>“(1) An interview notice does not require an individual to answer questions to the extent that requiring the person to do so would involve an infringement of the privileges of either House of Parliament.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that protects the privileges of either House of Parliament, stating that an interview notice does not require an individual to answer questions if doing so would infringe upon these privileges.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially protect the privileges of Parliament, potentially impacting the balance of power between the legislative branch and the Commissioner.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 148C</subject>
   <quote>It is an offence for an individual, in response to an interview notice—
(a) to make a statement which the individual knows to be false in
a material respect, or
(b) recklessly to make a statement which is false in a material 40
respect.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new offence for making false statements in response to an interview notice.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>RED</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 160</subject>
   <quote>In section 160 (guidance about regulatory action)—
(a) in subsection (1), after paragraph (b) insert—
“(ba) interview notices,”, and
(b) after subsection (5) insert—
“(5A) In relation to interview notices, the guidance must include— 10
(a) provision specifying factors to be considered in
determining whether to give an interview notice to an
individual;
(b)
15
provision about the circumstances in which the
Commissioner would consider it appropriate to give an
interview notice to an individual in reliance on section
148A(8) (urgent cases);
(c) provision about the circumstances in which the
20
Commissioner would consider it appropriate to vary
the place or time specified in an interview notice at the
request of the individual to whom the notice is given;
(d) provision about the nature of interviews carried out in
accordance with an interview notice;
(e)
25
provision about how the Commissioner will determine
how to proceed if an individual does not comply with
an interview notice.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces new guidance about regulatory action in relation to interview notices. This includes factors to consider when giving an interview notice, circumstances for varying the place or time of an interview, and how to proceed if an individual does not comply with an interview notice.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 161A</subject>
   <quote>“161A Annual report on regulatory action
(1) The Commissioner must produce and publish an annual report 25
containing the information described in subsections (2) to (5).
(2) The report must include the following information about UK GDPR
investigations—
(a)
30
the number of investigations begun, continued or completed
by the Commissioner during the reporting period,
(b) the different types of act and omission that were the subject
matter of the investigations,
(c) the enforcement powers exercised by the Commissioner in the
reporting period in connection with the investigations,
(d) the duration of investigations that ended in the reporting 35
period, and
(e) the different types of outcome in investigations that ended in
that period.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a requirement for the Commissioner to produce and publish an annual report on regulatory action. This report must include information about UK GDPR investigations, such as the number of investigations, the types of acts and omissions investigated, the enforcement powers exercised, the duration of investigations, and the outcomes of investigations.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Freedom of Information"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 164A</subject>
   <quote>“164A Complaints by data subjects to controllers
(1) A data subject may make a complaint to the controller if the data 35
subject considers that, in connection with personal data relating to the
data subject, there is an infringement of the UK GDPR or Part 3 of
this Act.
(2)
40
A controller must facilitate the making of complaints under this section
by taking steps such as providing a complaint form which can be
completed electronically and by other means.
(3) If a controller receives a complaint under this section, the controller
must acknowledge receipt of the complaint within the period of 30
days beginning with the day on which it is received.
(4)
5
If a controller receives a complaint under this section, the controller
must without undue delay—
(a) take appropriate steps to respond to the complaint, and
(b) inform the complainant of the outcome of the complaint.
(5) The reference in subsection (4)(a) to taking appropriate steps to respond
to the complaint includes—
(a) making enquiries into the subject matter of the complaint, to 10
the extent appropriate, and
(b) informing the complainant about progress on the complaint.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes a new section that allows data subjects to make complaints directly to the controller if they believe there has been an infringement of the UK GDPR or Part 3 of the Act. The controller is required to facilitate the making of complaints, acknowledge receipt within 30 days, and respond without undue delay. The controller must also keep the complainant informed about the progress of the complaint.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change empowers individuals by giving them a direct avenue to raise concerns about potential infringements of their data rights.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially increase the workload of controllers, as they will now be required to handle complaints directly and respond in a timely manner.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 164B</subject>
   <quote>“164B Controllers to notify the Commissioner of the number of complaints
(1)
15
The Secretary of State may by regulations require a controller to notify
the Commissioner of the number of complaints made to the controller
under section 164A in periods specified or described in the regulations.
(2) Regulations under this section may provide that a controller is required
to make a notification to the Commissioner in respect of a period only
in circumstances specified in the regulations.
(3) Regulations under this section may include— 20
(a) provision about a matter listed in subsection (4), or
(b) provision conferring power on the Commissioner to determine
those matters.
(4) The matters are—
(a) the form and manner in which a notification must be made, 25
(b) the time at which, or period within which, a notification must
be made, and
(c) how the number of complaints made to a controller during a
period is to be calculated.
(5) Regulations under this section are subject to the negative resolution 30
procedure.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes a new section that allows the Secretary of State to require controllers to notify the Commissioner of the number of complaints they receive. The regulations may specify the form and manner of notification, the time or period within which a notification must be made, and how the number of complaints is to be calculated.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change could potentially improve transparency and accountability in the handling of data protection complaints.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially increase the workload of controllers, as they will now be required to track and report the number of complaints they receive.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 165</subject>
   <quote>(2) In section 165 (complaints by data subject to the Commissioner)—
(a) omit subsection (1), 35
(b) in subsection (2), after “infringement of” insert “the UK GDPR or”,
and
(c) after subsection (5) insert—
“(5A) Subsection (4) does not apply if the Commissioner refuses to
act on the complaint in reliance on section 165A.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend section 165 by omitting subsection (1), adding "the UK GDPR or" after "infringement of" in subsection (2), and adding a new subsection (5A) that allows the Commissioner to refuse to act on a complaint in reliance on section 165A.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change could potentially limit the rights of data subjects by allowing the Commissioner to refuse to act on their complaints under certain conditions.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially reduce the workload of the Commissioner by allowing them to refuse to act on certain complaints.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 183A of the 2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>“Prohibitions and restrictions etc on processing
183A Protection of prohibitions and restrictions etc on processing
(1) A relevant enactment or rule of law which imposes a duty, or confers 25
a power, to process personal data does not override a requirement
under the main data protection legislation relating to the processing
of personal data.
(2) Subsection (1) does not apply—
(a) to a relevant enactment forming part of the main data 30
protection legislation, or
(b) to the extent that an enactment makes express provision to the
contrary referring to this section or to the main data protection
legislation (or a provision of that legislation).
(3) Subsection (1) does not prevent a duty or power to process personal 35
data from being taken into account for the purpose of determining
whether it is possible to rely on an exception to a requirement under
the main data protection legislation that is available where there is
such a duty or power.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a new section 183A into the 2018 Act. This section provides that a law or rule that imposes a duty or confers a power to process personal data does not override the requirements of the main data protection legislation. However, this does not apply to a relevant enactment forming part of the main data protection legislation or if an enactment makes express provision to the contrary. It also does not prevent a duty or power to process personal data from being considered when determining if an exception to a requirement under the main data protection legislation is available.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change strengthens the protection of personal data by ensuring that other laws or rules do not override the requirements of the main data protection legislation. This could have significant implications for the protection of privacy and personal data.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 2 of the Bill</subject>
   <quote>(1) This Part contains provision to secure the reliability of digital verification 30
services by means of—
(a) a trust framework (see section 47),
(b) a register (see section 48),
(c) an information gateway (see section 54), and
(d) a trust mark (see section 57).</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the establishment of a new framework to secure the reliability of digital verification services. This includes the creation of a trust framework, a register, an information gateway, and a trust mark.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Economy">This change could have significant implications for the digital economy, particularly for businesses that provide digital verification services. It could also impact consumers by providing greater security and reliability when using these services.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">The establishment of a new framework for digital verification services could lead to increased regulation of tech companies that provide these services.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>UK GDPR, Chapter 9A</subject>
   <quote>“CHAPTER 9A
Regulations 5
Article 91A
Regulations made by Secretary of State
1. This Article makes provision about regulations made by the Secretary
of State under this Regulation (“UK GDPR regulations”).</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a new Chapter 9A into the UK GDPR. This chapter provides for regulations made by the Secretary of State under the UK GDPR.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially increase the power of the Secretary of State by allowing them to make regulations under the UK GDPR.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The ability for the Secretary of State to make regulations under the UK GDPR could have implications for digital privacy, depending on the nature of the regulations made.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>DVS trust framework</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State must prepare and publish a document setting out rules concerning the provision of digital verification services.</quote>
   <quote>The Secretary of State must consult—
(a) the Information Commissioner, and 15
(b) such other persons as the Secretary of State thinks appropriate.</quote>
   <quote>At least every 12 months, the Secretary of State must—
(a) carry out a review of the DVS trust framework, and 20
(b) in doing so, consult the persons mentioned in subsection (3).</quote>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may revise and republish the DVS trust framework, whether following a review under subsection (5) or otherwise.</quote>

   <summary>The Secretary of State is required to prepare and publish a document outlining rules for the provision of digital verification services, known as the DVS trust framework. This framework must be reviewed and potentially revised at least every 12 months, with consultation from the Information Commissioner and other relevant parties.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Internet Governance">The creation of the DVS trust framework will establish a new set of rules for the provision of digital verification services, impacting how these services are governed and regulated.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">Tech companies providing digital verification services will be directly affected by the rules set out in the DVS trust framework, potentially impacting their operations and responsibilities.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>DVS register</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State must establish and maintain a register of persons providing digital verification services.</quote>
   <quote>The Secretary of State must make the DVS register publicly available.</quote>
   <quote>The Secretary of State must, subject to section 52(9), register a person providing digital verification services in the DVS register if—
(a) the person holds a certificate from an accredited conformity assessment body certifying that the digital verification services provided by the person are provided in accordance with the DVS trust framework,
(b) the person applies to be registered in the DVS register in respect of the digital verification services to which the certificate relates,
(c) the application complies with any requirements imposed by a determination under section 49, and
(d) the person pays any fee required to be paid by a determination under 10 section 50(1).</quote>

   <summary>The Secretary of State is required to establish and maintain a public register of persons providing digital verification services, known as the DVS register. To be registered, a person must hold a certificate from an accredited conformity assessment body, apply for registration, comply with any requirements, and pay any required fee.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Internet Governance">The establishment of the DVS register will create a new mechanism for tracking and regulating providers of digital verification services, impacting the governance of these services.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">Tech companies providing digital verification services will be required to register in the DVS register, potentially impacting their operations and responsibilities.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 2—Digital verification services</subject>

   <quote>Where the Secretary of State removes the person from the DVS register, the Secretary of State must by written notice inform the person— (a) that the person has been removed from the register, and (b) that any application for re-registration made by the person during a period specified in the notice must be refused.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a new process for removing a person from the Digital Verification Services (DVS) register and refusing their re-registration for a specified period.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Identity"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 2—Digital verification services</subject>

   <quote>This section applies where the Secretary of State revises and republishes the DVS trust framework and the revisions include— (a) the addition of a rule, or (b) the alteration of an existing rule.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a provision for the Secretary of State to revise and republish the DVS trust framework, including the addition or alteration of rules.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Identity"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 2—Digital verification services</subject>

   <quote>A public authority may disclose to the person information relating to the individual for the purpose of enabling the person to provide the digital verification services for the individual.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a new provision allowing public authorities to disclose personal information to registered persons for the purpose of providing digital verification services.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 2—Digital verification services</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State must prepare and publish a code of practice about the disclosure of information under section 54.</quote>

   <summary>The bill mandates the Secretary of State to prepare and publish a code of practice regarding the disclosure of information under the proposed section.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 2—Digital verification services</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State may designate a mark for use in the course of providing, or offering to provide, digital verification services.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a provision for the Secretary of State to designate a mark for use in the course of providing or offering to provide digital verification services.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Identity"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 2—Digital verification services</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State may by written notice require— (a) an accredited conformity assessment body, or (b) a person registered in the DVS register, to provide the Secretary of State with information that the Secretary of State reasonably requires for the purposes of the exercise of the Secretary of State’s functions under this Part.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a new power for the Secretary of State to require information from an accredited conformity assessment body or a person registered in the DVS register.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Identity"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 59</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may make arrangements for a person prescribed by regulations under this section to exercise functions of the Secretary of State under this Part (and where arrangements are made, references in this Part to the Secretary of State are to be read accordingly).</quote>
   <summary>The Secretary of State is given the power to delegate their functions under this part of the bill to a person prescribed by regulations.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially shift some power from the Secretary of State to another person or entity, depending on who is prescribed by the regulations.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 60</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State must prepare and publish reports on the operation of this Part.</quote>
   <summary>The Secretary of State is required to prepare and publish reports on the operation of this part of the bill.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Transparency">This change increases transparency by requiring the Secretary of State to publish reports on the operation of this part of the bill.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 61</subject>
   <quote>This Part confers powers on the Secretary of State and the Treasury to make provision in connection with access to customer data and business data.</quote>
   <summary>The Secretary of State and the Treasury are given powers to make provisions regarding access to customer data and business data.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Privacy">This change could potentially impact privacy, depending on the provisions made by the Secretary of State and the Treasury.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially impact businesses, depending on the provisions made by the Secretary of State and the Treasury.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 62</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State or the Treasury may by regulations make provision requiring a data holder to provide customer data— (a) to the customer, at the customer’s request, or (b) to a person who is authorised by the customer to receive the data (an “authorised person”), at the customer’s request or at the authorised person’s request.</quote>
   <summary>The Secretary of State or the Treasury can make regulations requiring a data holder to provide customer data to the customer or an authorised person, at the request of the customer or the authorised person.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Privacy">This change could potentially impact privacy, depending on the regulations made by the Secretary of State or the Treasury.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially impact businesses, depending on the regulations made by the Secretary of State or the Treasury.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulation of customer data</subject>
   <quote>The regulations may make provision about the procedure by which customers authorise persons to receive customer data or to do other things</quote>
   <quote>The regulations may make provision about the providing of customer data and the exercising of customers’ rights</quote>
   <quote>The regulations may make provision requiring a person who, in the course of a business, processes customer data of a trader to assist, or take specified steps to assist, the trader in complying with regulations under this Part.</quote>
   <quote>The regulations may make provision about the processing of customer data provided to an authorised person in accordance with the regulations</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes regulations on how customers can authorize others to receive their data, how customer data is provided and how customers' rights are exercised. It also proposes regulations on the processing of customer data and the assistance required from those who process customer data in the course of business.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The proposed changes will significantly impact digital privacy as they regulate how customer data is handled, processed, and shared.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">Tech companies that handle customer data will be directly affected by these regulations, as they will need to comply with new procedures and requirements.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulation of business data</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State or the Treasury may by regulations make provision requiring a data holder to publish business data or to provide business data on request</quote>
   <quote>The Secretary of State or the Treasury may by regulations make provision enabling or requiring a data holder to produce, collect or retain, or arrange for the production, collection or retention of, business data.</quote>
   <quote>The regulations may make provision about the providing or publishing of business data</quote>
   <quote>The regulations may make provision about the processing of business data provided to a person in accordance with the regulations</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes regulations on the publication, provision, collection, retention, and processing of business data. These regulations will be made by the Secretary of State or the Treasury.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Economy">The proposed changes will impact the digital economy as they regulate how business data is handled, processed, and shared.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">Tech companies that handle business data will be directly affected by these regulations, as they will need to comply with new procedures and requirements.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Dispute resolution and complaint handling</subject>
   <quote>The regulations may make provision about complaints, including provision requiring data holders, authorised persons or decision-makers to implement procedures for the handling of complaints.</quote>
   <quote>The regulations may make provision about procedures for the resolution of disputes</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes regulations on the handling of complaints and the resolution of disputes related to customer and business data. These regulations will require data holders, authorised persons, and decision-makers to implement procedures for handling complaints and resolving disputes.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The proposed changes will impact the justice system by introducing new procedures for handling complaints and resolving disputes related to customer and business data.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">Tech companies that handle customer and business data will be directly affected by these regulations, as they will need to implement new complaint handling and dispute resolution procedures.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulations about data holders and approved persons</subject>
   <quote>(8) The regulations may make provision enabling or requiring a data holder or an approved person to publish specified information relating to the rights and obligations of persons under the regulations, including information about the activities carried out by the data holder or approved person in performance of their obligations under the regulations.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes regulations that may enable or require data holders or approved persons to publish specified information relating to the rights and obligations of persons under the regulations. This includes information about the activities carried out by the data holder or approved person in performance of their obligations under the regulations.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change could potentially increase transparency and accountability of data holders and approved persons, which could enhance the protection of individuals' data rights.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Freedom of Information">This change could potentially increase the availability of information about the activities of data holders and approved persons, which could enhance public understanding and scrutiny of these entities.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulations about decision-makers</subject>
   <quote>(1) This section is about the provision about decision-makers that regulations under section 62 or 64 must or may (among other things) contain. (2) The regulations may make provision about the appointment of a decision-maker. (3) The regulations may make provision enabling or requiring a decision-maker to suspend or revoke a decision.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes regulations that may make provision about the appointment of a decision-maker and enabling or requiring a decision-maker to suspend or revoke a decision.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially affect the appointment and decision-making processes of decision-makers, which could impact the enforcement of data regulations.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Enforcement of data regulations</subject>
   <quote>(1) The Secretary of State or the Treasury may by regulations make provision— (a) for the enforcement of data regulations, and (b) for the enforcement of requirements imposed in exercise of a power conferred by regulations under this Part, including provision for enforcement by a specified public body (an “enforcer”).</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes that the Secretary of State or the Treasury may by regulations make provision for the enforcement of data regulations and for the enforcement of requirements imposed in exercise of a power conferred by regulations under this Part, including provision for enforcement by a specified public body (an “enforcer”).</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially affect the enforcement of data regulations, which could impact the protection of individuals' data rights.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially increase the powers of the Secretary of State or the Treasury in relation to the enforcement of data regulations, which could impact the balance of power within the government.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Customer data and business data</subject>
   <quote>(4) Information is within this subsection if it is information in respect of a communication which is made— (a) between a professional legal adviser and the adviser’s client or between such an adviser or client and another person, (b) in connection with or in contemplation of proceedings under or arising out of data regulations, and (c) for the purposes of such proceedings.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a provision that defines the scope of information that falls under this subsection. This includes information related to communications between a professional legal adviser and their client, or between such an adviser or client and another person, in connection with or in contemplation of proceedings under or arising out of data regulations.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Customer data and business data</subject>
   <quote>(6) Information is within this subsection if requiring a person to provide the information would, by revealing evidence of the commission of an offence, expose the person to proceedings for that offence.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a provision that defines the scope of information that falls under this subsection. This includes information that, if required to be provided, would expose a person to proceedings for an offence by revealing evidence of the commission of that offence.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Customer data and business data</subject>
   <quote>(8) An oral or written statement provided by a person in response to a request for information made by a decision-maker or an enforcer in accordance with regulations under this Part may not be used in evidence against that person on a prosecution for an offence (other than an offence under regulations made under this Part) unless in the proceedings— (a) in giving evidence the person provides information inconsistent with the statement, and (b) evidence relating to the statement is adduced, or a question relating to it is asked, by that person or on that person’s behalf.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a provision that restricts the use of an oral or written statement provided by a person in response to a request for information made by a decision-maker or an enforcer in accordance with regulations under this Part. Such a statement may not be used in evidence against that person on a prosecution for an offence, unless certain conditions are met.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Customer data and business data</subject>
   <quote>69 Financial penalties (1) This section is about provision that regulations under this Part conferring power on an enforcer to impose a financial penalty may or must (among other things) contain.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a provision that outlines the power of an enforcer to impose a financial penalty under regulations of this Part.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Customer data and business data</subject>
   <quote>70 Fees (1) The Secretary of State or the Treasury may by regulations— (a) make provision enabling a person listed in subsection (2), or a person acting on their behalf, to require other persons to pay fees for the purpose of meeting expenses incurred, or to be incurred, in performing duties, or exercising powers, imposed or conferred by regulations under this Part, and (b) make provision about how amounts paid as fees must or may be used.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a provision that allows the Secretary of State or the Treasury to make regulations enabling certain persons to require others to pay fees for the purpose of meeting expenses incurred in performing duties or exercising powers under this Part. It also provides for how these fees must or may be used.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Customer data and business data</subject>
   <quote>71 Levy (1) The Secretary of State or the Treasury may by regulations— (a) impose, or provide for a specified public body to impose, a levy on data holders for the purpose of meeting all or part of the expenses incurred, or to be incurred, during a period by decision-makers or enforcers or by persons acting on their behalf, and (b) make provision about how funds raised by means of the levy must or may be used.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a provision that allows the Secretary of State or the Treasury to make regulations imposing a levy on data holders for the purpose of meeting all or part of the expenses incurred by decision-makers or enforcers or by persons acting on their behalf. It also provides for how funds raised by means of the levy must or may be used.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Customer data and business data</subject>
   <quote>72 Financial assistance (1) The Secretary of State or the Treasury may give financial assistance to a person for the purpose of meeting any expenses incurred, or to be incurred, by the person in performing duties or exercising powers under, or in connection with, regulations made under this Part.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a provision that allows the Secretary of State or the Treasury to give financial assistance to a person for the purpose of meeting any expenses incurred in performing duties or exercising powers under regulations made under this Part.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Customer data and business data</subject>
   <quote>73 Confidentiality and data protection (1) Except as provided by subsection (2), regulations under this Part may provide for the processing of information in accordance with the regulations not to be in breach of— (a) any obligation of confidence owed by the person processing the information, or (b) any other restriction on the processing of information (however imposed).</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a provision that allows for the processing of information in accordance with regulations under this Part not to be in breach of any obligation of confidence owed by the person processing the information, or any other restriction on the processing of information.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Customer data and business data</subject>

   <quote>Regulations under this Part may (among other things)—
(a) make provision generally or in relation to particular cases;
(b) make different provision for different purposes or areas;
(c) make provision about the form and manner in which things must or may be done;
(d) make provision about the content of requests, notices or other documents;
(e) make provision about the time by which, or period within which, things must or may be done;
(f) make provision by reference to specifications or technical requirements published from time to time by a specified person;
(g) confer functions on a person, including functions involving the exercise of a discretion;
(h) make incidental, supplementary, consequential, transitory, transitional or saving provision.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces regulations that provide a framework for handling customer and business data. These regulations can be applied generally or to specific cases, and can be different for different purposes or areas. They also dictate the form and manner of actions, the content of requests, notices or other documents, and the timeframes for actions. The regulations can refer to specifications or technical requirements published by a specified person, and can confer functions on a person, including discretionary functions. They can also make incidental, supplementary, consequential, transitory, transitional or saving provisions.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The regulations provide a framework for handling customer and business data, which could have significant implications for digital privacy.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">The regulations could affect how tech companies handle customer and business data, potentially impacting their operations and responsibilities.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Customer data and business data</subject>

   <quote>Regulations under this Part making the following types of provision may amend or repeal primary legislation—
(a) provision about the handling of complaints;
(b) provision about the resolution of disputes;
(c) provision about appeals;
(d) provision described in subsection (1)(h).</quote>

   <summary>The bill allows for regulations under this part to amend or repeal primary legislation in relation to the handling of complaints, the resolution of disputes, appeals, and provisions described in subsection (1)(h).</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The ability to amend or repeal primary legislation could have significant implications for the justice system, particularly in relation to the handling of complaints, the resolution of disputes, and appeals.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Customer data and business data</subject>

   <quote>The relevant person must review data regulations for the time being in force—
(a) before the end of the period of 5 years beginning with the day on which the regulations come into force, and
(b) at subsequent intervals not exceeding 5 years.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a requirement for the relevant person to review data regulations currently in force before the end of a 5-year period starting from when the regulations come into force, and at subsequent intervals not exceeding 5 years.</summary>

   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The regular review of data regulations could help ensure that they remain relevant and effective in protecting digital privacy.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">The regular review of data regulations could impact tech companies by potentially leading to changes in the regulations they must comply with.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Customer data and business data</subject>

   <quote>Omit sections 89 to 91 of the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Act 2013 (supply of customer data).</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to omit sections 89 to 91 of the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Act 2013, which relate to the supply of customer data.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The omission of these sections could have significant implications for digital privacy, depending on what provisions they contained regarding the supply of customer data.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">The omission of these sections could affect tech companies by potentially removing certain regulations related to the supply of customer data.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulation 6(1)</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may by regulations made by statutory instrument—
(a) amend these regulations— 15
(i) by adding an exception to the prohibition in regulation
6(1), or
(ii) by omitting or varying an exception to that prohibition,
and
(b) make consequential, incidental or supplementary provision 20
amending these regulations.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to give the Secretary of State the power to amend regulations by adding, omitting, or varying exceptions to the prohibition in regulation 6(1). The Secretary of State can also make consequential, incidental, or supplementary provisions amending these regulations.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change gives significant power to the Secretary of State to amend regulations, potentially impacting how data protection laws are enforced.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulation 6B</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may by regulations made by statutory instrument
provide that a person of a specified description may supply, provide
or otherwise make available information technology of a specified
description only if the technology meets specified requirements.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to give the Secretary of State the power to regulate the supply, provision, or availability of certain types of information technology. This regulation would only apply if the technology meets certain requirements.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change gives the Secretary of State significant power to regulate the supply and provision of certain types of information technology, potentially impacting the tech industry and user privacy.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">This change could have significant impacts on tech companies, as it gives the Secretary of State the power to regulate the supply and provision of certain types of information technology.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Regulation 2 of the PEC Regulations</subject>
   <quote>in the definition of “call”, at the end insert “, and a reference to making
a call includes a reference to attempting to establish such a connection”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend the definition of "call" in Regulation 2 of the PEC Regulations to include attempts to establish a connection.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">This change could potentially impact digital privacy, as it expands the definition of a "call" to include attempts to establish a connection, potentially broadening the scope of data collection and monitoring.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulation 22 of the PEC Regulations (use of electronic mail for direct marketing purposes)</subject>

   <quote>(3A) A person may send or instigate the sending of electronic mail for the purposes of direct marketing where— (a) the direct marketing is solely for the purpose of furthering a charitable, political or other non-commercial objective of that person; (b) that person obtained the contact details of the recipient of the electronic mail in the course of the recipient expressing an interest in or offering or providing support for the furtherance of that objective or a similar objective; and (c) the recipient has been given a simple means of refusing (free of charge except for the costs of the transmission of the refusal) the use of their contact details for the purposes of such direct marketing, at the time that the details were initially collected, and, where the recipient did not initially refuse the use of the details, at the time of each subsequent communication.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes an insertion to the PEC Regulations that allows for the sending of electronic mail for direct marketing purposes under certain conditions. These conditions include the marketing being for a charitable, political, or non-commercial objective, the contact details of the recipient being obtained during their expression of interest or support for the objective, and the recipient being given a simple means of refusing the use of their contact details for such marketing.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change could potentially impact individuals' rights to privacy, as it allows for their contact details to be used for direct marketing purposes under certain conditions. However, it also includes safeguards such as the requirement for the recipient to be given a simple means of refusing the use of their contact details for such marketing.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially impact the ways in which political entities are able to engage in direct marketing, as it allows for the use of electronic mail for this purpose when it is for a political objective.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 83</subject>

   <quote>(1) The Secretary of State may by regulations provide an exception from a direct marketing provision for a case where communications activity— (a) is carried out for the purposes of democratic engagement, and (b) is not directed to individuals under the age of 14.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes an insertion that allows the Secretary of State to provide an exception from a direct marketing provision for communications activity carried out for the purposes of democratic engagement, as long as it is not directed to individuals under the age of 14.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change could potentially impact individuals' rights to privacy, as it allows for an exception from a direct marketing provision for communications activity carried out for the purposes of democratic engagement. However, it also includes a safeguard in that it cannot be directed to individuals under the age of 14.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially impact the ways in which political entities are able to engage in direct marketing, as it allows for an exception from a direct marketing provision for communications activity carried out for the purposes of democratic engagement.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>PEC Regulations</subject>

   <quote>“26A Duty to notify Commissioner of unlawful direct marketing
(1) A provider of a public electronic communications service must notify
the Commissioner of any reasonable grounds the provider has for
suspecting that a person is contravening or has contravened any of
the direct marketing regulations in the course of using the service.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a new duty for providers of public electronic communications services to notify the Commissioner if they suspect any contravention of direct marketing regulations.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">
      This change could potentially increase digital privacy by ensuring that violations of direct marketing regulations are reported and potentially addressed.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">
      This change imposes a new duty on tech companies providing public electronic communications services, potentially increasing their regulatory burden.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>PEC Regulations</subject>

   <quote>26B Fixed penalty for failure to comply with regulation 26A
(1) If a provider of a public electronic communications service or public
electronic communications network fails to comply with regulation
26A, the Commissioner may issue a fixed monetary penalty notice in
respect of the failure.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a new fixed monetary penalty for providers of public electronic communications services or networks who fail to comply with the new duty to notify the Commissioner of suspected contraventions of direct marketing regulations.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">
      This change could potentially increase the regulatory burden on tech companies by introducing a new penalty for non-compliance with the new duty to report suspected contraventions of direct marketing regulations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>PEC Regulations</subject>

   <quote>26C Guidance in relation to regulation 26A
(1) The Commissioner must produce and publish guidance about what may constitute reasonable grounds for suspecting that a person is contravening or has contravened any of the direct marketing regulations in the course of using a public electronic communications service or public electronic communications network.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that the Commissioner must produce and publish guidance on what may constitute reasonable grounds for suspecting contraventions of direct marketing regulations.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">
      This change could potentially provide clarity for tech companies on their new duty to report suspected contraventions of direct marketing regulations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Regulations 32 and 33</subject>
   <quote>In regulations 32 and 33, “enforcement functions” means the functions of the Information Commissioner under those provisions, as applied by that Schedule.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend regulations 32 and 33 to define "enforcement functions" as the functions of the Information Commissioner under those provisions.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Regulation 31A and 31B</subject>
   <quote>(6) Omit regulation 31A (third party information notices).
(7) Omit regulation 31B (appeals against third party information notices).</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to delete regulation 31A and 31B, which deal with third party information notices and appeals against them.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>substitution</type>
   <subject>Schedule 1</subject>
   <quote>(8) For Schedule 1 substitute the Schedule set out in Schedule 10.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to substitute Schedule 1 with the Schedule set out in Schedule 10.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Paragraph 58(1) of Schedule 20 to the 2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>(9) In paragraph 58(1) of Schedule 20 to the 2018 Act (transitional provision 15 relating to the PEC Regulations) for “regulations 2, 31 and 31B of, and Schedule 1 to,” substitute “regulation 2 of”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend paragraph 58(1) of Schedule 20 to the 2018 Act, replacing the reference to "regulations 2, 31 and 31B of, and Schedule 1 to," with "regulation 2 of".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>eIDAS Regulation</subject>
   <quote>In sections 88 to 91, “the eIDAS Regulation” means Regulation (EU) No. 20 910/2014 of the European Parliament and the Council of 23 July 2014 on electronic identification and trust services for electronic transactions in the internal market.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to insert a definition for "the eIDAS Regulation" in sections 88 to 91, referring to Regulation (EU) No. 910/2014 of the European Parliament and the Council of 23 July 2014 on electronic identification and trust services for electronic transactions in the internal market.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>eIDAS Regulation</subject>
   <quote>88 Recognition of EU conformity assessment bodies
In Chapter 3 of the eIDAS Regulation (trust services), after Article 24A insert— 25
“Article 24B
Recognition of EU conformity assessment bodies
For the purposes of Articles 20(1), 21 and 24(1)(d), a body is to
30
be treated as if it were a conformity assessment body in relation
to a description of trust services provider (and trust service) if
it is a conformity assessment body in relation to that description
of provider (and service) for the purposes of the equivalent EU
law.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend the eIDAS Regulation to include a new Article 24B, which provides for the recognition of EU conformity assessment bodies for the purposes of Articles 20(1), 21 and 24(1)(d).</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>eIDAS Regulation</subject>
   <quote>89 Removal of recognition of EU standards etc
(1) The Secretary of State may by regulations— 35
114 Data Protection and Digital Information (No. 2) Bill
Part 4—Other provision about digital information 
(a) amend Article 24A of the eIDAS Regulation (recognition of EU
standards etc for qualified trust services) so as to remove circumstances
in which something is to be treated as qualified under that Regulation
5
for the purposes of a provision or measure specified in paragraph 1
of that Article;
(b) revoke that Article;
(c) revoke Article 24B of the eIDAS Regulation (recognition of EU
conformity assessment bodies);
(d)
10
revoke Article 51 of the eIDAS Regulation (transitional measures for
electronic signatures);
(e) amend a provision listed in subsection (3) so as to remove a reference
to a trust service provider established in the EU;
(f) amend a provision listed in subsection (4) so as to remove a reference
to European standards or provisions of equivalent EU law.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend the eIDAS Regulation to allow the Secretary of State to remove recognition of EU standards and conformity assessment bodies, revoke certain articles, and remove references to trust service providers established in the EU and to European standards or equivalent EU law.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>RED</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>eIDAS Regulation</subject>
   <quote>90 Recognition of overseas trust products
(1) The eIDAS Regulation is amended as follows.
Data Protection and Digital Information (No. 2) Bill 115
Part 4—Other provision about digital information 
(2) In Chapter 3 of the eIDAS Regulation, after Article 45 insert—
“Section 9
Recognition of overseas trust services
Article 45A
Legal effects of overseas electronic signatures etc 5
1. The Secretary of State may by regulations provide that, for the
purposes of Articles 25(2), 35(2), 41(2) and 43(2), an overseas trust
product of a specified description is to be treated as qualified.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend the eIDAS Regulation to allow the Secretary of State to provide by regulations that an overseas trust product of a specified description is to be treated as qualified for the purposes of certain articles.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>eIDAS Regulation</subject>
   <quote>91 Co-operation between supervisory authority and overseas authorities
(1) Article 18 of the eIDAS Regulation (co-operation with EU authorities) is
amended as follows.
(2) In the heading, for “EU” substitute “overseas”.
(3) In paragraph 1, for “public authority in the EU” substitute “designated 10
overseas authority”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Article 18 of the eIDAS Regulation to replace references to "EU" and "public authority in the EU" with "overseas" and "designated overseas authority", respectively.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 35 of the Digital Economy Act 2017</subject>
   <quote>(1) Section 35 of the Digital Economy Act 2017 (disclosure of information to improve public service delivery) is amended as follows.
(2) In subsection (9)—
(a) in paragraph (a), for “or households” substitute “, households or 35
undertakings”, and
118 Data Protection and Digital Information (No. 2) Bill
Part 4—Other provision about digital information 
(b) in paragraph (b), for “or households” substitute “, households or
undertakings”.
(3) In subsection (10)—
(a) the words after “its purpose” become paragraph (a), and
(b) at the end of that paragraph, insert “, or 5
(b) the assisting of undertakings in connection with any
trade, business or charitable purpose.”
(4) After subsection (12) insert—
“(13) In this section “undertaking” means—
(a) any person, other than a public authority, carrying on a trade 10
or business, whether or not with a view to profit, or
(b) any body, or the trustees of a trust, established for charitable
purposes only.</quote>
   <summary>The amendment expands the scope of Section 35 of the Digital Economy Act 2017 to include "undertakings" in the disclosure of information to improve public service delivery. Undertakings are defined as any person, other than a public authority, carrying on a trade or business, or any body or trustees of a trust established for charitable purposes only.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This amendment could potentially impact businesses and charities by allowing them to receive disclosed information to improve public service delivery.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Implementation of law enforcement information-sharing agreements</subject>
   <quote>93 Implementation of law enforcement information-sharing agreements
(1) The Secretary of State may by regulations make such provision as the Secretary
20
of State considers appropriate for the purpose of, or in connection with,
implementing an international agreement so far as relating to the sharing of
information for law enforcement purposes, as it has effect from time to time.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a provision that allows the Secretary of State to make regulations for implementing international agreements related to the sharing of information for law enforcement purposes.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security">This provision could potentially enhance the UK's ability to cooperate with international law enforcement agencies, thereby strengthening national security.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>The Births and Deaths Registration Act 1953</subject>
   <quote>(1) The Births and Deaths Registration Act 1953 is amended as follows.
(2) For section 25 (provision of registers, etc, by Registrar General) substitute— 10
“25 Form in which registers are to be kept, etc
(1) Registers of live-births, still-births and deaths must be kept in such
form as the Registrar General may reasonably require.</quote>
   <summary>The amendment changes the Births and Deaths Registration Act 1953 to allow the Registrar General to determine the form in which registers of live-births, still-births, and deaths are kept.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Public Health">This amendment could potentially impact public health by changing the way birth and death records are kept and accessed.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 39A (regulations made by the Minister: further provisions)</subject>
   <quote>In section 39A (regulations made by the Minister: further provisions), after
subsection (5) insert—
“(6) A statutory instrument that contains (whether alone or with other
5
provision) regulations made by the Minister under section 38B may
not be made unless a draft of the instrument has been laid before, and
approved by a resolution of, each House of Parliament.”</quote>
   <summary>The amendment requires that any statutory instrument containing regulations made by the Minister under section 38B must be laid before and approved by a resolution of each House of Parliament before it can be made.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>repeal</type>
   <subject>Section 28 of the Births and Deaths Registration Act 1953</subject>
   <quote>The repeal of section 28 of the Births and Deaths Registration Act 1953 by
section 94 above does not affect—</quote>
   <summary>Section 28 of the Births and Deaths Registration Act 1953 is repealed, but the requirements under section 28(2) and 28(4) of that Act are not affected by the repeal.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>establishment</type>
   <subject>The Information Commission</subject>
   <quote>A body corporate called the Information Commission is established.</quote>
   <summary>The bill establishes a new body corporate called the Information Commission.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>abolition</type>
   <subject>The office of Information Commissioner</subject>
   <quote>The office of Information Commissioner is abolished.</quote>
   <summary>The bill abolishes the office of the Information Commissioner.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>RED</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>transfer</type>
   <subject>Functions of the Information Commissioner</subject>
   <quote>The functions of the Information Commissioner are transferred to the
Information Commission.</quote>
   <summary>The bill transfers the functions of the Information Commissioner to the newly established Information Commission.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>abolition</type>
   <subject>The office of Commissioner for the Retention and Use of Biometric Material</subject>
   <quote>The office of Commissioner for the Retention and Use of Biometric Material is abolished.</quote>
   <summary>The bill abolishes the office of Commissioner for the Retention and Use of Biometric Material.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>RED</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 20</subject>
   <quote>For the heading before section 20 substitute “Functions of the Investigatory Powers Commissioner”.</quote>
   <quote>In section 20 (appointment and functions of the Commissioner for the Retention and Use of Biometric Material)— (a) in the heading, omit “Appointment and”, (b) omit subsection (1), (c) after that subsection insert— 15 “(1A) In this section, “the Commissioner” means the Investigatory Powers Commissioner (as defined in section 263(1) of the Investigatory Powers Act 2016).”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 20 to change the title of the Commissioner for the Retention and Use of Biometric Material to the Investigatory Powers Commissioner.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Section 21</subject>
   <quote>Omit section 21 (reports by Commissioner).</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to delete Section 21, which pertains to reports by the Commissioner.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 22</subject>
   <quote>In section 22 (guidance on making national security determinations)— (a) in subsection (4)— (i) for “the guidance, or revising guidance already given” substitute “guidance or revised guidance under this section”, and (ii) for “Commissioner for the Retention and Use of Biometric Material” substitute “Investigatory Powers Commissioner”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 22 to replace references to the Commissioner for the Retention and Use of Biometric Material with the Investigatory Powers Commissioner.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Office of Surveillance Camera Commissioner</subject>
   <quote>The office of Surveillance Camera Commissioner is abolished.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to abolish the office of the Surveillance Camera Commissioner.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>RED</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 63AB of the Police and Criminal Evidence Act 1984</subject>
   <quote>Section 63AB of the Police and Criminal Evidence Act 1984 (National DNA Database Strategy Board) is amended as follows. (2) For the heading substitute “Oversight of biometrics databases”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 63AB of the Police and Criminal Evidence Act 1984 to change the title of the National DNA Database Strategy Board to the Oversight of Biometrics Databases.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 5—Regulation and oversight</subject>
   <quote>“biometric data” means personal data resulting from specific 5
technical processing relating to the physical, physiological or
behavioural characteristics of an individual, which allows or
confirms the unique identification of that individual, such as
facial images or dactyloscopic data;</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a definition for "biometric data", which is described as personal data that results from specific technical processing related to the physical, physiological, or behavioural characteristics of an individual. This data allows or confirms the unique identification of that individual.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">The definition of biometric data could have significant implications for privacy and data protection rights, as it includes sensitive information such as facial images.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">This definition is crucial for setting the scope of data protection and privacy laws, particularly in relation to emerging technologies such as facial recognition.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 6—Final provisions</subject>
   <quote>107 Power to make consequential amendments
(1) The Secretary of State may by regulations make provision that is consequential 15
on any provision made by this Act.</quote>
   <summary>The bill grants the Secretary of State the power to make regulations that are consequential on any provision made by this Act.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This provision grants significant power to the Secretary of State, allowing them to make consequential amendments to regulations based on the provisions of this Act.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 6—Final provisions</subject>
   <quote>110 Financial provision 20
There is to be paid out of money provided by Parliament—
(a) any expenditure incurred under or by virtue of this Act by the Secretary of
State, the Treasury or a government department, and
(b)
25
any increase attributable to this Act in the sums payable under any other
Act out of money so provided.</quote>
   <summary>The bill provides for any expenditure incurred under this Act by the Secretary of State, the Treasury, or a government department to be paid out of money provided by Parliament. It also covers any increase attributable to this Act in the sums payable under any other Act out of money so provided.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This provision has implications for public spending, as it commits Parliament to cover any expenditure or increased costs resulting from this Act.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Processing of data for democratic engagement</subject>

   <quote>For the purposes of paragraph 9, processing is carried out for the purposes of democratic engagement if— (a) the processing— (i) is carried out by an elected representative or a person acting with the authority of such a representative, and (ii) is necessary for the purposes of discharging the elected representative’s functions or for the purposes of the elected representative’s democratic engagement activities...</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces provisions for the processing of personal data for the purposes of democratic engagement. This includes processing carried out by elected representatives, candidates for election, permitted participants in a referendum, and accredited campaigners in relation to a recall petition. The processing must be necessary for the discharge of the representative's functions or for democratic engagement activities.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">The change could potentially increase the power of elected representatives and other political actors by allowing them to process personal data for the purposes of democratic engagement. This could enhance their ability to engage with constituents and campaign effectively.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">The change could potentially impact the right to privacy, depending on how the data is processed and used. However, the bill specifies that the processing must be necessary for democratic engagement activities, which could mitigate potential privacy concerns.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Purpose limitation: Processing to be treated as compatible with original purpose</subject>

   <quote>PURPOSE LIMITATION: PROCESSING TO BE TREATED AS COMPATIBLE WITH ORIGINAL PURPOSE In the UK GDPR, after Annex 1 (inserted by Schedule 1 to this Act) insert— “ANNEX 2 PURPOSE LIMITATION: PROCESSING TO BE TREATED AS COMPATIBLE WITH ORIGINAL PURPOSE...</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a new annex to the UK GDPR, which provides for certain types of processing to be treated as compatible with the original purpose of data collection. This includes processing necessary for public security, responding to emergencies, detecting or preventing crime, protecting vital interests of data subjects, and safeguarding vulnerable individuals.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">The change could potentially impact the right to privacy, as it allows for certain types of processing to be treated as compatible with the original purpose of data collection. However, the bill specifies that the processing must be necessary for certain purposes, such as public security or safeguarding vulnerable individuals, which could mitigate potential privacy concerns.</pillar>
     <pillar type="National Security">The change could potentially enhance national security by allowing for processing necessary for public security and responding to emergencies.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Paragraph 7</subject>
   <quote>“safeguarding”, in relation to vulnerable individual, means —
(a) protecting a vulnerable individual from neglect or physical, mental 10
or emotional harm, or
(b) protecting the physical, mental or emotional well-being of a
vulnerable individual;
“vulnerable individual” means an individual—
(a) aged under 18, or 15
(b) aged 18 or over and at risk.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces definitions for "safeguarding" and "vulnerable individual". Safeguarding refers to protecting a vulnerable individual from neglect or harm, or protecting their well-being. A vulnerable individual is defined as someone under 18 or someone 18 or over who is at risk.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change could potentially enhance the protection of vulnerable individuals, particularly minors and adults at risk, by providing a clear definition for safeguarding measures.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Article 12 of the UK GDPR</subject>
   <quote>In paragraph 1, for “under Articles 15 to 22” substitute “made under or by
virtue of Articles 15 to 22D”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to Article 12 of the UK GDPR, changing the reference from "under Articles 15 to 22" to "made under or by virtue of Articles 15 to 22D".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">This change could potentially affect the transparency of information, communication, and modalities for the exercise of the rights of the data subject.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Article 4(1) of the UK GDPR</subject>
   <quote>In Article 4(1) (definitions), after point (11) insert—
“(11A) “senior responsible individual” means an individual designated as
the senior responsible individual of a controller or processor under
Article 27A;”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new definition for "senior responsible individual" in Article 4(1) of the UK GDPR. This term refers to an individual designated as the senior responsible individual of a controller or processor under Article 27A.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">This change could potentially enhance accountability and responsibility in data processing activities by introducing a designated senior responsible individual.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>substitution</type>
   <subject>Section 67(4)(b), Section 68(2)(b), Section 134, Section 135(1)</subject>
   <quote>In section 67(4)(b) (notification of a personal data breach to the Commissioner), for “data protection officer” substitute “senior responsible individual”.</quote>
   <quote>In section 68(2)(b) (communication of a personal data breach to the data subject), for “data protection officer” substitute “senior responsible individual”.</quote>
   <quote>Section 134 (Commissioner’s power to charge fees for services) is amended as follows. (1) (2) The existing text becomes subsection (1). (3) In that subsection, for “data protection officer” substitute “senior responsible individual”.</quote>
   <quote>In section 135(1) (manifestly unfounded or excessive requests by data subject etc), for “data protection officer” substitute “senior responsible individual”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to replace the term "data protection officer" with "senior responsible individual" in several sections of the existing legislation.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Chapter 5 of the UK GDPR</subject>
   <quote>Chapter 5 of the UK GDPR (transfers of personal data to third countries or international organisations) is amended as follows.</quote>
   <quote>Omit Article 44 (transfers of personal data to third countries etc: general principles for transfers).</quote>
   <quote>After that Article insert— “Article 44A General principles for transfers</quote>
   <quote>Omit Article 45 (transfers on the basis of an adequacy decision).</quote>
   <quote>After that Article insert— “Article 45A Transfers approved by regulations</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Chapter 5 of the UK GDPR, which deals with transfers of personal data to third countries or international organisations. It suggests omitting Article 44 and 45 and inserting new Articles 44A and 45A, which provide new general principles for transfers and regulations for approved transfers, respectively.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="National Security"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Article 45A</subject>
   <quote>Where the Secretary of State becomes aware that the data protection test is no longer met in relation to transfers approved, or of a description approved, in regulations under Article 45A, the Secretary of State must, to the extent necessary, amend or revoke the regulations.</quote>
   <summary>The Secretary of State is given the power to amend or revoke regulations under Article 45A if the data protection test is no longer met in relation to approved transfers.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change gives the Secretary of State significant power to amend or revoke regulations related to data transfers, potentially impacting the operations of businesses and organizations that rely on such transfers.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The amendment could potentially improve data privacy if it leads to stricter regulations when the data protection test is not met. However, it could also lead to less privacy if regulations are loosened.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Article 46</subject>
   <quote>A transfer of personal data to a third country or an international organisation by a controller or processor is made subject to appropriate safeguards only— (a) in a case in which— (i) safeguards are provided in connection with the transfer as described in paragraph 2 or 3 or regulations made under Article 47A(4), and (ii) the controller or processor, acting reasonably and proportionately, considers that the data protection test is met in relation to the transfer or that type of transfer (see paragraph 6), or (b) in a case in which— (i) safeguards are provided in accordance with paragraph 2(a) by an instrument that is intended to be relied on in connection with the transfer or that type of transfer, and (ii) each public body that is a party to the instrument, acting reasonably and proportionately, considers that the data protection test is met in relation to the transfers, or types of transfer, intended to be made in reliance on the instrument (see paragraph 6).</quote>
   <summary>The bill amends Article 46 to specify the conditions under which a transfer of personal data to a third country or international organization is subject to appropriate safeguards. These conditions include the provision of safeguards in connection with the transfer and the consideration by the controller or processor that the data protection test is met.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">This amendment could potentially improve data privacy by specifying the conditions under which data transfers are subject to appropriate safeguards.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">The amendment gives significant power to controllers, processors, and public bodies to determine whether the data protection test is met.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Article 47A</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may by regulations specify standard data protection clauses which the Secretary of State considers are capable of securing that the data protection test set out in Article 46 is met in relation to transfers of personal data generally or in relation to a type of transfer specified in the regulations.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces Article 47A, which allows the Secretary of State to specify standard data protection clauses by regulations. These clauses should be capable of securing that the data protection test set out in Article 46 is met.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change gives the Secretary of State significant power to specify standard data protection clauses, potentially impacting the operations of businesses and organizations that rely on data transfers.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The insertion could potentially improve data privacy by allowing for the specification of standard data protection clauses.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Article 49A</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State may by regulations restrict the transfer of a category of personal data to a third country or international organisation where— (a) the transfer is not approved by regulations under Article 45A for the time being in force, and (b) the Secretary of State considers the restriction to be necessary for important reasons of public interest.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of Article 49A, which gives the Secretary of State the power to restrict the transfer of a category of personal data to a third country or international organisation for reasons of public interest.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security">This change could potentially enhance national security by preventing the transfer of sensitive personal data to foreign entities.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change could potentially impact human rights, particularly the right to privacy, depending on how the Secretary of State exercises this power.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">This change directly impacts digital privacy by providing a mechanism to restrict the transfer of personal data.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 73 (general principles for transfers)</subject>

   <quote>(2) In subsection (1)— (a) for “may not” substitute “may”, (b) for “unless” substitute “for a law enforcement purpose only if”, (c) omit paragraph (b) (and the “and” before it), and (d) after that paragraph insert— “(c) the transfer is carried out in accordance with the other provisions of this Part, and (d) in a relevant restricted transfer case, the overseas authoriser has authorised the transfer or subsection (5) applies.”</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to Section 73, changing the conditions under which personal data may be transferred for law enforcement purposes. The transfer must now be carried out in accordance with other provisions of this Part, and in a relevant restricted transfer case, the overseas authoriser must have authorised the transfer.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security">This change could potentially enhance national security by ensuring that personal data transfers for law enforcement purposes are carried out under stricter conditions.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change could potentially impact human rights, particularly the right to privacy, depending on how these conditions are applied.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">This change directly impacts digital privacy by tightening the conditions under which personal data may be transferred for law enforcement purposes.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 74AA</subject>

   <quote>For the purposes of section 73, the Secretary of State may by regulations approve transfers of personal data to— (a) a third country, or (b) an international organisation.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of Section 74AA, which gives the Secretary of State the power to approve transfers of personal data to a third country or international organisation by regulations.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security">This change could potentially enhance national security by providing a mechanism for the Secretary of State to control the transfer of personal data to foreign entities.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change could potentially impact human rights, particularly the right to privacy, depending on how the Secretary of State exercises this power.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">This change directly impacts digital privacy by providing a mechanism for the Secretary of State to control the transfer of personal data.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 74B (transfers based on adequacy regulations: review etc)</subject>
   <quote>For the heading substitute “Transfers approved by regulations: monitoring”.</quote>
   <quote>Omit subsections (1) and (2).</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (3), for “under section 74A” substitute “giving approval under section 74AA”.</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (4), for the words from the beginning to “otherwise,” substitute “Where the Secretary of State becomes aware that the data protection test is no longer met in relation to transfers to approved, or of a description approved, in regulations under section 74AA,”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to Section 74B, changing its title to "Transfers approved by regulations: monitoring" and omitting subsections (1) and (2). It also proposes changes to subsections (3) and (4) to refer to section 74AA instead of 74A, indicating a shift in the approval process for data transfers.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The proposed changes could potentially affect the process and standards for transferring personal data to third countries or international organisations, impacting digital privacy.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 75 (transfers on the basis of appropriate safeguards)</subject>
   <quote>In the heading, for “on the basis of” substitute “subject to”.</quote>
   <quote>Omit subsection (1).</quote>
   <quote>After that subsection insert—“(1A) A transfer of personal data to a third country or an international organisation is made subject to appropriate safeguards only if—(a) the controller, acting reasonably and proportionately, considers that the data protection test is met in relation to the transfer or that type of transfer (see subsection (5)), or (b) an appropriate legal instrument binds the intended recipient of the data (see subsection (4)).”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to Section 75, changing its title to "Transfers subject to appropriate safeguards" and omitting subsection (1). It also proposes a new subsection (1A) that outlines conditions under which a transfer of personal data to a third country or an international organisation is made subject to appropriate safeguards.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The proposed changes could potentially affect the safeguards for transferring personal data to third countries or international organisations, impacting digital privacy.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 76 (transfers on the basis of special circumstances)</subject>
   <quote>In the heading, for “on the basis of” substitute “based on”.</quote>
   <quote>Before subsection (1) insert—“(A1) A transfer of personal data to a third country or international organisation is based on special circumstances where—(a) it is made in the absence of approval by regulations under section 74AA and of compliance with section 75 (appropriate safeguards), and (b) it is necessary for a special purpose.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to Section 76, changing its title to "Transfers based on special circumstances" and inserting a new subsection (A1) that outlines conditions under which a transfer of personal data to a third country or an international organisation is based on special circumstances.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The proposed changes could potentially affect the conditions under which personal data can be transferred to third countries or international organisations under special circumstances, impacting digital privacy.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 78 (subsequent transfers)</subject>
   <quote>In subsection (1)—(a) after “transfer” insert “—(a)”, and (b) at the end insert “(the “UK authoriser”), or (b) (subject to subsection (4)) that—(i) the data is not to be so transferred without such authorisation except where subsection (1A) applies, and (ii) where a transfer is made without such authorisation, the UK authoriser must be informed without delay.”</quote>
   <quote>After subsection (1) insert—“(1A) This subsection applies if— (a) the transfer is necessary for the prevention of an immediate and serious threat to the public security or national security of a third country or the United Kingdom, and (b) authorisation from the UK authoriser cannot be obtained in good time.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to Section 78, inserting new provisions in subsection (1) and a new subsection (1A) that outline conditions under which a subsequent transfer of personal data can be made without authorisation from the UK authoriser.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The proposed changes could potentially affect the conditions under which subsequent transfers of personal data can be made, impacting digital privacy.</pillar>
     <pillar type="National Security">The proposed changes could potentially affect the conditions under which personal data can be transferred in the event of an immediate and serious threat to public or national security.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Subsection (4)</subject>
   <quote>(6) For subsection (4) substitute—
“(4) In a relevant restricted transfer case— 25
(a) the transferring controller must make the transfer subject to
the condition described in subsection (1)(a), and
(b) the UK authoriser may not authorise a further transfer of
30
personal data under subsection (1)(a) unless the overseas
authoriser has authorised the further transfer or subsection
(5) applies.”</quote>
   <summary>The amendment modifies the conditions under which a transferring controller can make a transfer in a relevant restricted transfer case. It also restricts the UK authoriser from authorising a further transfer of personal data unless the overseas authoriser has authorised the further transfer or subsection (5) applies.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">This amendment could potentially increase the protection of personal data during transfers, as it adds an additional layer of authorisation from the overseas authoriser.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Subsection (5)</subject>
   <quote>(7) In subsection (5)—
(a) for the words before paragraph (a) substitute “This subsection
applies if—”,
(b) in paragraph (a), for the words from “either” to “State” substitute 35
“to the public security, national security or essential interests of a
third country or the United Kingdom”, and
(c) in paragraph (b), for “the authorisation” substitute “authorisation
from the overseas authoriser”.</quote>
   <summary>The amendment modifies the conditions under which subsection (5) applies, and changes the criteria in paragraph (a) and (b) to include public security, national security or essential interests of a third country or the United Kingdom, and authorisation from the overseas authoriser.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">This amendment could potentially increase the protection of personal data during transfers, as it adds an additional layer of authorisation from the overseas authoriser and includes national security interests.</pillar>
     <pillar type="National Security">The inclusion of national security interests in the criteria could potentially increase the security of personal data during transfers.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Subsection (6)</subject>
   <quote>(8) In subsection (6)— 40
Data Protection and Digital Information (No. 2) Bill 159
Schedule 6—Transfers of personal data to third countries etc: law enforcement processing 
(a) for “without the authorisation” substitute “in a relevant restricted
transfer case without the authorisation from the overseas authoriser”,
and
(b)
5
for the words from “(4)” to “the transfer” substitute “(4)(b), the
overseas authoriser”.</quote>
   <summary>The amendment modifies the conditions under which a transfer can be made in a relevant restricted transfer case in subsection (6), requiring authorisation from the overseas authoriser.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">This amendment could potentially increase the protection of personal data during transfers, as it adds an additional layer of authorisation from the overseas authoriser.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Schedule 7—Transfers of personal data to third countries etc: consequential and transitional provision</subject>

   <quote>Regulations made under section 17A of the 2018 Act (transfers based on adequacy regulations) and in force immediately before the relevant day are to be treated, on and after that day, as if made under Article 45A of the UK GDPR (inserted by Schedule 5 to this Act).</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to treat regulations made under section 17A of the 2018 Act as if they were made under Article 45A of the UK GDPR. This change seems to be a part of a larger shift in the regulatory framework for data transfers.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">
      This change could potentially affect the privacy of individuals' data during transfers to third countries. The impact would depend on the specifics of Article 45A of the UK GDPR.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">
      Tech companies that transfer data to third countries would need to comply with the new regulatory framework, which could affect their operations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Schedule 7—Transfers of personal data to third countries etc: consequential and transitional provision</subject>

   <quote>For the purposes of Article 44A(1)(a) and (2)(b) of the UK GDPR (general principles for transfers of personal data), a transfer of personal data to a third country or an international organisation made on or after the relevant day is made subject to appropriate safeguards where— (a) the transfer is made under arrangements entered into before the relevant day, (b) safeguards are provided in accordance with paragraph 2 or 3 of Article 46 of the UK GDPR or paragraph 9 of Schedule 21 to the 2018 Act, and (c) if the transfer had been made immediately before the relevant day, it would have satisfied— (i) the condition in Article 46(1) of the UK GDPR relating to data subjects’ rights and legal remedies, and (ii) the requirements of the last sentence of Article 44 of the UK GDPR (level of protection must not be undermined).</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes new conditions for transfers of personal data to third countries or international organisations. These conditions include the transfer being made under arrangements entered into before a certain day, safeguards being provided in accordance with certain articles of the UK GDPR or the 2018 Act, and the transfer satisfying certain conditions if it had been made immediately before a certain day.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">
      This change could potentially affect the privacy of individuals' data during transfers to third countries. The impact would depend on the specifics of the new conditions.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">
      Tech companies that transfer data to third countries would need to comply with the new conditions, which could affect their operations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Part 3 of the 2018 Act (law enforcement processing): transfers subject to appropriate safeguards</subject>

   <quote>For the purposes of section 73(3) of the 2018 Act (general principles for transfers of personal data), a transfer of personal data to a third country or an international organisation made on or after the relevant day is a transfer made subject to appropriate safeguards where—
(a) an appropriate pre-commencement legal instrument binds the intended recipient of the data, and
(b) if the transfer had been made immediately before the relevant day, it would have been a transfer based on there being appropriate safeguards by virtue of that instrument and section 75(1)(a) of the 2018 Act.</quote>

   <summary>The amendment clarifies the conditions under which a transfer of personal data to a third country or international organisation is considered to be made subject to appropriate safeguards. These conditions include the existence of a binding legal instrument and the fact that the transfer would have been considered safe under the previous law.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">The amendment provides additional safeguards for the transfer of personal data, potentially enhancing the protection of individuals' privacy rights.</pillar>
     <pillar type="National Security">The amendment could impact how law enforcement agencies transfer data internationally, potentially affecting national security operations.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The amendment directly relates to the protection of personal data during international transfers, a key aspect of digital privacy.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>The UK GDPR</subject>

   <quote>The UK GDPR is amended as follows.
2 In Article 12(4) (transparent information, communication and modalities for the exercise of the rights of the data subject), for “lodging a complaint with the Commissioner” substitute “making a complaint to the controller under section 164A of the 2018 Act, making a complaint to the Commissioner under section 165 of that Act”.</quote>

   <summary>The amendment changes the process for lodging a complaint under the UK GDPR. Instead of lodging a complaint with the Commissioner, individuals will now make a complaint to the controller under section 164A of the 2018 Act or to the Commissioner under section 165 of that Act.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">The amendment changes the process for individuals to exercise their right to lodge a complaint, potentially affecting their ability to seek redress for violations of their privacy rights.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The amendment directly relates to the process for lodging complaints under the UK GDPR, a key aspect of digital privacy.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 135 (manifestly unfounded or excessive requests by data subjects)</subject>
   <quote>In section 135 (manifestly unfounded or excessive requests by data subjects), after subsection (5) (inserted by section 32 of this Act), insert— “(6) In this section, “request” does not include a complaint under section 165.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 135 by specifying that a "request" does not include a complaint under section 165.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 149 (enforcement notices)</subject>
   <quote>Section 149 (enforcement notices) is amended as follows. (2) In subsection (1), for “or (5)” substitute “, (5) or (5A)”. (3) After subsection (5) insert— “(5A) The fifth type of failure is where a controller has failed, or is failing, to comply with section 164A or with regulations under section 164B.” (4) In subsection (6), for “or (5)” substitute “, (5) or (5A)”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 149 by adding a new type of failure where a controller has failed, or is failing, to comply with section 164A or with regulations under section 164B.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 155 (penalty notices)</subject>
   <quote>In section 155 (penalty notices), in subsection (1)(a), for “or (5)” substitute “, (5) or (5A)”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 155 by changing the reference in subsection (1)(a) from "or (5)" to ", (5) or (5A)".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 157 (maximum amount of penalty)</subject>
   <quote>In section 157 (maximum amount of penalty), after subsection (4) insert— “(4A) In relation to an infringement of section 164A or of regulations under section 164B, the maximum amount of the penalty that may be imposed by a penalty notice is the standard maximum amount.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 157 by specifying that the maximum penalty for an infringement of section 164A or regulations under section 164B is the standard maximum amount.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 165 (complaints by data subjects)</subject>
   <quote>In section 165 (complaints by data subjects), in the heading, at the end insert “to the Commissioner”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend the heading of Section 165 to specify that complaints by data subjects are directed to the Commissioner.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 166 (orders to progress complaints)</subject>
   <quote>Section 166 (orders to progress complaints) is amended as follows. (2) In the heading, at the end insert “to the Commissioner”. (3) In subsection (1), omit “or Article 77 of the UK GDPR”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 166 by specifying in the heading that orders to progress complaints are directed to the Commissioner and by omitting the reference to "Article 77 of the UK GDPR" in subsection (1).</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 187 (representation of data subjects with their authority)</subject>
   <quote>Section 187 (representation of data subjects with their authority) is amended as follows. (2) In subsection (1)(a)— (a) for “Articles 77,” substitute “sections 164A and 165 (complaints) and Articles”, and (b) omit “to lodge complaints and”. (3) In subsection (2)— (a) before paragraph (a) insert— “(za) the right under section 164A (complaints to the controller);”, and (b) in paragraph (a), for “165(2) and (4)(d)” substitute “165”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 187 by changing the references in subsections (1)(a) and (2) to specify the right under section 164A (complaints to the controller) and to substitute "165(2) and (4)(d)" with "165".</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 204A (vexatious or excessive)</subject>
   <quote>Section 204A (vexatious or excessive) (inserted by section 7 of this Act) is amended as follows. (2) After subsection (1) insert— “(1A) For the purposes of this Act, whether a complaint to the Commissioner is vexatious or excessive must be determined having regard to the circumstances of the complaint, including (so far as relevant)— (a) the nature of the complaint, (b) the complainant’s relationship with the person who is the subject of the complaint (“the subject”) and the Commissioner, (c) the resources available to the Commissioner, (d) the extent to which the complaint repeats a previous complaint made by the complainant to the subject or the Commissioner, (e) how long ago any previous complaint was made, and (f) whether the complaint overlaps with other complaints made by the complainant to the subject or the Commissioner.” (3) In subsection (2), after “requests”, in both places it occurs, insert “and complaints”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 204A by adding a new subsection (1A) that provides criteria for determining whether a complaint to the Commissioner is vexatious or excessive. It also proposes to amend subsection (2) to include "and complaints" after "requests".</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>The UK GDPR</subject>
   <quote>The UK GDPR is amended as follows. 2 (1) Article 4(1) (interpretation) is amended as follows. (2) After point (A3) insert— “(A4) “the data protection legislation” has the same meaning as in the 2018 Act (see section 3(9) of that Act);”. (3) After point (15) insert— “(15A) “direct marketing” means the communication (by whatever means) of advertising or marketing material which is directed to particular individuals;”. (4) After point (28) insert— “(29) “enactment” has the same meaning as in the 2018 Act (see section 205 of that Act); (30) “tribunal” means any tribunal in which legal proceedings may be brought.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend the UK GDPR by adding new definitions for "the data protection legislation", "direct marketing", "enactment", and "tribunal".</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Article 9 (processing of special categories of personal data)</subject>
   <quote>In Article 9 (processing of special categories of personal data)— (a) in paragraph 2, after “apply if” insert “the processing is based on Article 6(1) and”, (b) in paragraph 2(f), after “courts” insert “or tribunals”, and (c) in paragraph 3, for the words from the beginning to “data are” substitute “Paragraph 1 is only disapplied by point (h) of paragraph 2 if the personal data is”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Article 9 by specifying that the processing is based on Article 6(1), adding "or tribunals" after "courts", and changing the wording in paragraph 3.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Article 12(5) (information etc to be provided free of charge)</subject>
   <quote>In Article 12(5) (information etc to be provided free of charge), at the beginning insert “Subject to Article 15(3),”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Article 12(5) by adding "Subject to Article 15(3)," at the beginning.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Article 23(1)(h) (restrictions)</subject>
   <quote>In Article 23(1)(h) (restrictions), for “(a)” substitute “(c)”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Article 23(1)(h) by changing the reference from "(a)" to "(c)".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Article 24(3) (responsibility of the controller)</subject>
   <quote>In Article 24(3) (responsibility of the controller), for “an element by which to demonstrate” substitute “a means of demonstrating”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Article 24(3) by changing the phrase "an element by which to demonstrate" to "a means of demonstrating".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Article 25(3) (data protection by design and by default)</subject>
   <quote>In Article 25(3) (data protection by design and by default), for “an element to demonstrate” substitute “a means of demonstrating”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Article 25(3) by changing the phrase "an element to demonstrate" to "a means of demonstrating".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Article 28(5) (processors)</subject>
   <quote>In Article 28(5) (processors), for “an element by which to demonstrate” substitute “a means of demonstrating”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Article 28(5) by changing the phrase "an element by which to demonstrate" to "a means of demonstrating".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>paragraph 14(1)(b) (preventing fraud)</subject>
   <quote>In paragraph 14(1)(b) (preventing fraud), after sub-paragraph (ii) (but before the “or” at the end of that sub-paragraph) insert— “(iia) the processing of personal data carried out in preparation for disclosure described in sub-paragraph (i) or (ii),”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to insert a new sub-paragraph (iia) in paragraph 14(1)(b) that allows for the processing of personal data in preparation for disclosure as described in sub-paragraphs (i) or (ii).</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Data Protection"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>paragraph 24(1)(a) (disclosure to elected representatives)</subject>
   <quote>In paragraph 24(1)(a) (disclosure to elected representatives), after “consists of” insert “, or is carried out in preparation for,”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to insert a new phrase in paragraph 24(1)(a) that allows for the processing of personal data in preparation for disclosure to elected representatives.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Data Protection"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 2 (exemptions etc from the UK GDPR)</subject>
   <quote>Schedule 2 (exemptions etc from the UK GDPR) is amended as follows. (2) In paragraph 2(1)(a) (crime), after “prevention” insert “, investigation”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to insert the term "investigation" after "prevention" in paragraph 2(1)(a) of Schedule 2, expanding the scope of exemptions from the UK GDPR.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Data Protection"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 10 Section 86 PRIVACY AND ELECTRONIC COMMUNICATIONS: COMMISSIONER’S ENFORCEMENT POWERS</subject>
   <quote>SCHEDULE 10 Section 86 PRIVACY AND ELECTRONIC COMMUNICATIONS: COMMISSIONER’S ENFORCEMENT POWERS</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to insert a new Schedule 10 Section 86, which outlines the enforcement powers of the Information Commissioner in relation to privacy and electronic communications.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Data Protection"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Internet Governance"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Schedule 10—Privacy and electronic communications: Commissioner’s enforcement powers</subject>

   <quote>(ii) in paragraph (h), for “the processing of personal data” there were substituted “any activity regulated by the PEC Regulations”;</quote>
   <quote>(iii) in paragraph (i), for “process personal data on behalf of the controller” there were substituted “are involved in any such activity on behalf of the person to whom the notice is given”;</quote>
   <quote>(d) in subsection (3A), for “controller or processor” there were substituted “person”;</quote>
   <quote>(e) in subsection (7), for “controller or processor” there were substituted “person to whom the notice is given”;</quote>
   <quote>(f) in subsection (8)— (i) in paragraph (a), for “controller or processor” there were substituted “person to whom the notice is given”;</quote>
   <quote>(ii) in the words after paragraph (c), for “controller or processor” there were substituted “person”;</quote>
   <quote>(g) in subsection (9)— (i) in paragraph (a), for the words from “a controller” to “this Act” there were substituted “the person to whom the notice is given has failed or is failing to comply with the requirements of the PEC Regulations or that an offence under section 144, 148 or 148C or paragraph 15 of Schedule 15”;</quote>
   <quote>(ii) in paragraph (d), for “controller or processor” there were substituted “person”;</quote>
   <quote>(h) in subsection (10), for “controller or processor” there were substituted “person”;</quote>
   <quote>(i) subsection (11) were omitted;</quote>
   <quote>(j) in subsection (11A)— (i) for “controller or processor”, in the first place it occurs, there were substituted “person to whom it is given”;</quote>
   <quote>(ii) for “controller or processor”, in the second place it occurs, there were substituted “the person”.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to amend the language in Schedule 10, replacing references to "the processing of personal data" and "controller or processor" with broader terms such as "any activity regulated by the PEC Regulations" and "person". This change expands the scope of the regulations to cover any activity regulated by the PEC Regulations, not just the processing of personal data. It also broadens the entities that can be held accountable from just controllers or processors to any person involved in such activities.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">
      This amendment broadens the scope of privacy regulations, potentially increasing protections for individuals' digital information.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation">
      The change could have significant implications for tech companies, as it expands the range of activities and entities that can be held accountable under the PEC Regulations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 155 (penalty notices)</subject>

   <quote>Section 155 has effect as if— 5
(a) in subsection (1)—
(i) in paragraph (a), for “as described in section 149(2), (3), (4),
(5) or (5A)” there were substituted “to comply with a
requirement of the PEC Regulations”;
(ii) after paragraph (c), there were inserted “or 10
(d) has failed to comply with the prohibition in section
142(8B),”;</quote>

   <summary>The amendment modifies the conditions under which penalty notices can be issued, specifically to include failure to comply with the PEC Regulations and the prohibition in section 142(8B).</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The amendment could potentially increase the number of penalty notices issued, impacting the legal processes and enforcement mechanisms.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The amendment could potentially increase the enforcement of digital privacy regulations, impacting the rights and protections of individuals.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 155 (penalty notices)</subject>

   <quote>(f) after subsection (4) there were inserted— 35
“(4A) If a penalty notice is given to a body in respect of a failure
to comply with any of regulations 19 to 24 of the PEC
Regulations, the Commissioner may also give a penalty notice
40
to an officer of the body if the Commissioner is satisfied that
the failure—
(a) took place with the consent or connivance of the
officer, or
(b) was attributable to any neglect on the part of the
officer.</quote>

   <summary>The amendment allows for penalty notices to be issued to an officer of a body corporate or a Scottish partnership if the Commissioner is satisfied that the failure to comply with regulations 19 to 24 of the PEC Regulations took place with the consent or connivance of the officer, or was attributable to any neglect on the part of the officer.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The amendment could potentially increase the accountability of officers in a body corporate or a Scottish partnership, impacting the legal processes and enforcement mechanisms.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The amendment could potentially increase the enforcement of digital privacy regulations, impacting the rights and protections of individuals.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Births and Deaths Registration Act 1953</subject>

   <quote>In subsection (5), for the words from “direct” to the end substitute “enter
30
in the margin of the relevant register of births a reference to the
re-registration of the birth or, if the relevant register of births is in hard
copy form, shall direct the officer having custody of that register to do so.”</quote>

   <quote>Section 13 (registration of name of child or of alteration of name) is amended 5
as follows.</quote>

   <quote>Section 29 (correction of errors in registers) is amended as follows.</quote>

   <quote>Section 30 (searches of indexes kept by Registrar General) is amended as
follows.</quote>

   <quote>For section 32 (searches in registers kept by registrars) substitute—
“32 Obtaining copies of entries from registrars</quote>

   <quote>Section 33 (short certificate of birth) is amended as follows.</quote>

   <quote>In section 34 (entry in register as evidence of birth or death), in subsection
(5), before “on which” insert “in or”.</quote>

   <quote>Section 34A (searches and records of information: additional provision) is
amended as follows.</quote>

   <quote>In section 35 (offences relating to registers), in paragraph (b), after “deaths”
insert “kept in hard copy form”.</quote>

   <quote>In section 41 (interpretation), after subsection (3) insert—
“(4) For the purposes of this Act a register is in hard copy form if it
consists of a paper copy or similar form capable of being read with
the naked eye.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes several amendments to the Births and Deaths Registration Act 1953. These changes include modifications to the process of re-registration of births, registration of name changes, correction of errors in registers, searches of indexes kept by the Registrar General, obtaining copies of entries from registrars, issuance of short certificates of birth, and the interpretation of what constitutes a register in hard copy form.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Registration Service Act 1953</subject>

   <quote>In section 10 (district register offices), in subsection (1), omit the words from “, and shall provide” to the end.</quote>
   <quote>In section 12 (provision of register boxes), omit “registrar of births and deaths and”.</quote>
   <quote>In section 13 (local schemes of organisation), in subsection (2), after paragraph (b) insert—“(ba) determining the equipment or facilities to be provided at those offices and stations by the council for the non-metropolitan county or metropolitan district;”.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the Registration Service Act 1953, specifically sections 10, 12, and 13. These changes involve the removal of certain phrases and the addition of a new provision regarding the determination of equipment or facilities to be provided at offices and stations by the council.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Bureaucratic Processes"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Public Records Act 1958</subject>

   <quote>In Schedule 1 to the Public Records Act 1958 (definition of public records), in paragraph 2(2)(b), after “adoptions,” insert “or to any other records held by the Registrar General of information entered in any register of births or deaths kept under any such enactment,”.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes an amendment to the Public Records Act 1958, specifically in Schedule 1, to include other records held by the Registrar General of information entered in any register of births or deaths.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Bureaucratic Processes"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Social Security Administration Act 1992</subject>

   <quote>In section 124 of the Social Security Administration Act 1992 (provisions relating to age, death and marriage), after subsection (5) insert—“(6) The reference in subsection (1) above to a register in the custody of a registrar or superintendent registrar includes, in relation to registers of births or deaths kept under the Births and Deaths Registration Act 1953, a reference to any such register kept for the registrar’s sub-district or (as the case may be) for a sub-district within the superintendent registrar’s district; and references in subsection (3) above to the custodian of the register are to be read accordingly.”</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes an amendment to the Social Security Administration Act 1992, specifically in section 124, to include a reference to any register of births or deaths kept for the registrar’s sub-district or for a sub-district within the superintendent registrar’s district.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Bureaucratic Processes"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Education Act 1996</subject>

   <quote>Section 564 of the Education Act 1996 (certificates of birth and registrars’ returns) is amended as follows.</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (1), for “the registrar having the custody of the register of births and deaths” substitute “the relevant registrar for the register”.</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (3)—(a) for “A registrar” substitute “The relevant registrar for a register”; (b) for “any register of births and deaths in his custody” substitute “the register”.</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (4)—(a) in the definition of “the appropriate fee”, for “the registrar having custody of the register concerned” substitute “the relevant registrar for a register”; (b) for the definition of “register of births and deaths” substitute— ““register” means a register of births or register of deaths kept under that Act,”; (c) at the end insert— ““the relevant registrar” for a register means— (a) in the case of a register in hard copy form (within the meaning of the Births and Deaths Registration Act 1953), the superintendent registrar having custody of the register; (b) in the case of a register not in hard copy form (within the meaning of that Act)— (i) the registrar of births and deaths for the sub-district for which the register is or has been kept, or (ii) the superintendent registrar for the district containing that sub-district.”</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the Education Act 1996, specifically in section 564, to replace references to "the registrar having the custody of the register of births and deaths" with "the relevant registrar for the register". It also redefines "register" and "the relevant registrar".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Education"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Adoption and Children Act 2002</subject>

   <quote>In section 78 of the Adoption and Children Act 2002 (Adopted Children Register: searches and copies), in subsection (4)—(a) in paragraph (a), omit “certified copies of”; (b) in paragraph (b), for “certified copies” (in the second place it occurs) substitute “registers”.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes an amendment to the Adoption and Children Act 2002, specifically in section 78, to replace "certified copies" with "registers".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Family and Children"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Gender Recognition Act 2004</subject>

   <quote>The Gender Recognition Act 2004 is amended as follows.</quote>
   <quote>Section 10 (registration) is amended as follows. In subsection (2), omit the “or” after paragraph (a) and after paragraph (b) insert “, or (c) an entry in a register kept under section 1 of the Births and Deaths Registration Act 1953,”.</quote>
   <quote>For subsection (3) substitute— “(3) “The appropriate Registrar General” means— (a) in relation to a UK birth register entry of which a certified copy is kept by a Registrar General or which is in a register so kept, whichever Registrar General keeps that certified copy or that register; (b) in relation to a UK birth register entry in a register kept under section 1 of the Births and Deaths Registration Act 1953, the Registrar General for England and Wales. (3A) For the purposes of this section each of the following is a Registrar General— (a) the Registrar General for England and Wales; (b) the Registrar General for Scotland; (c) the Registrar General for Northern Ireland.”</quote>
   <quote>In Part 1 of Schedule 3 (registration: England and Wales), in paragraphs 5(3) and 8(2), for “or (b)” substitute “, (b) or (c)”.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the Gender Recognition Act 2004, specifically in section 10 and Part 1 of Schedule 3, to include an entry in a register kept under section 1 of the Births and Deaths Registration Act 1953 and to redefine "The appropriate Registrar General".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Gender and Sexuality"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Presumption of Death Act 2013</subject>

   <quote>In Schedule 1 to the Presumption of Death Act 2013 (Register of Presumed Deaths), in paragraph 7 (interpretation)—(a) after “means” insert “— (a)”; (b) at the end insert “, or (b) the index kept in the General Register Office of such entries.”</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes an amendment to the Presumption of Death Act 2013, specifically in Schedule 1, to include the index kept in the General Register Office of such entries.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Bureaucratic Processes"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Health and Social Care Act 2012</subject>

   <quote>Part 9 of the Health and Social Care Act 2012 (health and adult social care services: information) is amended as follows.</quote>
   <quote>Before section 250 insert— “Powers to publish standards”.</quote>
   <quote>Section 250 (powers to publish information standards) is amended as follows. In subsection (2), at the end insert “and includes, among other things, a standard relating to information technology or IT services used, or intended to be used, in connection with the processing of information (see section 250A)”.</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (2B)(c)—(a) after “provision” insert “in, or in relation to, England”, and (b) omit “in England”. In subsection (2B), at the end insert— “(e) a relevant IT provider.”</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (3)—(a) after “provision” insert “in, or in relation to, England”, and (b) omit “in England”. In subsection (7)—(a) in the opening words, for “section” substitute “Chapter”, (b) after the definition of “health care” insert— ““information technology” includes— (a) computers, (b) other devices whose uses include the processing of information by electronic means (“IT devices”), (c) parts, accessories and other equipment made or adapted for use in connection with computers or IT devices, (d) software and code made or adapted for use in connection with computers or IT devices, and (e) networks and other infrastructure (whether physical or virtual) used in connection with other information technology; “IT service” means an information technology service, including any service (whether physical or virtual) which consists of, or is provided in connection with, the development, making available, operation or maintenance of information technology;”, (c) in the definition of “processing”, omit “and (14)”, and (d) at the end insert— ““relevant IT provider” means a person involved in marketing, supplying, providing or otherwise making available— (a) information technology, (b) an IT service, or (c) a service which consists of processing information using information technology, whether for payment or free of charge, but only so far as the technology or service is used, or intended to be used, in connection with the provision in, or in relation to, England of health care or of adult social care.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the Health and Social Care Act 2012, specifically in Part 9, to include powers to publish standards, a standard relating to information technology or IT services used in connection with the processing of information, and the definition of "relevant IT provider".</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Public Health"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 250A</subject>
   <quote>“250A Standards relating to information technology
(1) An information standard relating to information technology or IT
services may, among other things, make provision about—
(a)
20
the design, quality, capabilities or other characteristics of
such technology or services;
(b) contracts or other arrangements under which such technology
or services are marketed, supplied, provided or otherwise
made available.
(2)
25
An information standard may include technical provision about
information technology or IT services, including provision about—
(a) functionality;
(b) connectivity;
(c) interoperability;
(d) portability;
(e) storage of, and access to, information; 30
(f) security of information.
(3) An information standard may make provision by reference to open
standards or proprietary standards.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a new section 250A, which allows for the creation of information standards relating to information technology or IT services. These standards can cover a wide range of aspects, including the design, quality, capabilities, or other characteristics of such technology or services, as well as the contracts or arrangements under which they are made available. The standards can also include technical provisions about functionality, connectivity, interoperability, portability, storage of and access to information, and security of information. The standards can be made by reference to open or proprietary standards.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Economy"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Cybersecurity"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Interoperability"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 251ZB</subject>
   <quote>“251ZB Notice requesting compliance by relevant IT providers
(1) If the Secretary of State has reasonable grounds to suspect that a 10
relevant IT provider is not complying with an information standard
which applies to the provider, the Secretary of State may give the
provider a written notice which—
(a) identifies the standard in question,
(b) sets out the Secretary of State’s grounds for suspecting that 15
the provider is not complying with the standard,
(c) asks the provider to comply with the standard within a
period specified in the notice,
(d)
20
asks the provider, within a period specified in the notice, to
provide evidence to the Secretary of State’s satisfaction that
the provider is complying with the standard, and
(e) if the Secretary of State considers it appropriate, sets out the
steps that the Secretary of State considers the provider must
25
take, within a period specified in the notice, in order to
comply with the standard.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a new section 251ZB, which gives the Secretary of State the power to issue a written notice to IT providers suspected of non-compliance with an information standard. The notice must identify the standard in question, set out the grounds for suspicion, ask the provider to comply within a specified period, ask the provider to provide evidence of compliance, and may set out the steps the provider must take to comply.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Cybersecurity"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 251ZC</subject>
   <quote>“251ZC Public censure of relevant IT providers
(1) If the Secretary of State has reasonable grounds to suspect that a
35
relevant IT provider is not complying with an information standard
which applies to the provider, the Secretary of State may publish a
statement to that effect.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a new section 251ZC, which gives the Secretary of State the power to publicly censure IT providers suspected of non-compliance with an information standard.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Cybersecurity"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 251ZE</subject>
   <quote>“251ZE Accreditation of information technology etc
(1)
35
Regulations may make provision for the establishment and operation
of a scheme for the accreditation of information technology and IT
services so far as used, or intended to be used, in connection with
the provision in, or in relation to, England of health care or of adult
social care.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a new section 251ZE, which allows for the creation of regulations to establish and operate an accreditation scheme for information technology and IT services used or intended to be used in connection with the provision of health care or adult social care in England.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Public Health"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 12A</subject>
   <quote>“SCHEDULE 12A Section 114A
THE INFORMATION COMMISSION
Status
1 (1) The Commission is not to be regarded—
(a) as a servant or agent of the Crown, or 30
(b) as enjoying any status, immunity or privilege of the
Crown.
(2) The Commission’s property is not to be regarded—
(a) as property of the Crown, or
(b) as property held on behalf of the Crown. 35
194 Data Protection and Digital Information (No. 2) Bill
Schedule 13—The Information Commission 
Number of members
2 The number of members of the Commission is to be determined
by the Secretary of State.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a new Schedule 12A, which establishes the Information Commission. The Commission is not to be regarded as a servant or agent of the Crown, nor as enjoying any status, immunity or privilege of the Crown. The Commission's property is not to be regarded as property of the Crown, or as property held on behalf of the Crown. The number of members of the Commission is to be determined by the Secretary of State.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Tech Company Regulation"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Cybersecurity"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Freedom of Information"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 13—The Information Commission</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State may not recommend a person for appointment as the chair of the Commission unless the person has been selected on merit on the basis of fair and open competition.</quote>
   <quote>A person may not be appointed as a member of the Commission unless the person has been selected on merit on the basis of fair and open competition.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a new regulation for the appointment of the chair and members of the Information Commission. They must be selected on merit through a fair and open competition.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially increase the transparency and fairness of the appointment process for the Information Commission, which could lead to a more competent and diverse Commission.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 13—The Information Commission</subject>

   <quote>Before—
(a) recommending a person for appointment as the chair of the Commission, or
(b) appointing a person as a non-executive member of the Commission,
the Secretary of State must be satisfied that the person does not have a conflict of interest.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a new regulation that requires the Secretary of State to ensure that a person does not have a conflict of interest before recommending them for appointment as the chair or a non-executive member of the Information Commission.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially reduce the risk of corruption or bias in the Information Commission, which could lead to more impartial decision-making.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 13—The Information Commission</subject>

   <quote>The chair of the Commission holds and vacates office in accordance with the terms of the chair’s appointment, subject to the provisions of this paragraph.</quote>
   <quote>The chair must be appointed for a term of not more than 7 years.</quote>
   <quote>A person cannot be appointed as the chair more than once.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes new regulations for the tenure of the chair of the Information Commission. The chair is to be appointed for a term of not more than 7 years and cannot be appointed more than once.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially prevent the concentration of power in the hands of a single individual, which could lead to a more democratic and accountable Information Commission.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 13—The Information Commission</subject>

   <quote>The Commission may establish committees.</quote>
   <quote>A committee of the Commission may consist of or include persons who are neither members nor employees of the Commission.</quote>

   <summary>The bill allows the Information Commission to establish committees, which can include individuals who are neither members nor employees of the Commission.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially increase the diversity of perspectives in the committees of the Information Commission, which could lead to more comprehensive and inclusive decision-making.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 13—The Information Commission</subject>

   <quote>The delegation of a function by the Commission or a committee of the Commission under this paragraph does not prevent the Commission or the committee from exercising that function.</quote>
   <quote>The Commission may require a committee of the Commission to give the Commission advice about matters relating to the discharge of the Commission’s functions.</quote>
   <quote>The Commission may make arrangements for regulating— (a) its own procedure, and (b) the procedure of a committee of the Commission.</quote>
   <quote>The Commission must make arrangements for the keeping of proper records of— (a) its proceedings, (b) the proceedings of a committee of the Commission, (c) the proceedings at a meeting of the non-executive members of the Commission, (d) anything done by a member or employee of the Commission under paragraph 14(1), and (e) anything done by a member of a committee of the Commission under paragraph 14(3).</quote>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may make payments to the Commission.</quote>
   <quote>All fees, charges, penalties and other sums received by the Commission in carrying out its functions are to be paid to the Secretary of State.</quote>
   <quote>The Commission must keep proper accounts and proper records in relation to them.</quote>
   <quote>The application of the Commission’s seal must be authenticated by the signature of— (a) the chair of the Commission, or (b) another person authorised for that purpose by the Commission.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the establishment of the Information Commission, which will have the power to delegate functions, regulate its own procedures, keep records of its proceedings, receive payments from the Secretary of State, collect fees and other sums, maintain proper accounts, and authenticate the application of its seal.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">The establishment of the Information Commission represents a significant shift in political power, as it will have the authority to regulate the processing of information relating to identified or identifiable living individuals, oversee the use of information to ascertain and verify facts about individuals, and manage access to customer data and business data.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Public Health">The Information Commission will also have the power to set information standards for health and social care, which could have significant implications for public health.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">The creation of the Information Commission could have far-reaching implications for human rights, particularly in relation to privacy and data protection.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The Information Commission will have the power to collect fees, charges, penalties and other sums, which could have implications for the justice system.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Term limit for the chair of the Information Commission</subject>

   <quote>The term for which the person is treated as having been appointed as the chair of the Information Commission may not be extended under paragraph 7(3) of Schedule 12A to the 2018 Act so that the term as extended expires after the end of the period of 7 years beginning with the day the person began to hold the office of Information Commissioner.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a term limit for the chair of the Information Commission. The term may not be extended such that it exceeds a total of 7 years from the day the person took office.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">
      This change could potentially limit the concentration of power in the hands of the chair of the Information Commission by ensuring a regular turnover in leadership. This could promote fresh perspectives and prevent stagnation in the Commission's approach to data protection and digital information.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change could impact the continuity and consistency of the Commission's decisions and policies, as new chairs may bring different priorities and interpretations of the law.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change></all>