<all><change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Power to designate undertaking as having Strategic Market Status (SMS)</subject>

   <quote>2 Designation of undertaking
3 Digital activities
4 Link to the United Kingdom
5 Substantial and entrenched market power
6 Position of strategic significance
7 The turnover condition
8 Turnover of an undertaking</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces the concept of Strategic Market Status (SMS) and provides the power to designate an undertaking as having SMS. This designation is based on several factors including the digital activities of the undertaking, its link to the UK, its substantial and entrenched market power, its position of strategic significance, and its turnover.</summary>

   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could have significant economic implications, particularly for large digital companies operating in the UK. Being designated as having SMS could potentially subject these companies to additional regulatory scrutiny and requirements.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Power to impose conduct requirements</subject>

   <quote>19 Power to impose conduct requirements
20 Permitted types of conduct requirement
21 Content of notice imposing a conduct requirement
22 Revocation of conduct requirements</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces the power to impose conduct requirements on undertakings with Strategic Market Status (SMS). It also outlines the permitted types of conduct requirements, the content of the notice imposing a conduct requirement, and the process for revoking conduct requirements.</summary>

   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could have significant economic implications, particularly for large digital companies operating in the UK. The imposition of conduct requirements could potentially affect these companies' operations and business practices.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Power to make pro-competition interventions</subject>

   <quote>45 Power to make pro-competition interventions</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces the power to make pro-competition interventions. This could potentially involve measures to promote competition in digital markets.</summary>

   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could have significant economic implications, particularly for large digital companies operating in the UK. Pro-competition interventions could potentially affect these companies' market dominance and business practices.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 1 - Digital Markets, Chapter 1 - Overview</subject>

   <quote>Provide for the regulation of competition in digital markets; to amend the Competition Act 1998 and the Enterprise Act 2002 and to make other provision about competition law; to make provision relating to the protection of consumer rights and to confer further such rights; and for connected purposes.</quote>
   <quote>This Part—
(a) confers functions on the CMA in relation to the regulation of competition in digital markets, and
(b) makes related provision.</quote>
   <quote>Chapter 2 makes provision about the designation of undertakings as having strategic market status in respect of a digital activity.</quote>
   <quote>Chapter 3 provides for the CMA to be able to impose conduct requirements on a designated undertaking.</quote>
   <quote>Chapter 4 provides for the CMA to take steps to promote competition where it considers that activities of a designated undertaking are having an adverse effect on competition.</quote>
   <quote>Chapter 5 makes provision about a duty to report certain possible mergers involving a designated undertaking.</quote>
   <quote>Chapter 6 makes provision about investigatory powers and compliance reports in relation to a designated undertaking.</quote>
   <quote>Chapter 7 makes provision about enforcement and appeals in relation to functions of the CMA under this Part.</quote>
   <quote>Chapter 8 makes provision about administration and other matters in relation to functions of the CMA under this Part.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the establishment of a new regulatory framework for digital markets. This includes the ability for the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) to regulate competition in digital markets, designate undertakings as having strategic market status, impose conduct requirements on designated undertakings, promote competition, require reporting of possible mergers, and exercise investigatory powers and compliance reports. The bill also provides for enforcement and appeals mechanisms, as well as administrative provisions.</summary>

   <impact>4</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">The proposed changes could significantly reshape the digital market landscape, potentially affecting large tech companies and their business practices. This could have substantial economic implications.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">The bill grants significant new powers to the CMA, a non-ministerial government department, which could shift the balance of power in the regulation of digital markets.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">The bill's provisions on consumer rights and protections could have implications for individual privacy and data rights in the digital sphere.</pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Strategic Market Status (SMS) Designation</subject>

   <quote>The CMA may designate an undertaking as having strategic market status (“SMS”) in respect of a digital activity carried out by the undertaking where the CMA considers that— (a) the digital activity is linked to the United Kingdom (see section 4), and (b) the undertaking meets the SMS conditions in respect of the digital activity.</quote>

   <summary>
     The bill introduces a new designation of "Strategic Market Status" (SMS) for certain digital activities. The Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) has the power to designate an undertaking as having SMS if the digital activity is linked to the UK and the undertaking meets certain conditions.
   </summary>

   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      This change could have significant economic implications, as it introduces a new regulatory status for digital activities. This could potentially affect large tech companies and their operations in the UK.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">
      This change could also have political implications, as it gives the CMA new powers to regulate digital activities.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Turnover Condition for SMS Designation</subject>

   <quote>The CMA may not designate an undertaking as having SMS in respect of a digital activity unless the turnover condition is met in relation to the undertaking. The turnover condition is met in relation to an undertaking if the CMA estimates that— (a) the total value of the global turnover of an undertaking or, where the undertaking is part of a group, the global turnover of that group in the relevant period exceeds £25 billion, or (b) the total value of the UK turnover of an undertaking or, where the undertaking is part of a group, the UK turnover of that group in the relevant period exceeds £1 billion.</quote>

   <summary>
     The bill introduces a "turnover condition" for the designation of SMS. An undertaking can only be designated as having SMS if its global turnover exceeds £25 billion or its UK turnover exceeds £1 billion.
   </summary>

   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      This change could have significant economic implications, as it sets a high financial threshold for the designation of SMS. This could potentially affect large tech companies and their operations in the UK.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">
      This change could also have political implications, as it gives the CMA new powers to regulate digital activities based on their financial turnover.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>SMS Investigations</subject>

   <quote>The CMA may begin an initial SMS investigation where it has reasonable grounds to consider that it may be able to designate an undertaking as having SMS in respect of a digital activity in accordance with section 2.</quote>

   <summary>
     The bill allows the CMA to initiate an SMS investigation if it has reasonable grounds to believe that an undertaking could be designated as having SMS.
   </summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      This change could have economic implications, as it introduces a new investigative process for the designation of SMS. This could potentially affect large tech companies and their operations in the UK.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">
      This change could also have political implications, as it gives the CMA new powers to investigate digital activities.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Strategic Market Status (SMS) investigations</subject>

   <quote>The CMA must give the undertaking one or more revised versions of the SMS investigation notice if it changes its view of the purpose and scope of the investigation.</quote>
   <quote>As soon as reasonably practicable after giving an SMS investigation notice or a revised version of an SMS investigation notice, the CMA must— (a) publish a statement summarising the contents of the notice, and (b) give a copy of the statement to the FCA, OFCOM, the Information Commissioner, the Bank of England and the PRA.</quote>
   <quote>The CMA may close an initial SMS investigation at any time before it has reached a final view on the matters mentioned in paragraphs (a) and (b) of section 2(1).</quote>
   <quote>When the CMA decides to close an initial SMS investigation, the CMA must give the undertaking to which the investigation related a notice to that effect.</quote>
   <quote>The notice must include the CMA’s reasons for closing the investigation.</quote>
   <quote>As soon as reasonably practicable after giving a notice under subsection (2), the CMA must publish a statement summarising the contents of the notice.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces new procedures for the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) to conduct Strategic Market Status (SMS) investigations. The CMA must provide revised versions of the SMS investigation notice if its view of the investigation's purpose and scope changes. The CMA must also publish a summary of the notice and provide a copy to various entities. The CMA can close an SMS investigation at any time before reaching a final view and must provide a notice to the undertaking under investigation, including the reasons for closing the investigation. This notice must also be published.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">The new procedures for SMS investigations could have significant implications for digital markets, potentially leading to increased scrutiny and regulation of dominant firms.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">The CMA is granted new powers to conduct and close SMS investigations, which could enhance its ability to regulate competition in digital markets.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Conduct requirements for designated undertakings</subject>

   <quote>The trust and transparency objective is that users or potential users of the relevant digital activity have the information they require to enable them to—
(a) understand the services or digital content provided by the undertaking 10
through the relevant digital activity, including the terms on which
they are provided, and
(b) make properly informed decisions about whether and how they interact
with the undertaking in respect of the relevant digital activity.</quote>

   <quote>Conduct requirements are of a permitted type if they are within subsection 25
(2) or (3).
(2) Requirements are within this subsection if they are for the purpose of obliging
a designated undertaking to—
(a) trade on fair and reasonable terms;
(b) have effective processes for handling complaints by and disputes with 30
users or potential users;
(c) provide clear, relevant, accurate and accessible information about the
relevant digital activity to users or potential users;
(d)
35
give explanations, and a reasonable period of notice, to users or
potential users of the relevant digital activity, before making changes
in relation to the relevant digital activity where those changes are
likely to have a material impact on the users or potential users;
(e) present to users or potential users any options or default settings in
40
relation to the relevant digital activity in a way that allows those users
or potential users to make informed and effective decisions in their
own best interests about those options or settings.</quote>

   <quote>Requirements are within this subsection if they are for the purpose of
preventing a designated undertaking from—
(a) applying discriminatory terms, conditions or policies to certain users
or potential users or certain descriptions of users or potential users;
(b) using its position in relation to the relevant digital activity, including 5
its access to data relating to that activity, to treat its own products
more favourably than those of other undertakings;
(c) carrying on activities other than the relevant digital activity in a way
10
that is likely to increase the undertaking’s market power materially,
or bolster the strategic significance of its position, in relation to the
relevant digital activity;
(d) requiring or incentivising users or potential users of one of the
designated undertaking’s products to use one or more of the
15
undertaking’s other products alongside services or digital content the
provision of which is, or is comprised in, the relevant digital activity;
(e) restricting interoperability between the relevant service or digital
content and products offered by other undertakings;
(f) restricting whether or how users or potential users can use the relevant
digital activity;
(g) using data unfairly; 20
(h) restricting the ability of users or potential users to use products of
other undertakings.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces conduct requirements for designated undertakings in digital markets. These requirements aim to ensure transparency, fair trading, effective complaint handling, clear and accessible information, and non-discriminatory practices. The bill also provides for the prevention of certain activities that could unfairly increase an undertaking's market power or restrict users' choices and interoperability with other products.</summary>

   <impact>4</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">The proposed changes could significantly impact the operations of digital market undertakings, potentially leading to more competitive and transparent digital markets.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">The changes could enhance users' rights in digital markets by ensuring they have access to clear and accurate information, fair trading terms, and effective complaint handling processes.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The introduction of conduct requirements could lead to increased regulatory oversight and potential legal disputes related to compliance.</pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Power to amend permitted types of conduct requirement</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State may by regulations amend this section so as to modify
the permitted types of requirement.
(5) Regulations under subsection (4) are subject to the affirmative procedure.</quote>

   <summary>The bill grants the Secretary of State the power to amend the section on permitted types of conduct requirements by regulations. Any such regulations would be subject to the affirmative procedure.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change grants the Secretary of State significant power to modify the conduct requirements for digital market undertakings, potentially influencing the regulatory landscape of digital markets.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The change could lead to legal disputes related to the interpretation and application of any amendments to the conduct requirements.</pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Power to begin a conduct investigation</subject>

   <quote>The CMA may begin an investigation (a “conduct investigation”) where it 10
has reasonable grounds to suspect that a designated undertaking has breached
a conduct requirement.</quote>

   <summary>The bill grants the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) the power to begin a conduct investigation if it has reasonable grounds to suspect that a designated undertaking has breached a conduct requirement.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could lead to increased regulatory oversight and potential legal disputes related to compliance with conduct requirements.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">The change grants the CMA significant power to investigate potential breaches of conduct requirements, potentially influencing the regulatory landscape of digital markets.</pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Countervailing benefits exemption</subject>

   <quote>The countervailing benefits exemption applies where— 25
(a) the conduct to which the investigation relates gives rise to benefits to
users or potential users of the digital activity in respect of which the
conduct requirement in question applies,
(b)
30
those benefits outweigh any actual or likely detrimental impact on
competition resulting from a breach of the conduct requirement,
(c) the conduct is indispensable and proportionate to the realisation of
those benefits, and
(d) the conduct does not eliminate or prevent effective competition.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a countervailing benefits exemption, which applies when the conduct under investigation provides benefits to users or potential users of the digital activity, outweighs any negative impact on competition, is indispensable and proportionate to the realization of those benefits, and does not eliminate or prevent effective competition.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially allow certain anti-competitive behaviors if they are deemed to provide significant benefits to users, which could have implications for the balance of power in digital markets.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Enforcement orders</subject>

   <quote>Where the CMA finds, as a result of a conduct investigation, that a designated 20
undertaking has breached a conduct requirement, it may make an order (an
“enforcement order”) imposing on the undertaking such obligations as the
CMA considers appropriate for one or more of the following purposes—
(a) in a case where the breach is ongoing, stopping the breach;
(b) preventing the breach from happening again; 25
(c) addressing any damage caused by the breach.</quote>

   <summary>The bill allows the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) to issue enforcement orders when it finds that a designated undertaking has breached a conduct requirement. These orders can impose obligations to stop an ongoing breach, prevent future breaches, or address any damage caused by the breach.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change gives the CMA significant power to enforce conduct requirements in digital markets, which could have a major impact on the behavior of digital companies.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Commitments relating to conduct requirements</subject>

   <quote>The CMA may accept an appropriate commitment from an undertaking subject
to a conduct investigation as to its behaviour in respect of a conduct
requirement to which the investigation relates.</quote>

   <summary>The bill allows the CMA to accept commitments from undertakings under conduct investigation, where the undertaking commits to certain behavior in respect of a conduct requirement.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could provide a more flexible approach to enforcing conduct requirements, allowing companies to make commitments to change their behavior rather than facing enforcement orders.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 3—Conduct requirements</subject>

   <quote>(7) The CMA may release an undertaking from the requirement to comply with a commitment where it considers that it would be appropriate to do so.</quote>
   <quote>(8) The fact that a commitment ceases to have effect does not affect the exercise of any functions in relation to a breach or possible breach of that commitment.</quote>
   <quote>(9) Schedule 1 makes provision about— 15 (a) accepting, or accepting a variation of, a commitment, and (b) releasing an undertaking from the requirement to comply with a commitment, for the purposes of this Chapter and Chapter 4 (pro-competition orders).</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) may release an undertaking from the requirement to comply with a commitment where it considers it appropriate. The cessation of a commitment does not affect the exercise of any functions in relation to a breach or possible breach of that commitment. Provisions are made for accepting or accepting a variation of a commitment, and releasing an undertaking from the requirement to comply with a commitment.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially impact the economic landscape by providing the CMA with the power to release undertakings from commitments, which could affect market competition and business operations.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 3—Conduct requirements</subject>

   <quote>38 Power to adopt final offer mechanism 30 (1) Where the CMA considers that the following three conditions are met in relation to a transaction between a designated undertaking and a third party, the CMA may— (a) require the undertaking, and (b) invite the third party, 35 to submit to the CMA terms as to payment (“final offer payment terms”) which the undertaking or, as the case may be, the third party regards as fair and reasonable for the transaction.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a new power for the CMA to adopt a final offer mechanism in relation to a transaction between a designated undertaking and a third party. This mechanism would require the undertaking and invite the third party to submit to the CMA terms as to payment which they regard as fair and reasonable for the transaction.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially impact the economic landscape by providing the CMA with the power to adopt a final offer mechanism, which could affect market competition and business operations.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 4—Pro-competition interventions</subject>

   <quote>45 Power to make pro-competition interventions (1) The CMA may make a pro-competition intervention (a “PCI”) in relation to a designated undertaking where, following a PCI investigation (see section 46), the CMA considers that— (a) a factor or combination of factors relating to a relevant digital activity is having an adverse effect on competition, and (b) making the PCI would be likely to contribute to, or otherwise be of use for the purpose of, remedying, mitigating or preventing the adverse effect on competition.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a new power for the CMA to make pro-competition interventions in relation to a designated undertaking. This power can be exercised if the CMA considers that a factor or combination of factors relating to a relevant digital activity is having an adverse effect on competition, and making the intervention would likely contribute to remedying, mitigating or preventing the adverse effect on competition.</summary>

   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could dramatically reshape the economic landscape by providing the CMA with the power to make pro-competition interventions, which could significantly affect market competition and business operations.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Pro-competition interventions</subject>

   <quote>In considering whether to make a PCI, and the form and content of any PCI, the CMA may have regard to any benefits to UK users or UK customers that the CMA considers have resulted, or may be expected to result, from a factor or combination of factors that is having an adverse effect on competition.</quote>
   <quote>A PCI may take the form of one or both of the following—
(a) an order imposing on the designated undertaking requirements as to how the undertaking must conduct itself, in relation to the relevant digital activity or otherwise (a “pro-competition order”: see section 50);
(b) recommendations made by the CMA to any person exercising functions of a public nature about steps which the CMA considers the person ought to take in respect of the designated undertaking or the digital activity, or otherwise.</quote>
   <quote>The CMA may begin an investigation (a “PCI investigation”) in relation to a designated undertaking where it has reasonable grounds to consider that a factor or combination of factors relating to a relevant digital activity may be having an adverse effect on competition.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces the concept of Pro-competition Interventions (PCI), which the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) can use to regulate competition in digital markets. The CMA can make a PCI if it believes that a factor or combination of factors is having an adverse effect on competition. A PCI can take the form of an order imposing requirements on a designated undertaking or recommendations made by the CMA to any person exercising functions of a public nature. The CMA can also begin a PCI investigation if it has reasonable grounds to believe that a factor or combination of factors relating to a relevant digital activity may be having an adverse effect on competition.</summary>

   <impact>4</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">The introduction of PCIs could have a significant impact on the digital market, potentially leading to increased competition and better outcomes for consumers.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">The CMA is granted significant new powers to regulate competition in the digital market, which could have implications for the balance of power between the government and private companies.</pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 4—Pro-competition interventions</subject>

   <quote>The CMA must carry out a review of a pro-competition order, including a replacement order, to determine whether to—
(a) revoke it without making a replacement order, or
(b) make a replacement order.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a requirement for the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) to review pro-competition orders, including replacement orders, to determine whether to revoke or replace them.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially impact the economic landscape by ensuring that pro-competition orders are regularly reviewed and updated as necessary, promoting a more competitive market environment.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 4—Pro-competition interventions</subject>

   <quote>The CMA may accept an appropriate commitment from a designated undertaking as to its conduct in respect of an adverse effect on competition or a detrimental effect on UK users or UK customers that the CMA considers has resulted, or may be expected to result, from an adverse effect on competition.</quote>

   <summary>The bill allows the CMA to accept commitments from designated undertakings regarding their conduct in relation to adverse effects on competition or detrimental effects on UK users or customers.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially impact the economic landscape by allowing the CMA to directly influence the conduct of designated undertakings, promoting a more competitive market environment.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 5—Mergers</subject>

   <quote>A relevant person (in this Chapter, “P”) must report an event to which subsection (2) or (3) applies (a “reportable event”) to the CMA before the event takes place.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a requirement for relevant persons to report certain events, referred to as "reportable events", to the CMA before they take place.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially impact the economic landscape by ensuring that the CMA is informed of significant events before they occur, allowing it to take appropriate action to maintain a competitive market environment.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulation of Mergers in Digital Markets</subject>

   <quote>(3) The Secretary of State may by regulations make further provision about how
the value of—
(a) consideration,
(b) capital, or
(c) assets, 25
is to be calculated for the purposes of this Chapter.</quote>

   <quote>(4) The Secretary of State must consult the CMA before making regulations under
subsection (3).</quote>

   <quote>(5) Regulations under subsection (3) are subject to the negative procedure.</quote>

   <summary>The Secretary of State is given the power to make further regulations about how the value of consideration, capital, or assets is to be calculated for the purposes of this Chapter. The Secretary of State must consult the CMA before making these regulations, and these regulations are subject to the negative procedure.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could have significant implications for the digital market, potentially affecting the valuation of digital assets and companies. This could impact the economic landscape of the digital market.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulation of Mergers in Digital Markets</subject>

   <quote>(1) The CMA must by notice make provision setting out—
(a) the information which a report for the purposes of section 56(1) must
contain;
(b) the form in which such a report must be made.</quote>

   <quote>(2) The notice may not require a report to contain information other than 35
information which the CMA considers necessary to allow it to determine
whether to—
(a) begin an investigation for the purposes of deciding whether to make
40
a reference under section 33 of EA 2002 in relation to a reportable
event, or
(b) make an initial enforcement order under section 72 of that Act in
relation to a reportable event.</quote>

   <summary>The CMA is required to make provision setting out the information which a report for the purposes of section 56(1) must contain and the form in which such a report must be made. The notice may not require a report to contain information other than information which the CMA considers necessary to allow it to determine whether to begin an investigation or make an initial enforcement order in relation to a reportable event.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could have significant implications for the digital market, potentially affecting the process of reporting and investigating mergers. This could impact the economic landscape of the digital market.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulation of Mergers in Digital Markets</subject>

   <quote>(1) Two or more persons may comply with the duty in section 56(1) by making
a joint report to the CMA.</quote>

   <quote>(2) For the purposes of this Chapter, where a designated undertaking is part of
a group—
(a) anything which a member of a group does or fails to do is to be treated 15
as being done or not done by each member of the group;
(b) each member of a group is to be treated as providing the combined
consideration provided by all members of the group;
(c)
20
each member of a group is to be treated as holding the combined
interests or rights of all members of the group.</quote>

   <summary>Two or more persons may comply with the duty in section 56(1) by making a joint report to the CMA. For the purposes of this Chapter, where a designated undertaking is part of a group, anything which a member of a group does or fails to do is to be treated as being done or not done by each member of the group. Each member of a group is to be treated as providing the combined consideration provided by all members of the group and holding the combined interests or rights of all members of the group.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could have significant implications for the digital market, potentially affecting the process of reporting and investigating mergers. This could impact the economic landscape of the digital market.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 6—Investigatory powers etc and compliance reports</subject>

   <quote>68 Power to require information</quote>
   <quote>69 Requirement to name a senior manager</quote>
   <quote>70 Power of access</quote>
   <quote>71 Power to interview</quote>
   <quote>72 Use of interview statements in prosecution</quote>
   <quote>73 Power to enter business premises without a warrant</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces new investigatory powers for the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA). These include the power to require information, require a senior manager to be named, access business premises, interview individuals, use interview statements in prosecution, and enter business premises without a warrant.</summary>

   <impact>4</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      The new powers could potentially infringe on privacy rights, depending on how they are implemented and used.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      These changes could have significant impacts on businesses operating in digital markets, potentially increasing regulatory burdens and compliance costs.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The new powers could significantly affect legal processes, particularly in relation to investigations and prosecutions in the digital market sector.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 74: Power to enter premises under a warrant</subject>
   <quote>(1) On an application made to it by the CMA for the purposes of a breach investigation, the court or the Tribunal may issue a warrant if it is satisfied that—
(a) there are reasonable grounds for suspecting that there is information on or accessible from any premises which is relevant to the breach investigation (“information of the relevant kind”), and
(b) one or both of the following applies—
(i) the exercise by the CMA of another digital markets investigation power has not resulted in the CMA being given the information of the relevant kind;
(ii) there are reasonable grounds for suspecting that there is no other digital markets investigation power the exercise of which would result in the CMA being given the information of the relevant kind.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes a new power for the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) to apply for a warrant to enter premises for a breach investigation if there are reasonable grounds for suspicion. This power is applicable if other digital markets investigation powers have not yielded the necessary information or if there are reasonable grounds to suspect that no other power would yield the necessary information.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 74: Power to enter premises under a warrant</subject>
   <quote>(2) A warrant under this section authorises a named officer of the CMA (“the authorised officer”), and any other of the CMA’s officers whom the CMA has authorised in writing to accompany the authorised officer, to—
(a) enter the premises specified in the warrant, using such force as is reasonably necessary;
(b) take onto the premises such equipment as appears to the authorised officer to be necessary;
(c) search the premises for information appearing to be information of the relevant kind;
(d) operate any equipment found on the premises for the purpose of producing information;
(e) require any person on the premises to provide such assistance as the authorised officer may reasonably require (including providing passwords or encryption keys and operating equipment on the premises);
(f) require any person on the premises to give information to the authorised officer;
(g) require any person on the premises to state, to the best of their knowledge and belief, where information appearing to be of the relevant kind may be found;
(h) take copies of, or extracts from, any information appearing to be information of the relevant kind;
(i) take possession of any information appearing to be information of the relevant kind that is produced under paragraph (d) or given to the authorised officer under paragraph (f);
(j) take possession of any other information appearing to be information of the relevant kind if—
(i) such action appears to be necessary for preserving the information or preventing interference with it, or
(ii) it is not reasonably practicable to take copies of the information on the premises;
(k) take any other steps which appear to be necessary for the purpose of preserving any information appearing to be information of the relevant kind or preventing interference with it.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes a new power for the CMA to enter premises under a warrant, use necessary force, bring equipment, search for and operate equipment to produce information, require assistance from people on the premises, take copies or possession of relevant information, and take steps to preserve information or prevent interference with it.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 76: Amendments to the Criminal Justice and Police Act 2001</subject>
   <quote>(1) The Criminal Justice and Police Act 2001 is amended as follows.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the Criminal Justice and Police Act 2001, though the specific amendments are not detailed in this excerpt.</summary>
   <impact>Unknown</impact>
   <clarity>1</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 78: Reports by skilled persons</subject>
   <quote>(1) The CMA may exercise the powers in this section in relation to a designated undertaking or an undertaking which is the subject of an SMS investigation (in either case, “U”) for the purposes of exercising, or deciding whether to exercise, any of its digital markets functions.
(2) The CMA may appoint a skilled person to provide it with a report in a specified form about matters relevant to the purposes for which the powers under this section are or may be exercised (“the relevant matters”).</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes a new power for the CMA to appoint a skilled person to provide a report about matters relevant to the exercise of its digital markets functions.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 78</subject>
   <quote>(6) Where the skilled person is to be appointed by U, U may not make an 30
appointment unless the CMA has approved in writing—
(a) the identity of the skilled person, and
(b) the terms on which they will be appointed, including in relation to
their remuneration and expenses.</quote>
   <quote>(12) It is the duty of—
(a) U, and 15
(b) any person connected to (see section 116(3)) U,
to give a skilled person who has been appointed under this section all such
assistance (including access to such business premises (see section 70(7)),
20
equipment, services, information and individuals) as the skilled person may
reasonably require to prepare the report.</quote>
   <quote>(13) The duty in section 78(12) does not include a duty to give access to premises,
equipment or individuals outside the United Kingdom.
(14) But the duty in section 78(12) does include a duty to give access to information
25
and services whether stored or provided within or outside the United
Kingdom.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes that a skilled person can be appointed by an entity (U) only with the approval of the CMA. This skilled person will have access to necessary resources to prepare a report. However, the duty to provide access does not extend to premises, equipment, or individuals outside the UK, but it does include access to information and services whether stored or provided within or outside the UK.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially increase the oversight and regulation of entities, potentially impacting their operations and costs.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially increase the accountability and transparency of entities, potentially impacting legal processes and outcomes.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Penalties for non-compliance with conduct requirements and investigative requirements</subject>

   <quote>The CMA may impose a penalty on an undertaking where the CMA considers that the undertaking has, without reasonable excuse, failed to comply with a conduct requirement under section 19.</quote>
   <quote>The CMA may impose a penalty on a person where it considers that the person has, without reasonable excuse—
(a) failed to comply with a requirement imposed by or under Chapter 6,
(b) given information which is false or misleading in a material particular in connection with any function of the CMA under this Part, or
(c) given information which is false or misleading in a material particular to another person knowing that the information was to be used for the purpose of giving information to the CMA in connection with any function of the CMA under this Part.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces penalties for undertakings and individuals who fail to comply with conduct requirements or investigative requirements, or who provide false or misleading information in connection with any function of the CMA under this Part.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change could potentially increase accountability and compliance within the digital markets, as it introduces penalties for non-compliance and for providing false or misleading information.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      The imposition of penalties could have financial implications for undertakings and individuals who fail to comply with the requirements.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Amount of penalties</subject>

   <quote>The amount of a penalty imposed on a person under section 84 may be such amount as the CMA considers appropriate, provided it does not exceed the amounts set out in subsection (4).</quote>
   <quote>The amount of a penalty imposed on a person under section 86 may be such amount as the CMA considers appropriate, provided it does not exceed the amounts set out in subsections (3) and (6).</quote>

   <summary>The bill sets out the amounts for penalties that can be imposed on a person under sections 84 and 86. The amount is to be determined by the CMA, provided it does not exceed the amounts set out in the respective subsections.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change provides a clear framework for the imposition of penalties, which could potentially increase fairness and transparency in the enforcement of the Act.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      The imposition of penalties could have financial implications for undertakings and individuals who fail to comply with the requirements.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Statement of policy on penalties</subject>

   <quote>The CMA must prepare and publish a statement of policy in relation to the exercise of powers to impose a penalty under sections 84 and 86.</quote>

   <summary>The bill requires the CMA to prepare and publish a statement of policy in relation to the exercise of powers to impose a penalty under sections 84 and 86. This statement must include considerations relevant to the determination of whether to impose a penalty and the nature and amount of any such penalty.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change could potentially increase transparency and predictability in the enforcement of the Act, as it requires the CMA to publish a statement of policy on penalties.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Monetary penalties: criminal proceedings and convictions</subject>
   <quote>(1) The CMA may not impose a penalty on a person under section 86 in relation
25
to an act or omission which constitutes an offence under section 92, 93 or 94
if the person has, in relation to that act or omission, been found guilty of that
offence.
(2) A person may not be found guilty of an offence under section 92, 93 or 94
by virtue of an act or omission if the person has paid a penalty imposed
under section 86 in relation to that act or omission.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes that the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) cannot impose a penalty on a person for an act or omission that constitutes an offence under sections 92, 93, or 94 if the person has already been found guilty of that offence. Similarly, a person cannot be found guilty of an offence under these sections if they have already paid a penalty for that act or omission.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially streamline the legal process by preventing double punishment for the same offence.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Offences</subject>
   <quote>92 Destroying or falsifying information
(1) A person (“P”) commits an offence if, having been required to give information
to the CMA or any other person under a provision of Chapter 6, P—
(a)
35
intentionally or recklessly destroys or otherwise disposes of it, falsifies
it or conceals it, or
(b) causes or permits its destruction, disposal, falsification or concealment.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new offence for intentionally or recklessly destroying, disposing of, falsifying, or concealing information that a person has been required to give to the CMA or any other person under a provision of Chapter 6. It also makes it an offence to cause or permit the destruction, disposal, falsification, or concealment of such information.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially increase accountability and transparency in digital markets.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Offences by officers of a body corporate etc</subject>
   <quote>(1) If an offence under section 92, 93 or 94 committed by a body corporate is
proved—
(a) to have been committed with the consent or connivance of an officer 30
of the body corporate, or
(b) to be attributable to neglect on the part of an officer of the body
corporate,
35
the officer as well as the body corporate is guilty of the offence and liable to
be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes that if a body corporate commits an offence under sections 92, 93, or 94, and it is proven that the offence was committed with the consent or connivance of an officer of the body corporate, or is attributable to neglect on the part of an officer of the body corporate, then the officer as well as the body corporate is guilty of the offence and liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially increase accountability within corporations and deter corporate misconduct.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 7—Enforcement and appeals</subject>

   <quote>(2) A CMA breach decision becomes final—
(a) when the time for appealing against the decision expires without an
appeal having been brought, or
(b) where an appeal has been brought against the decision, when—
(i) the appeal and any further appeal in relation to the decision 5
has been decided or has otherwise ended, and
(ii) the time for appealing against the result of the appeal or further
appeal has expired without another appeal having been
brought.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that a decision by the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) becomes final either when the time for appealing against the decision expires without an appeal having been brought, or when an appeal and any further appeal has been decided or has otherwise ended, and the time for appealing against the result of the appeal or further appeal has expired without another appeal having been brought.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially affect the justice system by providing a clear timeline for when a CMA decision becomes final, which could impact the length and process of legal proceedings.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 7—Enforcement and appeals</subject>

   <quote>(5) Rules of court or Tribunal rules may make provision in respect of assistance 15
to be given by the CMA to the appropriate court or the Tribunal in
proceedings brought otherwise than by the CMA in respect of a breach, or
an alleged breach, of a relevant requirement.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that allows for court or Tribunal rules to make provision for the CMA to assist the appropriate court or the Tribunal in proceedings brought in respect of a breach, or an alleged breach, of a relevant requirement.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially affect the justice system by allowing for the CMA to assist in court or Tribunal proceedings, which could impact the process and outcomes of these proceedings.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 7—Enforcement and appeals</subject>

   <quote>102 Applications for review etc 20
(1) A person with a sufficient interest in any decision to which subsection (2)
applies may apply to the Tribunal in accordance with Tribunal rules for a
review of that decision.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that allows a person with a sufficient interest in any decision to apply to the Tribunal for a review of that decision.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially affect the justice system by providing a mechanism for individuals to seek a review of a decision, which could impact the outcomes of these decisions and the process of legal proceedings.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 8—Administration etc</subject>

   <quote>103 Extension etc of periods
(1)
35
The CMA may publish a notice extending a relevant investigation period or
a final offer period by a period of up to 3 months where it considers that
there are special reasons for doing so.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that allows the CMA to extend a relevant investigation period or a final offer period by up to 3 months if it considers that there are special reasons for doing so.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially affect the justice system by providing the CMA with the ability to extend investigation periods, which could impact the length and process of legal proceedings.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 8—Administration etc</subject>

   <quote>105 Exercise and delegation of functions
(1) The CMA may make a reference to the CMA chair for the constitution of a
group under Schedule 4 to ERRA 2013 in respect of any non-reserved digital
markets function.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that allows the CMA to make a reference to the CMA chair for the constitution of a group in respect of any non-reserved digital markets function.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially affect the justice system by providing the CMA with the ability to delegate functions, which could impact the process and outcomes of legal proceedings.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Sub-paragraphs (2) and (2A) of the CMA Board</subject>
   <quote>A committee or sub-committee of the CMA Board may not be authorised to carry out any of the functions listed in sub-paragraph (2A) unless— (a) the committee or sub-committee includes— (i) at least two members of the Board who are not members of the CMA’s staff, or (ii) the chair and at least one member of the Board who is not a member of the CMA’s staff, and (b) at least half of the members of the committee or sub-committee are— (i) members of the Board who are not members of the CMA’s staff, or (ii) members of the CMA panel.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes a change to the composition of committees or sub-committees of the CMA Board. It stipulates that such committees cannot be authorised to carry out any functions unless they include at least two members of the Board who are not CMA staff, or the chair and at least one non-staff Board member. Additionally, at least half of the committee members must be either non-staff Board members or members of the CMA panel.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulatory coordination and information sharing</subject>
   <quote>The CMA must consult the FCA on a proposal to exercise a regulatory digital markets function in respect of a matter where the CMA considers the matter is a matter in relation to which the CMA and the FCA may have concurrent functions.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes that the CMA must consult with the FCA when proposing to exercise a regulatory function in the digital markets where both the CMA and FCA may have concurrent functions. Similar provisions are made for consultation with OFCOM, the Information Commissioner, the Bank of England, and the PRA.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Power to charge levy</subject>
   <quote>The CMA may require an undertaking to pay it a levy in respect of a chargeable year during the whole or part of which the undertaking is a designated undertaking.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes that the CMA may require an undertaking to pay a levy for a chargeable year during which the undertaking is a designated undertaking. The amount of the levy will be calculated according to rules made by the CMA.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Levy rules for the CMA's digital markets functions</subject>

   <quote>(4) The levy rules must—
(a) secure that the aggregate amount payable in respect of a chargeable
year is not to exceed the costs which the CMA incurs in exercising its
digital markets functions during that year;
(b) make provision about how the aggregate amount payable in respect
of a chargeable year is to be divided between the undertakings which
are designated undertakings for the whole or part of that year;
(c)
secure that where an undertaking is a designated undertaking for only
part of a chargeable year, the amount of the levy payable by that
undertaking in respect of that chargeable year is proportionately
reduced;
(d) set out how the CMA is to estimate the costs which it expects to incur
in exercising its digital markets functions during a chargeable year;
(e) set out how the CMA is to calculate the costs which it actually incurs 
in exercising its digital markets functions during a chargeable year;
(f) make provision about the repayment or crediting of any amounts of
levy paid in respect of a chargeable year on the basis of the CMA’s
estimate of the costs it would incur in exercising its digital markets
functions during that year where the CMA’s estimated costs exceed
the CMA’s actual costs of exercising those functions during that year;
(g) secure that any repayment or crediting in respect of a chargeable year
in accordance with provision made under paragraph (f), so far as
relating to an undertaking, is in proportion to the amount paid by
that undertaking in respect of that year;
(h) make provision about the charging of amounts of levy in respect of
a chargeable year where the CMA’s actual costs of exercising its digital
markets functions during that year exceed the costs which the CMA
estimated it would incur;
(i) secure that, where an undertaking is required to pay an amount of levy in respect of a chargeable year in accordance with provision made
under paragraph (h), the amount which the undertaking is required
to pay is in proportion to the amount already paid by the undertaking
in respect of that year;
(j) make provision about the administration of the levy.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes new rules for levies related to the Competition and Markets Authority's (CMA) digital markets functions. These rules include provisions for calculating and dividing the aggregate amount payable, estimating and calculating the CMA's costs, and administering the levy. The rules also provide for the repayment or crediting of any amounts of levy paid in excess of the CMA’s actual costs.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">The proposed changes could have significant economic implications for digital market undertakings, as they will be required to pay levies to cover the CMA's costs. The rules also provide for a fair distribution of costs and ensure that overpayments are credited or repaid.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Chapter 1 of Part 1 of CA 1998 (agreements), section 2</subject>
   <quote>In Chapter 1 of Part 1 of CA 1998 (agreements), section 2 (agreements etc preventing, restricting or distorting competition) is amended as follows.</quote>
   <quote>For subsection (1) substitute—
“(1) Subject to section 3, agreements between undertakings, decisions by associations of undertakings or concerted practices which have as their object or effect the prevention, restriction or distortion of competition within the United Kingdom and which—
(a) in the case of agreements, decisions or practices implemented, or intended to be implemented in the United Kingdom, may affect trade in the United Kingdom, or
(b) in any other case, are likely to have an immediate, substantial and foreseeable effect on trade within the United Kingdom, are prohibited unless they are exempt in accordance with the provisions of this Part.”</quote>
   <quote>Omit subsection (3).</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes an amendment to section 2 of Chapter 1 of Part 1 of CA 1998, which deals with agreements that prevent, restrict or distort competition. The amendment expands the scope of the prohibition to include not only agreements implemented or intended to be implemented in the UK but also those that are likely to have an immediate, substantial and foreseeable effect on trade within the UK. The bill also proposes the removal of subsection (3).</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This amendment could potentially have a significant impact on businesses operating in the UK, particularly those involved in international trade. It could lead to increased scrutiny of their agreements and practices, and potentially result in penalties for non-compliance.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 3 of Part 1 of CA 1998 (competition: investigation and enforcement)</subject>
   <quote>Chapter 3 of Part 1 of CA 1998 (competition: investigation and enforcement) is amended as follows.</quote>
   <quote>After section 25A insert—
“25B Duty to preserve documents relevant to investigations
(1) Subsection (2) applies where a person knows or suspects that an investigation by the CMA under section 25 is being or is likely to be carried out.
(2) The person must not—
(a) falsify, conceal, destroy or otherwise dispose of, or
(b) cause or permit the falsification, concealment, destruction or disposal of, a document which the person knows or suspects is or would be relevant to the investigation.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a new section (25B) into Chapter 3 of Part 1 of CA 1998, which deals with competition investigation and enforcement. This new section imposes a duty on individuals to preserve documents relevant to investigations by the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA).</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This insertion could potentially strengthen the enforcement of competition law by ensuring that relevant documents are preserved and not tampered with during investigations.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 28 of CA 1998 (power to enter business premises under a warrant)</subject>
   <quote>Section 28 of CA 1998 (power to enter business premises under a warrant) is amended as follows.</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (1)—
(a) in paragraph (a), in the words before sub-paragraph (i), after “there are on” insert “or accessible from”;
(b) in paragraph (b), in sub-paragraph (i), after “there are on” insert “or accessible from”;
(c) in paragraph (c), after “there are on” insert “or accessible from”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes an amendment to section 28 of CA 1998, which deals with the power to enter business premises under a warrant. The amendment expands the scope of this power to include not only documents that are on the premises but also those that are accessible from the premises.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This amendment could potentially strengthen the enforcement of competition law by allowing investigators to access a wider range of documents during their investigations.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 28 and 28A of CA 1998</subject>
   <quote>In subsection (2)—
(a)
35
in paragraph (f) omit “and which the named officer considers relates
to any matter relevant to the investigation,”;
(b) after that paragraph insert—
“(g) to operate any equipment found on the premises for
the purposes of producing such information in such a
form;
(h) to require any person on the premises to give the named 5
officer any assistance the named officer may reasonably
require (including for the purposes of paragraphs (f)
and (g));
(i)
10
to take copies of, or take possession of, anything
produced in accordance with paragraph (f) or (g) which
the named officer considers relates to any matter
relevant to the investigation.”</quote>
   <summary>The amendment expands the powers of the named officer during an investigation. The officer can now operate any equipment found on the premises to produce information, require any person on the premises to assist the officer, and take copies or possession of anything produced that the officer considers relevant to the investigation.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The amendment could potentially increase the efficiency and effectiveness of investigations, but it also raises concerns about potential abuses of power and violations of privacy rights.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 46 of CA 1998</subject>
   <quote>In section 46 of CA 1998 (appealable decisions), in subsection (3)—
(a) after paragraph (h) insert—
“(ha) to make directions under section 35,
(hb) not to make directions under section 35,”; 
(b) in the words after paragraph (i), for “, 33 or 35” substitute “or 33”.</quote>
   <summary>The amendment expands the list of appealable decisions to include decisions to make or not make directions under section 35.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The amendment could potentially increase the fairness of the legal process by allowing more decisions to be appealed.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 47C of CA 1998</subject>
   <quote>In section 47C of CA 1998 (collective proceedings: damages and costs), before
subsection (2) insert—
“(1) The Tribunal may not award exemplary damages in collective
proceedings.”</quote>
   <summary>The insertion prohibits the Tribunal from awarding exemplary damages in collective proceedings.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The insertion could potentially limit the ability of plaintiffs in collective proceedings to receive full compensation for their damages.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>RED</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 39 and Section 40 of the Enterprise Act 2002</subject>
   <quote>“(7A) An extension under subsection (2A) continues in force until— 5
(a) the end of the extension period, or
(b) an earlier time if, before end of that period—
(i) the CMA and the persons carrying on the
10
enterprises concerned agree that the extension
should be cancelled with effect from the earlier
time, and
(ii) the CMA publishes its decision to cancel the
extension with effect from that time.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the Enterprise Act 2002, specifically to sections 39 and 40, to allow for the extension of certain periods under mutual agreement between the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) and the concerned enterprises. The extension can be cancelled earlier if both parties agree and the CMA publishes its decision.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">The amendment could potentially impact the duration of investigations or other processes involving the CMA and enterprises, which could have economic implications for the businesses involved.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 96(5) of the Enterprise Act 2002</subject>
   <quote>In Chapter 5 of Part 3 of EA 2002 (mergers: supplementary), in section 96(5)
(merger notices), for “in the London, Edinburgh and Belfast Gazettes”
substitute “online”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 96(5) of the Enterprise Act 2002 to change the publication of merger notices from the London, Edinburgh and Belfast Gazettes to online platforms.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially increase the accessibility and visibility of merger notices, impacting businesses and investors.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Freedom of Information">The amendment could potentially increase the accessibility of information to the public.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 131B and Section 131C of the Enterprise Act 2002</subject>
   <quote>In section 131B (market studies and the making of decisions to refer: 30
time-limits) omit subsections (1) to (3).
(3) In section 131C (time-limits under section 131B: supplementary)—
(a) in subsection (1) omit paragraph (a);
(b) in subsection (2) omit paragraph (a) and the “or” after it.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend sections 131B and 131C of the Enterprise Act 2002, removing certain subsections and paragraphs related to time-limits for market studies and decisions to refer.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">The removal of these time-limits could potentially impact the duration and process of market studies and decisions to refer, which could have implications for businesses and the economy.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 162A(8) of the Competition Act 1998</subject>
   <quote>The CMA must give the Secretary of State such advice as it considers appropriate for the purposes mentioned in section 142(2) or 147A(2) (as the case may be) in relation to— (a) any possible variation or release by the Secretary of State of an enforcement undertaking accepted by the Secretary of State; (b) any possible new enforcement undertaking to be accepted by the Secretary of State under that section so as to supersede another enforcement undertaking given to the Secretary of State; (c) any possible variation or revocation by the Secretary of State of an enforcement order made by the Secretary of State; (d) any possible enforcement undertaking to be accepted by the Secretary of State instead of an enforcement order, or any possible enforcement order to be made by the Secretary of State instead of an enforcement undertaking accepted under that section.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes that the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) must provide advice to the Secretary of State on various enforcement undertakings and orders. This includes advice on possible variations, releases, new undertakings, and revocations.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially increase the power of the Secretary of State by providing them with advice from the CMA on enforcement undertakings and orders.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially affect the enforcement of competition law by providing the Secretary of State with advice on enforcement undertakings and orders.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 194 of the Enterprise Act 2002</subject>
   <quote>Section 194 of EA 2002 (power to enter premises under a warrant) is amended as follows. (2) In subsection (1), in paragraph (a), after “there are on” insert “or accessible from”. (3) In subsection (2)— (a) in paragraph (d) omit “and which the named officer considers relates to any matter relevant to the investigation,”; (b) after that paragraph insert— “(e) to operate any equipment found on the premises for the purposes of producing such information in such a form; (f) to require any person on the premises to give the named officer any assistance the named officer may reasonably require (including for the purposes of paragraphs (d) and (e)); (g) to take copies of, or seize, anything produced in accordance with paragraph (d) or (e) which the named officer considers relates to any matter relevant to the investigation.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to Section 194 of the Enterprise Act 2002, which deals with the power to enter premises under a warrant. The amendments include the ability to operate any equipment found on the premises to produce information, the power to require any person on the premises to provide assistance, and the power to take copies of or seize anything produced that is relevant to the investigation.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially affect the enforcement of competition law by expanding the powers of officers executing a warrant under Section 194 of the Enterprise Act 2002.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change could potentially impact the rights of individuals or businesses subject to a warrant under Section 194 of the Enterprise Act 2002, as it expands the powers of officers executing such a warrant.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 26A of the Competition Act 1998</subject>
   <quote>Section 26A of CA 1998 (investigations: power to ask questions) is amended as follows. (2) In subsection (1)— (a) in the words before paragraph (a) omit “who has a connection with a relevant undertaking”; (b) in paragraph (a), after “at a place” insert “or in a manner (which may be remote)”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to Section 26A of the Competition Act 1998, which deals with the power to ask questions during investigations. The amendments include removing the requirement for a connection with a relevant undertaking and allowing questions to be asked remotely.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially affect the enforcement of competition law by expanding the powers of investigators under Section 26A of the Competition Act 1998.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change could potentially impact the rights of individuals or businesses subject to an investigation under Section 26A of the Competition Act 1998, as it expands the powers of investigators.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Enforcement of consumer protection law, Chapter 2—Relevant infringements</subject>

   <quote>(4) It is immaterial for the purposes of the definition of “trader” in subsection
(2)—
(a) in relation to paragraph (a) of that definition, whether P is acting
5
personally or through another person acting in P’s name or on P’s
behalf;
(b) in relation to paragraph (b) of that definition, whether or not the
purposes relating to P’s business are the only or main purposes for
which the person is acting.
(5) For the purposes of this Part—
(a) references to consumers includes persons who may become consumers 10
in the future;
(b) the collective interests of consumers are capable of being harmed by
a single act or omission (as well as by repeated acts or omissions).</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a change in the definition of "trader" and "consumer". A trader can be a person acting personally or through another person acting in their name or on their behalf. The purposes relating to the trader's business do not have to be the only or main purposes for which the person is acting. The definition of consumers now includes persons who may become consumers in the future. The collective interests of consumers can be harmed by a single act or omission, as well as by repeated acts or omissions.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially have a significant impact on the digital market, as it broadens the definition of traders and consumers, potentially leading to more stringent regulations and protections for consumers.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Consultation requirements before enforcement order application</subject>
   <quote>(1) Before making an application for an enforcement order or an interim enforcement order, an enforcer must (subject to subsection (5)) engage in appropriate consultation with the person in respect of whom the order would be made (“the respondent”).</quote>
   <quote>(2) Consultation is “appropriate consultation” for the purposes of subsection (1) if it is carried out for the purposes of— (a) achieving the cessation of a relevant infringement (in a case where the infringement is occurring) and ensuring it does not recur; (b) ensuring there is no repetition of a relevant infringement in a case where the infringement has occurred; (c) ensuring that a relevant infringement does not take place in a case where the infringement has yet to occur; (d) ensuring, in the case of consultation carried out by a public designated enforcer, that the respondent is aware that an application for an enforcement order may include an application for the respondent to pay a monetary penalty.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a requirement for enforcers to engage in appropriate consultation with the respondent before making an application for an enforcement order or an interim enforcement order. The purpose of this consultation is to achieve the cessation of a relevant infringement, ensure there is no repetition of a relevant infringement, ensure that a relevant infringement does not take place, and make the respondent aware that an application for an enforcement order may include an application for the respondent to pay a monetary penalty.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Enforcement orders and undertakings</subject>
   <quote>(1) This section applies if, on an application under section 146 for an enforcement order, the court finds that the person in respect of whom the application is made (“the respondent”)— (a) has engaged, is engaging or is likely to engage in a commercial practice which constitutes a relevant infringement (“the infringing practice”), or (b) is an accessory to the infringing practice.</quote>
   <quote>(2) The court may— (a) make an enforcement order against the respondent, or (b) accept an undertaking from the respondent given under subsection (5).</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces provisions for enforcement orders and undertakings. If the court finds that the respondent has engaged, is engaging, or is likely to engage in a commercial practice which constitutes a relevant infringement, or is an accessory to the infringing practice, the court may make an enforcement order against the respondent or accept an undertaking from the respondent.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Enforcement orders: requirement to pay monetary penalty</subject>
   <quote>(1) This section applies where the court makes an enforcement order against the respondent on an application made by a public designated enforcer.</quote>
   <quote>(2) The order may, subject to subsection (3), include a requirement for the respondent to pay a monetary penalty.</quote>
   <quote>(5) The amount of a monetary penalty must be a fixed amount not exceeding £300,000 or, if higher, 10% of the total value of the turnover (if any) of the respondent.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a provision for the court to include a requirement for the respondent to pay a monetary penalty in an enforcement order. The amount of the monetary penalty must be a fixed amount not exceeding £300,000 or, if higher, 10% of the total value of the turnover of the respondent.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Interim enforcement orders and undertakings</subject>

   <quote>This section applies if—
(a) it is alleged in an application under section 146 for an interim
enforcement order that a person (“the respondent”)—
(i)
35
has engaged, is engaging or is likely to engage in a commercial
practice which constitutes a relevant infringement (“the
infringing practice”), or
(ii) is an accessory to the infringing practice,
(b) it appears to the court that if the application had been an application
for an enforcement order it would be likely to be granted, and
(c) the court considers it is expedient that the infringing practice is
prohibited or prevented immediately.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a provision for interim enforcement orders and undertakings. This applies if a person is alleged to have engaged, is engaging, or is likely to engage in a commercial practice that constitutes a relevant infringement, or is an accessory to the infringing practice. The court can make an interim enforcement order if it appears that an enforcement order would likely be granted and it is expedient to immediately prohibit or prevent the infringing practice.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change could potentially expedite the process of halting infringing practices, thereby enhancing the efficiency of the justice system.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      This could have an impact on businesses engaging in commercial practices that are deemed to be infringing, potentially leading to economic consequences for those businesses.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Online interface orders and interim online interface orders</subject>

   <quote>The CMA may apply to the appropriate court for an online interface order,
5
or an interim online interface order, if the CMA considers that a person has
engaged, is engaging or is likely to engage in a commercial practice that
constitutes a relevant infringement.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a provision for the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) to apply for an online interface order or an interim online interface order if it considers that a person has engaged, is engaging, or is likely to engage in a commercial practice that constitutes a relevant infringement.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change could potentially expedite the process of halting infringing practices in the digital space, thereby enhancing the efficiency of the justice system.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      This could have an impact on businesses engaging in commercial practices that are deemed to be infringing, potentially leading to economic consequences for those businesses.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">
      This could potentially impact digital privacy, depending on the nature of the infringing practices and the measures taken to halt them.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Enforcement of consumer protection law</subject>

   <quote>The enforcer may accept an undertaking from the respondent to do one or more of the following—</quote>
   <quote>Where the enforcer accepts an undertaking under subsection (2) the enforcer may publish the undertaking or accept a further undertaking from the respondent to do so.</quote>
   <quote>Where an enforcer has accepted from the respondent an undertaking under this section— the enforcer may accept from the respondent any such variation of the undertaking that the enforcer considers appropriate for meeting the purposes for which the undertaking was given;</quote>
   <quote>Each enforcer must keep a record of— undertakings it has accepted under this section, and reviews it has carried out into the effectiveness of such undertakings.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that an enforcer may accept an undertaking from a respondent to cease or not engage in infringing practices. The enforcer may also publish the undertaking, accept variations of the undertaking, and must keep a record of accepted undertakings and reviews of their effectiveness.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially improve the enforcement of consumer protection laws by allowing enforcers to accept undertakings from respondents, thereby providing a mechanism for respondents to cease infringing practices.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This could potentially have economic implications for businesses that are respondents, as they may need to change their practices to comply with undertakings.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Enforcement of consumer protection law</subject>

   <quote>An undertaking under section 156(2) may include a requirement to take such enhanced consumer measures as the enforcer accepting the undertaking considers just and reasonable.</quote>
   <quote>Where the respondent is required by an undertaking to take enhanced consumer measures, the undertaking may include requirements for the respondent to provide information or documents to the enforcer accepting the undertaking in order that the enforcer may determine if the respondent is taking those measures.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that an undertaking may include a requirement for the respondent to take enhanced consumer measures that the enforcer deems just and reasonable. The undertaking may also require the respondent to provide information or documents to the enforcer to determine if the respondent is taking those measures.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially improve the enforcement of consumer protection laws by allowing enforcers to require respondents to take enhanced consumer measures as part of an undertaking.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This could potentially have economic implications for businesses that are respondents, as they may need to implement enhanced consumer measures to comply with undertakings.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Enforcement of consumer protection law</subject>

   <quote>If on an application under this section the court finds that an undertaking is not being complied with, the court may do either or both of the following— make a consumer protection order (instead of making any other order it has power to make); make an order requiring the respondent to pay a monetary penalty.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that if a court finds that an undertaking is not being complied with, the court may make a consumer protection order or require the respondent to pay a monetary penalty.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially improve the enforcement of consumer protection laws by allowing courts to make consumer protection orders or impose monetary penalties if an undertaking is not being complied with.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This could potentially have economic implications for businesses that are respondents, as they may face monetary penalties for non-compliance with undertakings.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Monetary penalties under sections 159 and 160: amount</subject>

   <quote>The amount of the penalty must be—
(a) a fixed amount,
(b) an amount calculated by reference to a daily rate, or
(c) a combination of a fixed amount and an amount calculated by reference
to a daily rate.</quote>

   <quote>The penalty must not exceed— 5
(a) in the case of a fixed amount, £150,000 or, if higher, 5% of the total
value of the turnover (if any) of the respondent;
(b) in the case of an amount calculated by reference to a daily rate, £15,000
10
or, if higher, 5% of the total value of the daily turnover (if any) of the
respondent;
(c) in the case of a fixed amount and an amount calculated by reference
to a daily rate, such fixed amount and such amount per day.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a new framework for monetary penalties under sections 159 and 160. The penalty can be a fixed amount, an amount calculated by a daily rate, or a combination of both. The penalty must not exceed £150,000 or 5% of the total value of the turnover of the respondent for a fixed amount, £15,000 or 5% of the total value of the daily turnover of the respondent for an amount calculated by a daily rate, and a fixed amount and an amount per day for a combination of both.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could have a significant economic impact on businesses that are found to be in violation of the regulations outlined in sections 159 and 160. The penalties could potentially be quite large, particularly for businesses with high turnover.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could also impact the justice system by providing a clear framework for determining monetary penalties in these cases.</pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Notification requirements: applications</subject>

   <quote>Before making an application for an enforcement order or an interim
enforcement order the enforcer—
(a) must by notice inform the CMA of its intention to do so, and
(b) may only proceed to make the application after expiry of the minimum 25
period or, if sooner, after the CMA has by notice informed the enforcer
that it consents to the making of the application.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a new requirement for enforcers to notify the CMA before making an application for an enforcement order or an interim enforcement order. The enforcer can only proceed with the application after a minimum period has expired or if the CMA has given its consent.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could impact the justice system by adding a new step to the process of applying for enforcement orders and interim enforcement orders. This could potentially slow down the process, but it could also ensure that the CMA is kept informed of all such applications.</pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Appropriate court</subject>

   <quote>If the respondent has a place of business in, or carries on business in, a part 10
of the United Kingdom, the appropriate court is—
(a) the High Court or the county court in England and Wales, if the
respondent carries on business in England and Wales or has a place
of business in England and Wales;
(b) the High Court or a county court in Northern Ireland, if the respondent 15
carries on business in Northern Ireland or has a place of business in
Northern Ireland;
(c) the Court of Session or the sheriff, if the respondent carries on business
in Scotland or has a place of business in Scotland.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a new framework for determining the appropriate court for an application for a consumer protection order against a respondent in connection with a relevant infringement. The appropriate court is determined based on where the respondent has a place of business or carries on business.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could impact the justice system by providing a clear framework for determining the appropriate court in these cases. This could potentially streamline the process and ensure that cases are heard in the most appropriate venue.</pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Enhanced consumer measures: private designated enforcers</subject>

   <quote>(1) This section applies where—
(a) an enforcement order is made on the application of a private designated enforcer,
(b) an undertaking is given under section 149 on an application for an enforcement order made by a private designated enforcer, or
(c) an undertaking is given under section 156 to a private designated enforcer.
(2) The enforcement order or undertaking may include a requirement for the taking of any enhanced consumer measures only if both of the following conditions are met.
(3) The first condition is that the private designated enforcer is specified for the purposes of this section in regulations made by the Secretary of State.
(4) The second condition is that the enhanced consumer measures do not directly benefit the private designated enforcer or an associated undertaking.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision for the application of enhanced consumer measures by private designated enforcers. These measures can only be applied if the private enforcer is specified in regulations made by the Secretary of State and if the measures do not directly benefit the enforcer or an associated undertaking.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change could potentially increase the protection of consumer rights by allowing private designated enforcers to apply enhanced consumer measures. However, it also introduces a potential conflict of interest by allowing private entities to enforce consumer protection laws.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Power of CMA to investigate suspected infringements</subject>

   <quote>(1) This section applies where the CMA has reasonable grounds for suspecting that—
(a) a person has engaged, is engaging or is likely to engage in a commercial practice that constitutes a relevant infringement, or
(b) a person is an accessory to such a practice.
(2) The CMA may conduct an investigation into the matter.</quote>

   <summary>The bill grants the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) the power to investigate suspected infringements of commercial practices that constitute a relevant infringement or if a person is an accessory to such a practice.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change could potentially increase the protection of consumer rights by granting the CMA the power to investigate suspected infringements of commercial practices.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Provisional infringement notice</subject>

   <quote>(1) This section applies where—
(a) the CMA has started an investigation under section 173 that is continuing, and
(b) the condition in subsection (2) is met in respect of any person (“the respondent”) who is subject to the investigation.
(2) The condition in this subsection is met in respect of the respondent if the CMA has reasonable grounds to believe that—
(a) the respondent has engaged, is engaging or is likely to engage in a commercial practice constituting a relevant infringement (“the infringing practice”), or
(b) the respondent is an accessory to such a practice.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision for the issuance of a provisional infringement notice by the CMA during an ongoing investigation if there are reasonable grounds to believe that the respondent has engaged, is engaging or is likely to engage in a commercial practice constituting a relevant infringement or if the respondent is an accessory to such a practice.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change could potentially increase the protection of consumer rights by allowing the CMA to issue a provisional infringement notice during an ongoing investigation.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Final infringement notice</subject>

   <quote>(2) The CMA may give to the respondent a notice under this section (a “final 40 infringement notice”).</quote>
   <quote>(3) In deciding whether to give a final infringement notice the CMA must, in particular, have regard to whether the respondent has previously given an undertaking under this Chapter or Chapter 3 in respect of the acts or omissions in relation to which the final infringement notice would be given.</quote>
   <quote>(4) A final infringement notice may impose on the respondent a requirement to 5 do either or both of the following— (a) a requirement to comply with such directions as the CMA considers appropriate for or in connection with the purpose of securing that the respondent complies with section 174(5) (which may include directions to take enhanced consumer measures in accordance with section 176); (b) subject to subsection (5), a requirement to pay a monetary penalty.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces the concept of a "final infringement notice" that the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) can issue to a respondent. The decision to issue such a notice will take into account whether the respondent has previously given an undertaking in respect of the acts or omissions in question. The notice can require the respondent to comply with certain directions or pay a monetary penalty.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The introduction of a "final infringement notice" could significantly impact the enforcement of competition and consumer protection laws, providing the CMA with a new tool to ensure compliance.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">The potential for monetary penalties could have financial implications for businesses found to be in violation of competition and consumer protection laws.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Online interface notices</subject>

   <quote>(1) This section applies where the CMA is satisfied that a person has engaged, is engaging or is likely to engage in a commercial practice that constitutes a relevant infringement.</quote>
   <quote>(2) The CMA may give a notice under this section (an “online interface notice”) to— (a) the person that the CMA is satisfied has engaged, is engaging or is likely to engage in the commercial practice constituting the relevant infringement, or (b) any other person (subject to subsection (3)).</quote>
   <quote>(4) An online interface notice may contain whatever directions the CMA considers appropriate for the purpose of requiring the person to whom it is given to do, or to co-operate with another person so that person can do, one or more of the following— (a) remove content from, or modify content on, an online interface; (b) disable or restrict access to an online interface; (c) display a warning to consumers accessing an online interface; (d) delete a fully qualified domain name and take any steps necessary to facilitate the registration of that domain name by the CMA.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces the concept of an "online interface notice" that the CMA can issue if it is satisfied that a person has engaged, is engaging, or is likely to engage in a commercial practice that constitutes a relevant infringement. The notice can require the person to take certain actions, such as removing or modifying content on an online interface, disabling or restricting access to an online interface, displaying a warning to consumers, or deleting a domain name.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The introduction of "online interface notices" could significantly impact the enforcement of competition and consumer protection laws in the digital space, providing the CMA with a new tool to ensure compliance.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The ability for the CMA to require changes to online interfaces could have implications for digital privacy, depending on the nature of the required changes.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Undertakings</subject>

   <quote>(1) This section applies where the CMA— (a) has started an investigation under section 173 which is continuing, and (b) has not given a final infringement notice or an online interface notice in relation to the matter under investigation.</quote>
   <quote>(2) The CMA may accept an undertaking under this section in connection with that matter from any person whom the CMA believes— (a) has engaged, is engaging or is likely to engage in a commercial practice that constitutes a relevant infringement (“the infringing practice”), or (b) is an accessory to such a practice.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces the concept of an "undertaking" that the CMA can accept from a person whom it believes has engaged, is engaging, or is likely to engage in a commercial practice that constitutes a relevant infringement, or is an accessory to such a practice. This applies when the CMA has started an investigation that is continuing and has not yet issued a final infringement notice or an online interface notice.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The introduction of "undertakings" could significantly impact the enforcement of competition and consumer protection laws, providing the CMA with a new tool to ensure compliance.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">The potential for undertakings could have financial implications for businesses found to be in violation of competition and consumer protection laws, depending on the nature of the undertaking.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Provisional breach of undertakings enforcement notice</subject>
   <quote>This section applies where—
(a) the CMA has accepted an undertaking from a person (“the
respondent”) under section 178, and
(b) the CMA has reasonable grounds to believe that the respondent has 5
failed to comply with one or more of the terms of the undertaking.
(2) The CMA may give to the respondent a notice under this section (a
“provisional breach of undertakings enforcement notice”).</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new enforcement mechanism, the "provisional breach of undertakings enforcement notice", which the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) can issue if it believes a person has failed to comply with an undertaking.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Final breach of undertakings enforcement notice</subject>
   <quote>This section applies where—
(a) the CMA has given to the respondent a provisional breach of
undertakings enforcement notice under section 181,
(b) the time for the respondent to make representations to the CMA in 5
accordance with that notice has expired, and
(c) after considering such representations (if any), the CMA is satisfied
that the respondent has failed to comply with one or more of the terms
of the undertaking.
(2) The CMA may give to the respondent a notice under this section (a “final 10
breach of undertakings enforcement notice”).</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a "final breach of undertakings enforcement notice", which the CMA can issue if, after considering any representations, it is satisfied that a person has failed to comply with an undertaking.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Monetary penalties under section 182: amount</subject>
   <quote>This section applies in relation to a requirement imposed on the respondent
to pay a monetary penalty under a final breach of undertakings enforcement
notice.
(2) The amount of the penalty must be—
(a) a fixed amount,
(b) an amount calculated by reference to a daily rate, or
(c)
5
a combination of a fixed amount and an amount calculated by reference
to a daily rate.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision for monetary penalties, which can be imposed on a person who fails to comply with a final breach of undertakings enforcement notice. The penalty can be a fixed amount, an amount calculated by reference to a daily rate, or a combination of both.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Provisional breach of directions enforcement notice</subject>
   <quote>This section applies where—
(a)
25
an enforcement direction has been given to a person (“the respondent”),
and
(b) the CMA has reasonable grounds to believe that the respondent has
without reasonable excuse failed to comply with the direction (fully
or to any respect).
(2)
30
The CMA may give to the respondent a notice under this section (a
“provisional breach of directions enforcement notice”).</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a "provisional breach of directions enforcement notice", which the CMA can issue if it believes a person has failed to comply with an enforcement direction without reasonable excuse.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 4—Direct enforcement powers of CMA</subject>

   <quote>(6) In this Chapter “enforcement direction” means a direction given in—
(a) a final infringement notice,
(b) an online interface notice, or 15
(c) a final breach of undertakings enforcement notice.</quote>

   <quote>185 Final breach of directions enforcement notice
(1) This section applies where—
(a)
20
the CMA has given to the respondent a provisional breach of directions
enforcement notice under section 184 in respect of a suspected failure
to comply with an enforcement direction,</quote>

   <quote>(2) The CMA may give to the respondent a notice under this section (a “final
breach of directions enforcement notice”).
(3)
30
A final breach of directions enforcement notice is a notice that imposes on
the respondent a requirement to pay a monetary penalty.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces the concept of an "enforcement direction" which can be given in a final infringement notice, an online interface notice, or a final breach of undertakings enforcement notice. The CMA can give a final breach of directions enforcement notice if a respondent fails to comply with an enforcement direction. This notice imposes a monetary penalty on the respondent.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">The introduction of monetary penalties for non-compliance with enforcement directions could have significant economic implications for businesses operating in digital markets.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change strengthens the enforcement powers of the CMA, potentially leading to more effective regulation of digital markets.</pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 4—Direct enforcement powers of CMA</subject>

   <quote>186 Monetary penalties under section 185: amount
(1) This section applies in relation to a requirement imposed on the respondent
to pay a monetary penalty under a final breach of directions enforcement
notice.
(2) The amount of the penalty must be— 10
(a) a fixed amount,
(b) an amount calculated by reference to a daily rate, or
(c) a combination of a fixed amount and an amount calculated by reference
to a daily rate.</quote>

   <quote>(3) The penalty imposed on a person must not exceed— 15
(a) in the case of a fixed amount, £150,000 or, if higher, 5% of the total
value of the turnover (if any) of the respondent;
(b) in the case of an amount calculated by reference to a daily rate, £15,000
20
or, if higher, 5% of the total value of the daily turnover (if any) of the
respondent;
(c) in the case of a fixed amount and an amount calculated by reference
to a daily rate, such fixed amount and such amount per day.</quote>

   <summary>The bill specifies the amount of monetary penalties that can be imposed under a final breach of directions enforcement notice. The penalty can be a fixed amount, an amount calculated by reference to a daily rate, or a combination of both. The penalty must not exceed £150,000 or 5% of the total value of the respondent's turnover, £15,000 or 5% of the total value of the respondent's daily turnover, or a fixed amount and an amount per day.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">The introduction of monetary penalties could have significant economic implications for businesses operating in digital markets, particularly if they fail to comply with enforcement directions.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change strengthens the enforcement powers of the CMA, potentially leading to more effective regulation of digital markets.</pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Enforcement of consumer protection law, Chapter 4—Direct enforcement powers of CMA</subject>

   <quote>(1) The CMA must prepare and publish a statement of policy in relation to the exercise of powers to impose a monetary penalty under this Chapter.</quote>
   <quote>(2) The statement must include a statement about the considerations relevant to the determination of— (a) whether to impose a penalty under this Chapter, and (b) the nature and amount of any such penalty.</quote>
   <quote>(3) The CMA may revise its statement of policy and, where it does so, must publish the revised statement.</quote>
   <quote>(4) In preparing or revising its statement of policy the CMA must consult— (a) the Secretary of State, and (b) such other persons as the CMA considers appropriate.</quote>
   <quote>(5) A statement of policy, or revised statement, may not be published under this section without the approval of the Secretary of State.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) must prepare and publish a statement of policy regarding the imposition of monetary penalties. This statement must include considerations relevant to the decision of whether to impose a penalty and the nature and amount of any such penalty. The CMA may revise this statement and must publish any revisions. The CMA must consult the Secretary of State and other appropriate persons when preparing or revising this statement. The statement or any revisions cannot be published without the approval of the Secretary of State.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially increase transparency and accountability in the enforcement of consumer protection law by the CMA. It could also provide clearer guidelines for businesses regarding the imposition of monetary penalties.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">The requirement for the Secretary of State's approval before publishing the statement or any revisions could potentially increase the political oversight of the CMA's enforcement powers.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Enforcement of consumer protection law, Chapter 4—Direct enforcement powers of CMA</subject>

   <quote>(1) The CMA must keep a record of— (a) undertakings it has accepted and enforcement directions it has given, and (b) reviews it has carried out in relation to the effectiveness of such undertakings and directions.</quote>
   <quote>(2) If requested to do so by the Secretary of State, the CMA must prepare a report on— (a) the effectiveness of undertakings and enforcement directions, and (b) the number and outcome of appeals brought under section 195.</quote>
   <quote>(3) The CMA must— (a) provide to the Secretary of State a report prepared under this section, and (b) publish the report in such manner as the CMA considers appropriate.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that the CMA must keep a record of undertakings it has accepted, enforcement directions it has given, and reviews it has carried out regarding the effectiveness of these undertakings and directions. If requested by the Secretary of State, the CMA must prepare a report on the effectiveness of these undertakings and directions and the number and outcome of appeals. The CMA must provide this report to the Secretary of State and publish it in an appropriate manner.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially increase transparency and accountability in the enforcement of consumer protection law by the CMA. It could also provide clearer guidelines for businesses regarding the enforcement of undertakings and directions.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">The requirement for the CMA to provide a report to the Secretary of State could potentially increase the political oversight of the CMA's enforcement powers.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Enforcement of consumer protection law, Chapter 4—Direct enforcement powers of CMA</subject>

   <quote>(1) A person to whom a relevant notice is given may appeal to the appropriate appeal court against— (a) a decision to impose a monetary penalty by virtue of the notice, (b) the nature or amount of any such penalty, or (c) the giving of directions by virtue of the notice.</quote>
   <quote>(2) The grounds for an appeal under subsection (1)(a) or (b) are that— (a) the decision to impose a monetary penalty was based on an error of fact, (b) the decision was wrong in law, (c) the amount of the penalty is unreasonable, or (d) the decision was unreasonable or wrong for any other reason.</quote>
   <quote>(3) The grounds for an appeal under subsection (1)(c) are that— (a) the decision to give the directions was based on an error of fact, (b) the decision was wrong in law, (c) the nature of the directions is unreasonable, or (d) the decision was unreasonable or wrong for any other reason.</quote>
   <quote>(4) On an appeal under this section the appropriate court may quash, confirm or vary the relevant notice.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that a person to whom a relevant notice is given may appeal to the appropriate appeal court against a decision to impose a monetary penalty, the nature or amount of any such penalty, or the giving of directions. The grounds for an appeal include that the decision was based on an error of fact, was wrong in law, was unreasonable, or was wrong for any other reason. The appropriate court may quash, confirm, or vary the relevant notice on an appeal.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially increase fairness in the enforcement of consumer protection law by the CMA by providing a mechanism for appeal against decisions to impose monetary penalties or give directions.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulations under this section</subject>

   <quote>(3) Regulations under this section may, in particular, make provision as to— 20
(a) the amounts which are, or which are not, to be treated as comprising
a person’s turnover or daily turnover;
(b) the date or dates by reference to which a person’s turnover or daily
turnover is to be determined.
(4) Regulations under this section may include provision enabling the court or 25
the CMA to determine matters of a description specified in the regulations
(including any of the matters mentioned in paragraphs (a) and (b) of
subsection (3)).
(5) Regulations under this section are subject to the negative procedure.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes regulations that will determine how a person's turnover or daily turnover is calculated and the dates by which these are determined. The court or the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) will have the power to determine matters specified in the regulations.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could have significant implications for businesses, particularly those operating in digital markets, as it could affect how their turnover is calculated and thus potentially their tax liabilities and other financial metrics.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Power to amend amounts</subject>

   <quote>198 Power to amend amounts 30
(1) The Secretary of State may by regulations amend any of the following
provisions for the purpose of substituting a different monetary amount for
an amount of fixed or daily penalty for the time being specified—
(a) section 151(5);
(b) section 161(3)(a) and (b); 35
(c) section 175(6);
(d) section 183(3)(a) and (b);
(e) section 186(3)(a) and (b);
(f) section 191(4).</quote>

   <summary>The Secretary of State is given the power to amend the monetary amounts for fixed or daily penalties specified in various sections of the Act.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could have significant implications for the enforcement of the Act, as it could affect the penalties imposed for violations.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Recovery of monetary penalties</subject>

   <quote>199 Recovery of monetary penalties
(1) This section applies where a monetary penalty imposed under Chapter 4, or 5
any part of such a penalty, has not been paid by the date on which it is
required to be paid and—
(a) an appeal to a court against the imposition of the penalty has not been
10
brought before the end of the period within which it is required to be
brought, or
(b) any such appeal that was brought has been determined, withdrawn
or otherwise disposed of.
(2) The CMA may recover from the person on whom the penalty was imposed
any of the penalty and any interest which has not been paid.
(3) Any such penalty and interest may be recovered summarily (or, in Scotland, 15
recovered) as a civil debt by the CMA.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that the CMA can recover any unpaid monetary penalties and interest as a civil debt if the penalty has not been paid by the required date and no appeal has been brought or any appeal has been determined, withdrawn or otherwise disposed of.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could have significant implications for the enforcement of the Act, as it provides a mechanism for the recovery of unpaid penalties.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Enforcement of consumer protection law, Chapter 7—Miscellaneous, Section 204</subject>

   <quote>The CMA may make rules about procedural and other matters in connection with the carrying out of its direct enforcement functions.</quote>
   <quote>Rules may provide for any of the CMA’s direct enforcement functions to be carried out on its behalf—
(a) by one or more members of the CMA Board (see Part 2 of Schedule 4 to the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Act 2013);
(b) by one or more members of the CMA Panel (see Part 3 of Schedule 4 to that Act);
(c) by one or more members of staff of the CMA;
(d) jointly by one or more of the persons mentioned in paragraphs (a) to (c).</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) may make rules about procedural and other matters in connection with the carrying out of its direct enforcement functions. These rules may provide for any of the CMA’s direct enforcement functions to be carried out on its behalf by one or more members of the CMA Board, CMA Panel, or staff of the CMA.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially streamline the enforcement of consumer protection law, leading to more efficient and effective regulation of digital markets.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially increase the power of the CMA, as it allows for more flexibility in how its enforcement functions are carried out.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Enforcement of consumer protection law, Chapter 7—Miscellaneous, Section 205</subject>

   <quote>In preparing rules the CMA must consult such persons as the CMA considers appropriate.</quote>
   <quote>The CMA may not bring a rule into operation until the rule has been approved by regulations made by the Secretary of State.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that in preparing rules, the CMA must consult such persons as it considers appropriate. Furthermore, the CMA may not bring a rule into operation until the rule has been approved by regulations made by the Secretary of State.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially increase the power of the Secretary of State, as it gives them the authority to approve or reject rules made by the CMA.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially lead to more effective regulation of digital markets, as it ensures that rules made by the CMA are subject to approval by the Secretary of State.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3—Enforcement of consumer protection law, Chapter 7—Miscellaneous, Section 206</subject>

   <quote>The CMA must prepare and publish guidance about its general approach to the carrying out of its direct enforcement functions.</quote>
   <quote>Guidance under subsection (1) must provide information about the factors that the CMA will take into account in determining—
(a) whether it will exercise a power under Chapter 4 to accept, vary or release an undertaking;
(b) in cases where the exercise of any such power is exercisable only if the CMA considers a person has acted (or failed to act) without a reasonable excuse, whether a reasonable excuse exists;
(c) in a case where a monetary penalty has not been paid (or paid in full), whether to start proceedings for recovery of the penalty.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that the CMA must prepare and publish guidance about its general approach to the carrying out of its direct enforcement functions. This guidance must provide information about the factors that the CMA will take into account in determining whether it will exercise a power under Chapter 4 to accept, vary or release an undertaking, whether a reasonable excuse exists in cases where the exercise of any such power is exercisable only if the CMA considers a person has acted (or failed to act) without a reasonable excuse, and whether to start proceedings for recovery of the penalty in a case where a monetary penalty has not been paid (or paid in full).</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially lead to more effective regulation of digital markets, as it provides clear guidance on how the CMA will carry out its enforcement functions.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This change could potentially increase the power of the CMA, as it allows for more flexibility in how its enforcement functions are carried out.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Definition of "associate" and "relative"</subject>
   <quote>A person (“P”) is an associate of an individual if— 15
(a) P is the spouse or civil partner of the individual;
(b) P is a relative of the individual;
(c) P is a relative of the individual’s spouse or civil partner;
(d) P is the spouse or civil partner of a relative of the individual;
(e) P is a spouse or civil partner of a relative of the individual’s spouse 20
or civil partner;
(f) P lives in the same household as the individual otherwise than merely
because P, or the individual, is the other’s employer, tenant, lodger
or boarder;
(g) P is the relative of a person who is an associate of the individual by 25
virtue of paragraph (f);
(h) P has at some time in the past fallen within any of paragraphs (a) to
(g);
(i) P is in partnership with the individual;
(j) the individual is an associate of an individual with whom P is in 30
partnership.</quote>
   <quote>In this section “relative” means a brother, sister, uncle, aunt, nephew, niece, 5
lineal ancestor or lineal descendant.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a detailed definition of who can be considered an "associate" of an individual, including spouses, relatives, household members, past associates, and business partners. It also defines "relative" as a brother, sister, uncle, aunt, nephew, niece, lineal ancestor or lineal descendant.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Enhanced consumer measures</subject>
   <quote>References in this Part to “enhanced consumer measures” are references to—
(a) redress measures (see subsection (2)),
(b) compliance measures (see subsection (3)), or 10
(c) choice measures (see subsection (4)).</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces the concept of "enhanced consumer measures", which include redress measures, compliance measures, and choice measures. These measures are intended to offer compensation or other redress to affected consumers, prevent or reduce the risk of the occurrence or repetition of infringing conduct, and enable consumers to choose more effectively between suppliers.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Prohibition of unfair commercial practices</subject>
   <quote>Unfair commercial practices are prohibited.</quote>
   <summary>The bill explicitly prohibits unfair commercial practices, which is likely to provide greater protection for consumers.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 1—Protection from unfair trading</subject>

   <quote>For the purposes of this Chapter, a commercial practice involves a misleading action if the practice involves—
(a) the provision of false or misleading information relating to a product, 40
a trader or any other matter relevant to a transactional decision,
(b) an overall presentation which is likely to deceive the average consumer
about a matter relating to a product, a trader or any other matter
relevant to a transactional decision,
(c) any marketing of a product which creates confusion, or is likely to
create confusion, with any product, trade mark, trade name or other
distinguishing mark of another trader, or
(d) a failure to comply with a requirement in a code of conduct to which
subsection (5) applies in circumstances where the trader asserts that
the trader acts in compliance with that code.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces new regulations that define misleading actions in commercial practices. These include providing false or misleading information, creating confusion with other products or traders, and failing to comply with a code of conduct while claiming to do so.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Protection">This change strengthens consumer protection by clearly defining what constitutes misleading actions in commercial practices.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 1—Protection from unfair trading</subject>

   <quote>For the purposes of this Chapter, a commercial practice involves a misleading omission if, considering the matters mentioned in subsection (3), the practice—
(a) omits material information,
(b) omits information which the trader is required under any other 25
enactment to give to a consumer as part of the practice, or
(c) fails to identify its commercial intent (unless it is already apparent
from the context).</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces new regulations that define misleading omissions in commercial practices. These include omitting material information, omitting information required by other enactments, and failing to identify commercial intent.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Protection">This change strengthens consumer protection by clearly defining what constitutes misleading omissions in commercial practices.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 1—Protection from unfair trading</subject>

   <quote>For the purposes of this Chapter, a commercial practice involves an aggressive practice if it uses harassment, coercion or undue influence.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces new regulations that define aggressive practices in commercial practices. These include the use of harassment, coercion, or undue influence.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Protection">This change strengthens consumer protection by clearly defining what constitutes aggressive practices in commercial practices.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 1—Protection from unfair trading</subject>

   <quote>It is the duty of every local weights and measures authority in Great Britain to enforce in its area the prohibitions in section 218.
(2) It is the duty of the Department for the Economy in Northern Ireland to enforce the prohibitions in section 218 in Northern Ireland.
(3) The CMA may also enforce the provisions of this Chapter.</quote>

   <summary>The bill assigns the duty of enforcing the prohibitions in section 218 to local weights and measures authorities in Great Britain, the Department for the Economy in Northern Ireland, and the CMA.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Protection">This change strengthens consumer protection by assigning enforcement duties to specific authorities.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 1—Protection from unfair trading</subject>

   <quote>A consumer has rights of redress under this Chapter if each of the following four conditions is met.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces new consumer rights of redress under certain conditions.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Protection">This change strengthens consumer protection by introducing new rights of redress.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Consumer rights and disputes</subject>

   <quote>(3) The third condition is that the prohibited practice is a significant factor in the consumer’s decision—
(a) to enter into the contract mentioned in subsection (2)(a) or (b), or
(b) to make the payment mentioned in subsection (2)(c).</quote>

   <quote>(6) In subsection (3), “producer” means—
(a) a manufacturer of the goods or digital content,
(b) an importer of the goods or digital content into the United Kingdom, 25
or
(c) a person purporting to be such a manufacturer or importer by placing
the person’s name, trade mark or other distinctive sign on the goods
or by using it in connection with the digital content,
and includes a producer acting personally or through another person acting 30
in the producer’s name or on the producer’s behalf.</quote>

   <quote>(7) In this Chapter, “prohibited practice” means an unfair commercial practice
involving—
(a) a misleading action, or
(b) an aggressive practice.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces new conditions for consumer rights and disputes, defining a "prohibited practice" as an unfair commercial practice involving a misleading action or an aggressive practice. It also defines a "producer" as a manufacturer or importer of goods or digital content, or a person purporting to be such a manufacturer or importer.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Protection">This change strengthens consumer protection by clearly defining prohibited practices and the role of producers in consumer rights and disputes.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Consumer rights and disputes</subject>

   <quote>226 Rights of redress: further provision
(1) The Secretary of State may by regulations provide for any of the following
descriptions of rights to be exercisable by a consumer who has rights of
redress under this Chapter—
(a) a right to unwind in respect of a relevant contract or consumer 5
payment;
(b) a right to a discount in respect of a supply of a product under a
relevant contract;
(c)
10
a right to damages in respect of financial loss, distress or physical
inconvenience or discomfort.</quote>

   <summary>The bill grants the Secretary of State the power to regulate consumer rights of redress, including the right to unwind a contract or payment, the right to a discount for a product under a contract, and the right to damages for financial loss, distress, or physical inconvenience or discomfort.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Protection">This change enhances consumer protection by providing consumers with a range of rights of redress, which can be regulated by the Secretary of State.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Consumer rights and disputes</subject>

   <quote>230 Offences
(1) A trader commits an offence if, in breach of section 218(1), the trader engages
5
in an unfair commercial practice which involves a misleading action within
section 219(1)(a), (b) or (c) (see section 218(4)(a)(i)).
(2) A trader commits an offence if, in breach of section 218(1), the trader engages
in an unfair commercial practice which involves a misleading omission (see
section 218(4)(a)(ii)).
(3)
10
A trader commits an offence if, in breach of section 218(1), the trader engages
in an unfair commercial practice which involves an aggressive practice (see
section 218(4)(a)(iii)).</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces new offences for traders who engage in unfair commercial practices, including misleading actions, misleading omissions, and aggressive practices.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Protection">This change strengthens consumer protection by criminalizing certain unfair commercial practices by traders.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 232 - Offences: criminal liability of others</subject>

   <quote>(1) Subsections (2) and (3) apply where a trader—
(a) commits an offence under subsection (1), (2), (3), (6) or (7) of section 30
230, or
(b) would have committed an offence under that subsection but for a
defence under section 231,
35
and the commission of the offence, or of what would have been the offence,
is due to the act or omission of another person “P”.
(2) P commits the offence (whether or not P is a trader and whether or not P’s
act or omission is a commercial practice).
(3) P may be charged with and convicted of the offence by virtue of subsection
(2) whether or not proceedings are taken against the trader.</quote>

   <summary>This change introduces a new provision that holds a third party ("P") criminally liable for an offence committed by a trader if the offence was due to the act or omission of "P". This applies whether or not "P" is a trader or whether or not "P's" act or omission is a commercial practice. "P" can be charged and convicted of the offence whether or not proceedings are taken against the trader.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change could significantly impact the justice system by expanding the scope of criminal liability in the context of unfair trading practices. It could lead to more prosecutions and convictions of third parties who are found to have contributed to a trader's offence.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      This change could potentially deter third parties from engaging in acts or omissions that could contribute to a trader's offence, thereby promoting fair trading practices and protecting consumers.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 235 - Powers to amend this Chapter</subject>

   <quote>(1) The Secretary of State may by regulations amend Schedule 18 (commercial
practices which are in all circumstances considered unfair) so as to—
(a) add a description of a commercial practice;
(b) remove a description of a commercial practice;
(c) amend a description of a commercial practice.</quote>

   <summary>This change gives the Secretary of State the power to amend Schedule 18, which lists commercial practices considered unfair in all circumstances, by adding, removing, or amending descriptions of commercial practices.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">
      This change could potentially increase the power of the Secretary of State by giving them the authority to define what constitutes an unfair commercial practice.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      This change could potentially impact the economy by influencing the conduct of businesses and traders, depending on how the Secretary of State chooses to define unfair commercial practices.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 4—Consumer rights and disputes, Chapter 1—Protection from unfair trading</subject>
   <quote>The Consumer Protection from Unfair Trading Regulations 2008 (S.I. 2008/1277) are revoked.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to revoke the Consumer Protection from Unfair Trading Regulations 2008.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Protection"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 4—Consumer rights and disputes, Chapter 1—Protection from unfair trading</subject>
   <quote>This Chapter applies only in relation to an act or omission which takes place on or after the commencement date.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes that the changes in this chapter will only apply to acts or omissions that occur after the commencement date of the bill.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Protection"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 4—Consumer rights and disputes, Chapter 2—Subscription contracts</subject>
   <quote>This Chapter—
(a) imposes duties on traders in relation to subscription contracts,
(b) provides rights for consumers if those duties are breached, and
(c) provides rights for consumers to cancel subscription contracts during cooling-off periods.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes new regulations for subscription contracts, imposing duties on traders, providing rights for consumers if those duties are breached, and allowing consumers to cancel subscription contracts during cooling-off periods.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Protection"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 4—Consumer rights and disputes, Chapter 2—Subscription contracts</subject>
   <quote>Before a trader enters into a subscription contract with a consumer, the trader must—
(a) give to the consumer the information set out in Part 1 of Schedule 20 (“key pre-contract information”), and
(b) give, or make available, to the consumer the information set out in Part 2 of Schedule 20 (“full pre-contract information”) so far as that information is applicable to the contract and not already apparent from the context.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes that traders must provide consumers with key pre-contract information and full pre-contract information before entering into a subscription contract.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Protection"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Consumer rights and disputes in subscription contracts</subject>

   <quote>For the purposes of this section, information is made available to a consumer only if the consumer can reasonably be expected to— know how to access it, and be able to access it;</quote>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may by regulations amend Parts 1 and 2 of Schedule 10 so as to add, modify or remove descriptions of information.</quote>
   <quote>The trader must ensure that the final step which the consumer is required to take to enter into the contract involves the consumer expressly acknowledging that the contract imposes an obligation on the consumer to make payments to the trader.</quote>
   <quote>If the trader does not comply with subsection (2), the consumer is not bound by the subscription contract.</quote>
   <quote>Where a trader enters into a subscription contract with a consumer, the trader must give to the consumer a notice (referred to in this Chapter as a “reminder notice”)</quote>
   <quote>A trader must make arrangements to enable a consumer to exercise a right to bring a subscription contract to an end— in a single communication, without having to take any steps which are not reasonably necessary for bringing the contract to an end.</quote>
   <quote>This section applies where a consumer— has exercised a right under this Chapter to cancel a subscription contract, or has exercised a right to bring a subscription contract to an end.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces new regulations for subscription contracts, aiming to protect consumer rights. It mandates that traders must ensure consumers are aware of their obligations before entering a contract, and if this is not done, the consumer is not bound by the contract. Traders are also required to provide reminder notices to consumers about renewal payments. Furthermore, traders must facilitate consumers' ability to end a subscription contract in a single communication without unnecessary steps. If a consumer cancels or ends a subscription contract, the trader must acknowledge this and refund any overpayment.</summary>
   
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change significantly enhances consumer rights by introducing more transparency and ease in the process of entering, renewing, and ending subscription contracts. It also mandates traders to refund any overpayment, which could potentially prevent consumers from being financially exploited.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      This change could have a significant economic impact on businesses that rely heavily on subscription models. They may need to adjust their practices to comply with these new regulations, which could potentially increase their operational costs.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Consumer rights in subscription contracts</subject>

   <quote>In subsection (2)(b) “overpayment”, in relation to a subscription contract, means any payment made by the consumer for which the consumer is not liable as a result of cancelling the subscription contract or bringing it to an end.</quote>
   <quote>A trader’s compliance with the following duties is an implied term in every subscription contract— (a) the duty set out in section 249(1)(a) (key pre-contract information); (b) the duty set out in section 249(1)(b) (full pre-contract information); (c) the duty set out in section 251(1) (reminder notices); (d) the duty set out in section 253(1) (arrangements for consumer to end contract); (e) the duties set out in section 254(2) (end or cancellation of subscription contract).</quote>
   <quote>The consumer has the right to cancel the contract.</quote>
   <quote>A subscription contract is cancelled from the time the notification is given.</quote>
   <quote>No penalty or charge may be imposed on a consumer for cancelling a subscription contract under subsection (2).</quote>
   <quote>A consumer has the right to cancel a subscription contract during— (a) the initial cooling-off period, and (b) any renewal cooling-off period.</quote>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may by regulations make provision— (a) about the exercise of the rights of a consumer to cancel a subscription contract under this Chapter; (b) about the consequences that follow a consumer exercising such rights; (c) extending a cooling-off period in such cases, and to such extent, as the regulations may specify.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces new consumer rights in relation to subscription contracts. It defines "overpayment" and establishes that a trader's compliance with certain duties is an implied term in every subscription contract. It also gives consumers the right to cancel the contract without penalty, and the contract is considered cancelled from the time the cancellation notification is given. Consumers also have the right to cancel a subscription contract during the initial cooling-off period and any renewal cooling-off period. The Secretary of State may make regulations about the exercise of these rights and the consequences of exercising them, and may extend the cooling-off period.</summary>

   <impact>4</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change significantly enhances consumer rights by providing clear and explicit protections for consumers in relation to subscription contracts. It gives consumers the right to cancel contracts without penalty and establishes cooling-off periods during which contracts can be cancelled. This could have a significant impact on businesses that rely on subscription models, as they will need to ensure their practices comply with these new regulations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Offence of failing to provide pre-contract information about initial cooling-off rights</subject>

   <quote>A trader commits an offence if the trader—
(a) enters into an off-premises subscription contract, and
(b) fails to— 10
(i) give the consumer the information listed in paragraph 10(a) of
Schedule 20 in accordance with section 249(1)(a), or
(ii) give, or make available, the information set out in paragraph
20 of that Schedule in accordance with section 249(1)(b).</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a new offence for traders who fail to provide pre-contract information about initial cooling-off rights when entering into an off-premises subscription contract.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change strengthens consumer rights by ensuring they are informed about their cooling-off rights before entering into a subscription contract.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Penalty for offence and enforcement</subject>

   <quote>A person who is guilty of an offence under section 261(1) is liable—
(a) on summary conviction in England Wales, to a fine; 5
(b) on summary conviction in Scotland or Northern Ireland, to a fine not
exceeding level 5 on the standard scale.</quote>

   <summary>The bill establishes penalties for the new offence of failing to provide pre-contract information about initial cooling-off rights. The penalty is a fine, with the amount varying depending on the jurisdiction.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change impacts the justice system by introducing a new offence and associated penalties.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Terms of a subscription contract which are of no effect</subject>

   <quote>Any term of a subscription contract that is in contravention of this Chapter
is, to that extent, of no effect (including any term that seeks to exclude or
restrict a trader’s liability arising from the terms implied into the contract by
section 255).</quote>

   <summary>The bill declares that any term of a subscription contract that contravenes the provisions of this chapter is of no effect. This includes any term that seeks to exclude or restrict a trader's liability arising from the terms implied into the contract by section 255.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change enhances consumer rights by invalidating any contract terms that contravene the provisions of this chapter.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Consumer Rights Act 2015</subject>

   <quote>271 Amendment of the Consumer Rights Act 2015
(1) CRA 2015 is amended as follows.
(2) In section 11 (goods to be as described)— 35
178 Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Bill
Part 4—Consumer rights and disputes
Chapter 2—Subscription contracts 
(a) in subsection (4), after “(SI 2013/3134)” insert “, or in paragraph 13 of
Schedule 20 to the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act
2023,”, and
(b)
5
in subsection (5), after “effective” insert “as a variation of a term
implied by subsection (4)”.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the Consumer Rights Act 2015, specifically in section 11, which pertains to goods being as described. The amendments include the insertion of references to the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023 in subsections (4) and (5).</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      The proposed changes could potentially affect consumer rights, particularly in relation to the description of goods in digital markets. This could lead to more transparency and protection for consumers.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Regulatory Enforcement and Sanctions Act 2008</subject>

   <quote>272 Other consequential amendments 10
(1) In Schedule 3 to the Regulatory Enforcement and Sanctions Act 2008, at the
appropriate place insert—
“Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023, Chapter 2 of
Part 4.”.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes an amendment to the Regulatory Enforcement and Sanctions Act 2008, specifically in Schedule 3, to include a reference to the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Regulatory Enforcement">
      The proposed change could potentially affect regulatory enforcement, particularly in relation to digital markets. This could lead to more stringent enforcement of regulations in these markets.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Consumer Contracts (Information Cancellation and Additional Charges) Regulations 2013</subject>

   <quote>(2) The Consumer Contracts (Information Cancellation and Additional Charges) 15
Regulations 2013 (S.I. 2013/3134) is amended as follows.
(3) In regulation 5 (other definitions), in the appropriate place insert—
““subscription contract” has the meaning it has in Chapter 2 of Part 4 of
20
the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023 (see section
247 of that Act);”.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes an amendment to the Consumer Contracts (Information Cancellation and Additional Charges) Regulations 2013, specifically in regulation 5, to include a definition of "subscription contract" as per the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      The proposed change could potentially affect consumer rights, particularly in relation to subscription contracts in digital markets. This could lead to more transparency and protection for consumers.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Consumer Savings Scheme Contract</subject>

   <quote>For the purposes of this Chapter, a consumer savings scheme contract is a contract—
(a) under which—
(i) a consumer makes payments to a trader,
(ii) the trader credits those payments to an account that is held by the trader for the consumer (“the consumer’s account”), and
(iii) the payments credited to the consumer’s account provide a fund for the consumer to redeem as goods, services or digital content in accordance with the terms of the contract,
(b) to which one or more of subsections (2), (3) or (4) applies, and
(c) which is not an excluded arrangement (see section 277).</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a new concept of a "consumer savings scheme contract". This is a contract where a consumer makes payments to a trader, the trader credits those payments to an account held by the trader for the consumer, and the payments credited to the consumer’s account provide a fund for the consumer to redeem as goods, services or digital content in accordance with the terms of the contract.</summary>
   
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could have significant economic implications, as it introduces a new type of contract that could affect how consumers and traders interact in the marketplace.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Insolvency protection requirement</subject>

   <quote>A trader operating a consumer savings scheme must make and maintain the arrangements set out in section 279 (insurance arrangements) or in section 280 (trust arrangements) to cover, in the event of the trader’s insolvency, the cost of returning to the consumer any protected payments at the time of the insolvency.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a new requirement for traders operating a consumer savings scheme to have arrangements in place to cover the cost of returning to the consumer any protected payments in the event of the trader’s insolvency.</summary>
   
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could have a significant economic impact, as it introduces a new requirement for traders that could affect their financial stability and operations.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Consumer Protection">This change could also have a significant impact on consumer protection, as it ensures that consumers are protected in the event of a trader's insolvency.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Information requirements</subject>

   <quote>A trader must, before the end of 30 working days beginning with the day on which a consumer makes the first payment to the trader under a consumer savings scheme contract, provide to the consumer the following information—
(a) the name, address, telephone number and email address of the insurer or trustees responsible for protecting the consumer’s payments;
(b) where insurance arrangements are in place, the policy number for the policy under which the consumer’s payments are protected;
(c) where trust arrangements are in place, a copy of the trust deed under which the consumer’s payments are held.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a new requirement for traders to provide certain information to consumers within 30 working days of the consumer making the first payment under a consumer savings scheme contract. This information includes the contact details of the insurer or trustees responsible for protecting the consumer’s payments, the policy number if insurance arrangements are in place, and a copy of the trust deed if trust arrangements are in place.</summary>
   
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Protection">This change could have a significant impact on consumer protection, as it ensures that consumers are provided with important information about the protection of their payments.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Consumer Savings Schemes</subject>

   <quote>(4) The information provided under this section must be in clear and plain 25
language and, if in writing, in a legible form.</quote>
   <quote>(5) The information provided under this section must—
(a) in cases where the contract is to be entered into in the simultaneous
physical presence of the trader and the consumer, be given in writing
on a durable medium;</quote>
   <quote>(b) in cases where the contract is to be entered into online without the
simultaneous physical presence of the trader and the consumer—
(i) be given in writing by being displayed in any location online
where the consumer may take steps to enter into the contract,
and
(ii) be accessible in that location without the need for any action
by the consumer;</quote>
   <quote>(c) in cases where the contract is to be entered into orally without the
simultaneous physical presence of the trader and the consumer, be
given to the consumer orally and in a way that is audible and
comprehensible.</quote>
   <quote>(6) In cases not falling within subsection (5)(a) the trader must also, as soon as
reasonably practicable after the contract has been entered into, give the
consumer the information in writing on a durable medium.</quote>
   <quote>(7) A trader operating a consumer savings scheme in the United Kingdom, who
is not established in the United Kingdom, must comply with the requirements
of this section.</quote>
   <quote>(8) It is an implied term of every consumer savings scheme contract that the
trader complies with the requirements of this section.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes new regulations for Consumer Savings Schemes. It mandates that information provided under this section must be in clear and plain language and, if in writing, in a legible form. The information must be given in writing on a durable medium if the contract is to be entered into in the simultaneous physical presence of the trader and the consumer. If the contract is to be entered into online without the simultaneous physical presence of the trader and the consumer, the information must be given in writing by being displayed in any location online where the consumer may take steps to enter into the contract, and be accessible in that location without the need for any action by the consumer. If the contract is to be entered into orally without the simultaneous physical presence of the trader and the consumer, the information must be given to the consumer orally and in a way that is audible and comprehensible. In cases not falling within these categories, the trader must also, as soon as reasonably practicable after the contract has been entered into, give the consumer the information in writing on a durable medium. A trader operating a consumer savings scheme in the United Kingdom, who is not established in the United Kingdom, must comply with the requirements of this section. It is an implied term of every consumer savings scheme contract that the trader complies with the requirements of this section.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Protection">
      This change strengthens consumer protection by ensuring that consumers are provided with clear and comprehensible information about the contract they are entering into. This can help consumers make informed decisions and protect their rights.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Digital Markets">
      This change impacts digital markets by imposing new requirements on traders operating online. This could potentially affect the operations of online businesses and the digital economy.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Alternative dispute resolution for consumer contract disputes</subject>

   <quote>“Consumer contract dispute” means a dispute between the parties to a consumer contract which relates to the contract, including a dispute concerning—
(a) anything done by either party before making the contract,
(b) the making of the contract, 
(c) obligations under or relating to the contract, or
(d) the performance by either party of their obligations under or relating to the contract.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a definition for "Consumer contract dispute", which includes disputes related to actions taken before the contract, the making of the contract, obligations under the contract, and the performance of obligations under the contract.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change provides a clear definition of what constitutes a consumer contract dispute, which could potentially streamline the process of resolving such disputes and protect consumer rights.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Prohibition on acting as ADR provider without accreditation</subject>

   <quote>A person must not carry out ADR in relation to a consumer contract dispute unless the person—
(a) is an exempt ADR provider whose exemption covers the ADR being carried out,
(b) is an accredited ADR provider whose accreditation covers the ADR being carried out, or
(c) is acting under special ADR arrangements made by—
(i) an exempt ADR provider whose exemption covers the making of those special ADR arrangements, or
(ii) an accredited ADR provider whose accreditation covers the making of those special ADR arrangements.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a prohibition on acting as an Alternative Dispute Resolution (ADR) provider without accreditation or exemption. This applies to both carrying out ADR and making special ADR arrangements.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change could potentially increase the quality and reliability of ADR providers, thereby protecting consumers from unqualified or fraudulent providers.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Prohibitions relating to charging fees to consumers</subject>

   <quote>An accredited ADR provider must not charge the consumer a fee in respect of ADR being carried out (or to be carried out) in relation to a consumer contract—
(a) by the accredited ADR provider, or 
(b) by another ADR provider under special ADR arrangements made by the accredited ADR provider,
unless the fee is charged in accordance with provisions for the charging of fees to consumers which meet the conditions in subsection (2).</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a prohibition on accredited ADR providers charging consumers a fee for carrying out ADR, unless the fee is charged in accordance with approved and published provisions.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change could potentially protect consumers from being charged excessive or unexpected fees for ADR services.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Applications for accreditation etc</subject>

   <quote>A person who wishes to be an accredited ADR provider must apply to the Secretary of State for accreditation to enable the person to carry out ADR or to make special ADR arrangements (or to do both).</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a requirement for individuals or entities wishing to become accredited ADR providers to apply to the Secretary of State for accreditation.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change could potentially increase the quality and reliability of ADR providers, thereby protecting consumers from unqualified or fraudulent providers.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Extension and revocation of accreditations</subject>

   <quote>An extension of an accreditation is not time limited unless the Secretary of State determines that the extension is to have effect for a limited period and the notice of the decision on the application for extension...</quote>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may, by notice to the ADR provider, revoke the accreditation on the application of the ADR provider.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that an extension of an accreditation is not time-limited unless the Secretary of State determines otherwise. The Secretary of State also has the power to revoke the accreditation on the application of the ADR provider.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially affect the justice system by altering the duration and validity of accreditations.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Fees payable by accredited ADR providers</subject>

   <quote>Accredited ADR providers must pay to the Secretary of State, at such times as the Secretary of State may determine, such fees as may be so determined.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that accredited ADR providers must pay fees to the Secretary of State at times determined by the Secretary of State.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could have an economic impact on accredited ADR providers who will now be required to pay fees.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Enforcement notices</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State may give an enforcement notice to an ADR provider if satisfied that the provider is contravening, or has contravened, any one or more of the following...</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that the Secretary of State may give an enforcement notice to an ADR provider if they are found to be contravening certain prohibitions, conditions, or duties.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially affect the justice system by introducing a new enforcement mechanism for ADR providers.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>ADR information regulations</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State may by regulations require persons of a specified description (being persons within subsection (2))— (a) to provide ADR information to the Secretary of State; (b) to provide ADR information to a person with functions conferred by regulations under section 299; (c) to provide ADR information to consumers by publishing it.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that the Secretary of State may require certain persons to provide ADR information to the Secretary of State, to a person with functions conferred by regulations, or to consumers by publishing it.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially affect the justice system by introducing new information requirements for certain persons.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Alternative dispute resolution for consumer contract disputes</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State may give a direction to any person falling within
subsection (2) requiring the person to provide ADR information to the
Secretary of State.</quote>
   <quote>A person to whom a direction is given must so far as reasonably practicable
comply with it.</quote>
   <quote>The duty to comply with a direction is enforceable by the Secretary of State
in civil proceedings—
(a) for an injunction,
(b)
35
for specific performance of a statutory duty under section 45 of the
Court of Session Act 1988, or
(c) for any other appropriate remedy or relief.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that the Secretary of State can direct any person to provide Alternative Dispute Resolution (ADR) information. The person directed must comply as far as reasonably practicable, and the duty to comply is enforceable by the Secretary of State in civil proceedings.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change could potentially streamline the process of dispute resolution in consumer contract disputes, making it more efficient and effective.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Alternative dispute resolution for consumer contract disputes</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State may publish information to which this section applies
for the purpose of providing information to consumers.</quote>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may disclose information to which this section applies— 10
(a) to any Minister of the Crown, government department or devolved
authority;
(b) to a regulator;
(c) to a public designated enforcer (see section 144);
(d) if the disclosure is necessary for the purpose of criminal proceedings. 15</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that the Secretary of State can publish and disclose ADR information for the purpose of providing information to consumers, to any Minister of the Crown, government department or devolved authority, to a regulator, to a public designated enforcer, or if the disclosure is necessary for the purpose of criminal proceedings.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change could potentially increase transparency and accountability in the process of dispute resolution in consumer contract disputes.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Alternative dispute resolution for consumer contract disputes</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State may by regulations make provision for or in connection
with the conferring on another person of any function falling within subsection
25
(2) so far as it is exercisable in such cases or circumstances as may be
prescribed by the regulations, in place of the corresponding function of the
Secretary of State.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that the Secretary of State can make regulations to confer on another person any function that is exercisable in such cases or circumstances as may be prescribed by the regulations, in place of the corresponding function of the Secretary of State.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change could potentially increase the efficiency and effectiveness of the process of dispute resolution in consumer contract disputes by allowing the Secretary of State to delegate certain functions.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Alternative dispute resolution for consumer contract disputes</subject>

   <quote>This section applies where a trader responds to a complaint from a consumer
in respect of any matters relating to a consumer contract between them.</quote>
   <quote>The trader must, when communicating the outcome of the trader’s
consideration of the complaint to the consumer, also inform the consumer
about any ADR or other arrangement that is available if the consumer is
dissatisfied with the outcome.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that when a trader responds to a complaint from a consumer in respect of any matters relating to a consumer contract between them, the trader must also inform the consumer about any ADR or other arrangement that is available if the consumer is dissatisfied with the outcome.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change could potentially increase the protection of consumer rights by ensuring that consumers are informed about their options for dispute resolution.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 1—Provision of investigative assistance to overseas regulators</subject>

   <quote>A relevant regulator (“R”) may assist an overseas regulator (“O”) in accordance with the table in subsection (2) where—
(a) O makes a request to R (see section 304) for R to assist O’s carrying out of functions—
(i) which correspond or are similar to functions of R under a relevant enactment, but
(ii) which are not functions relating to the investigation of crime or the bringing of criminal proceedings,
(b) R considers that it would be appropriate to assist O (see section 305),
and
(c) the Secretary of State authorises R to assist O (see section 306).</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the provision for a relevant regulator to assist an overseas regulator in carrying out functions that correspond or are similar to the functions of the relevant regulator under a relevant enactment. This assistance is subject to the request of the overseas regulator, the relevant regulator's consideration of appropriateness, and the authorisation of the Secretary of State.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 1—Provision of investigative assistance to overseas regulators</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State may authorise R to assist O either—
(a) in relation to one or more specific requests for assistance, or
(b) generally in respect of requests for assistance of a particular description (including in respect of requests from particular overseas regulators).</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that the Secretary of State may authorise a relevant regulator to assist an overseas regulator either in relation to one or more specific requests for assistance, or generally in respect of requests for assistance of a particular description.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 1—Provision of investigative assistance to overseas regulators</subject>

   <quote>The Secretary of State must publish—
(a) any general authorisation given under subsection (2)(b);
(b) notice of any withdrawal of a general authorisation under subsection (3).</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes that the Secretary of State must publish any general authorisation given to a relevant regulator to assist an overseas regulator, as well as any notice of withdrawal of such a general authorisation.</summary>

   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Freedom of Information"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Provision of investigative assistance to overseas regulators</subject>

   <quote>In considering whether to authorise R to assist O (whether specifically or generally), the Secretary of State must have regard to whether—</quote>
   <quote>In authorising R to assist O, the Secretary of State may impose conditions on R doing so.</quote>
   <quote>The CMA must prepare and publish guidance about— the making and consideration of requests for assistance under this Chapter, and the provision of assistance under this Chapter.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a new framework for the provision of investigative assistance to overseas regulators. The Secretary of State is given the power to authorize such assistance and impose conditions on it. The Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) is tasked with preparing and publishing guidance on the process.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security">
      This change could potentially impact national security by facilitating international cooperation in investigations.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change could impact the justice system by enabling more effective cross-border investigations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Disclosing information overseas</subject>

   <quote>Part 9 of EA 2002 (information) is amended as follows.</quote>
   <quote>A public authority which holds information to which section 237 applies (“the discloser”) may disclose that information to an overseas public authority for the purpose of facilitating both—</quote>
   <quote>A public authority which holds information to which section 237 applies (“the discloser”) may disclose that information to an overseas public authority for a purpose permitted under or by virtue of a designated cooperation arrangement.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to Part 9 of the Enterprise Act 2002, allowing public authorities to disclose information to overseas public authorities for the purpose of facilitating their functions or under a designated cooperation arrangement.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security">
      This change could potentially impact national security by facilitating international cooperation in investigations.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change could impact the justice system by enabling more effective cross-border investigations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 243D</subject>
   <quote>Subsections (2) and (3) apply to information disclosed by virtue of section 243A to the extent that the disclosure was to facilitate the exercise by the discloser of any function it has under or by virtue of this Act or any other enactment (“the original function”) in relation to a particular matter (“the original matter”).</quote>
   <quote>The information must not be used by the overseas public authority other than for facilitating the exercise by the discloser of the original function in relation to the original matter unless— (a) the use is for the purpose of facilitating the exercise by the discloser of any function it has under this Act or any other enactment (other than the original function) whether or not in relation to the original matter, and (b) the discloser consents to the use of that information for that purpose.</quote>
   <quote>The information must not be further disclosed by the overseas public authority unless— (a) the further disclosure is for the purpose of facilitating the exercise by the discloser of any function it has under this Act or any other enactment (whether or not the original function) whether or not in relation to the original matter, and (b) the discloser consents to the further disclosure of the information for that purpose.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes a new section 243D that regulates the use and further disclosure of information disclosed under sections 243A and 243B. The information can only be used or further disclosed by the overseas public authority for facilitating the exercise by the discloser of the original function in relation to the original matter, unless the discloser consents to the use of that information for another purpose.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 243E</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may direct that a disclosure permitted under section 243A or 243B must not be made if the Secretary of State thinks that, in connection with any matter in respect of which the disclosure could be made, it is more appropriate— (a) if any investigation is to be carried out, that it is carried out by an authority in the United Kingdom or in another specified country or territory (rather than by the overseas public authority); (b) if any proceedings are to be brought, that they are brought in a court in the United Kingdom or in another specified country or territory (rather than in the country or territory of the overseas authority).</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes a new section 243E that gives the Secretary of State the power to direct that a disclosure permitted under section 243A or 243B must not be made if they think it is more appropriate for an investigation to be carried out by an authority in the UK or another specified country, or for proceedings to be brought in a court in the UK or another specified country.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 243F</subject>
   <quote>This section applies when a public authority is deciding whether to make a disclosure under section 243A or 243B.</quote>
   <quote>In deciding whether to make a disclosure under section 243A, the public authority must have regard in particular to the following considerations— (a) whether the law and practice of the country or territory to whose authority the disclosure would be made provides appropriate protection against self-incrimination in criminal proceedings; (b) whether the law and practice of that country or territory provides appropriate protection in relation to the storage and disclosure of confidential information.</quote>
   <quote>In deciding whether to make a disclosure under section 243B, the public authority must have regard in particular to the considerations in subsection (2) and the following additional considerations— (a) whether the matter in respect of which the disclosure is sought is sufficiently serious to justify making the disclosure; (b) whether the disclosure would further the aims or purposes of any convention or treaty relating in whole or in part to cooperation in matters relating to competition or consumer protection to which the United Kingdom and the country or territory of the authority to whom the disclosure would be made are parties; (c) whether there are arrangements in place for the provision of mutual assistance as between the United Kingdom and that country or territory to whose authority the disclosure would be made in relation to the disclosure of information of the kind to which section 237 applies; (d) whether a person or body in that country or territory would assist the public authority in a way that corresponds or is substantially similar to the assistance that it is proposed the public authority give to the overseas public authority by making the disclosure.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes a new section 243F that sets out the considerations a public authority must have regard to when deciding whether to make a disclosure under section 243A or 243B. These considerations include the law and practice of the country to whose authority the disclosure would be made, whether the matter is sufficiently serious to justify making the disclosure, whether the disclosure would further the aims or purposes of any relevant convention or treaty, whether there are arrangements in place for mutual assistance, and whether a person or body in that country would assist the public authority in a similar way.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 246</subject>
   <quote>For section 246 substitute— “246A Interpretation In this Part— “commercial information” means information relating to any business of an undertaking whose disclosure the public authority concerned or, for the purposes of section 243C the Secretary of State, thinks might significantly harm the undertaking’s legitimate business interests; “confidential information” means commercial information, private information or sensitive information; “overseas public authority” means a person or body in any country or territory outside the United Kingdom which appears to the discloser (within the meaning of any of sections 243A to 243C) to exercise functions of a public nature in relation to anything mentioned in sub-paragraphs (i) to (v) of section 243A(1)(b); “private information” mean information relating to the private affairs of an individual whose disclosure the public authority concerned, or for the purposes of section 243C the Secretary of State, thinks might significantly harm the individual’s interests; “sensitive information” means information whose disclosure the public authority concerned or, for the purposes of section 243C the Secretary of State, thinks would be contrary to the public interest;</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to substitute section 246 with a new section 246A that provides definitions for terms such as "commercial information", "confidential information", "overseas public authority", "private information", and "sensitive information".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 311</subject>
   <quote>In section 25 of ERRA 2013 (the Competition and Markets Authority), after subsection (4) insert— “(5) In making any decision, or otherwise taking action, for the purposes of any of its functions within Schedule 4A the CMA must have regard to the need for making a decision, or taking action, as soon as reasonably practicable.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes a new section 311 that amends section 25 of the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Act 2013 (ERRA 2013) to require the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) to have regard to the need for making a decision, or taking action, as soon as reasonably practicable for the purposes of any of its functions within Schedule 4A.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 2: Competition Functions</subject>
   <quote>2 Functions under Part 3 of the 2002 Act (mergers) other than 30
functions under—
(a) section 94B (statement of policy about functions under
sections 94 and 94AA);
(b)
35
section 106 (advice and information about references under
section 22 or 33);</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes new competition functions under Part 3 of the 2002 Act (mergers), excluding functions under section 94B and section 106.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">The proposed changes could potentially affect the economic landscape by altering the competition functions under the 2002 Act.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 3: Consumer Functions</subject>
   <quote>7
35
Functions under Part 3 of the Digital Markets, Competition and
Consumers Act 2023 (enforcement powers for infringements of
consumer protection law) other than functions under—
(a) section 192 (statement of policy about penalties);
(b) sections 204 and 205 (rules about direct enforcement
functions);</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes new consumer functions under Part 3 of the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023, excluding functions under section 192, 204, and 205.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">The proposed changes could potentially affect consumer rights by altering the enforcement powers for infringements of consumer protection law.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 4: Digital Market Functions</subject>
   <quote>11 Functions under Part 1 of the Digital Markets, Competition and
Consumers Act 2023 (digital markets) other than functions under—
(a) section 59 (content of report under section 56 etc); 25
(b) section 66 (regulations about duty to notify);
(c) section 90 (statement of policy on penalties);
(d) section 114 (guidance about functions under Part 1).</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes new digital market functions under Part 1 of the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023, excluding functions under section 59, 66, 90, and 114.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Digital Privacy">The proposed changes could potentially affect digital privacy by altering the functions related to digital markets.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 6: General</subject>
   <quote>314 Power to make consequential provision
(1)
35
The Secretary of State may by regulations make provision that is consequential
on this Act or on any provision made under it.
(2) The power to make regulations under this section includes power to amend,
repeal or revoke provision made by or under primary legislation passed or
made before the end of the Session in which this Act is passed.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to grant the Secretary of State the power to make regulations that are consequential on this Act or on any provision made under it. This includes the power to amend, repeal, or revoke provision made by or under primary legislation passed or made before the end of the Session in which this Act is passed.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">The proposed changes could potentially affect the balance of political power by granting the Secretary of State the power to make consequential regulations.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 1—Procedure relating to commitments</subject>
   <quote>The CMA must publish notice of its decision on whether to, and the form in which it will, accept a commitment or a requested variation as soon as reasonably practicable.</quote>
   <quote>Before releasing an undertaking from a commitment the CMA must—
(a) publish a notice under this paragraph, and 5
(b) consider any representations made in accordance with the notice and not withdrawn.</quote>
   <quote>The CMA must publish a notice of its decision on whether to release an undertaking from a commitment as soon as reasonably practicable.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes that the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) must publish a notice of its decision on whether to accept a commitment or a requested variation, and whether to release an undertaking from a commitment, as soon as reasonably practicable. It also requires the CMA to consider any representations made in accordance with the notice and not withdrawn before releasing an undertaking from a commitment.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 2—Mergers: holding of interests and rights</subject>
   <quote>If two or more persons each hold an interest or right jointly, each of them is treated as holding that interest or right.</quote>
   <quote>If interests or rights held by a person and interests or rights held by another person are the subject of a joint arrangement between those persons, each of them is treated as holding the combined interests or rights of both of them.</quote>
   <quote>An interest held by a person as nominee for another is to be treated as held by the other (and not by the nominee).</quote>
   <quote>Where a person controls a right, the right is to be treated as held by that person (and not by the person who in fact holds the right, unless that person also controls it).</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes new rules for how interests and rights are treated in the context of mergers. These include treating joint interests or rights as held by each person, treating interests or rights subject to a joint arrangement as held by each person, treating interests held by a nominee as held by the other person, and treating rights controlled by a person as held by that person.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Schedule 3—Power of Competition Appeal Tribunal to grant declaratory relief</subject>
   <quote>A declaration granted by the Tribunal in proceedings under section 47A or collective proceedings has the same effect as a declaration granted by the High Court.</quote>
   <quote>A declarator granted by the Tribunal in proceedings under section 47A or collective proceedings has the same effect as a declarator granted by the Court of Session.</quote>
   <quote>In deciding whether to grant a declaration in proceedings under section 47A or collective proceedings, the Tribunal must apply the principles that the High Court would apply in deciding whether to grant a declaration.</quote>
   <quote>In deciding whether to grant a declarator in proceedings under section 47A or collective proceedings, the Tribunal must apply the principles that the Court of Session would apply in deciding whether to grant a declarator.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes that a declaration or declarator granted by the Competition Appeal Tribunal in proceedings under section 47A or collective proceedings has the same effect as a declaration or declarator granted by the High Court or the Court of Session. The Tribunal must apply the same principles as the High Court or the Court of Session in deciding whether to grant a declaration or declarator.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 23 (relevant merger situations)</subject>
   <quote>In subsection (1), in paragraph (b), for “£70 million” substitute “£100 million”.</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (2)—
(a) omit the “and” at the end of paragraph (a);
(b) at the end insert “; and
(c) the value of the turnover in the United Kingdom of— 35
(i) the enterprise being taken over, or
(ii) any other enterprise concerned,
exceeds £10 million.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 23 of the Enterprise Act 2002, which deals with relevant merger situations. The amendment increases the threshold for the value of the enterprise being taken over from £70 million to £100 million. It also introduces a new condition that the turnover of the enterprise being taken over or any other enterprise concerned must exceed £10 million.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This amendment could potentially impact the business landscape by changing the criteria for what constitutes a relevant merger situation. This could affect the number of mergers that fall under the purview of the Enterprise Act 2002, potentially reducing regulatory scrutiny for some mergers while increasing it for others.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 28 (turnover test)</subject>
   <quote>In subsection (5)—
(a) in paragraph (a)— 10
(i) for “sum” substitute “sums”;
(ii) after “section 23(1)(b)” insert “, (2)(c) and (4E)”;
(b) in paragraph (b), for “sum is” substitute “sums are”.
(3) In subsection (6)—
(a) after “section 23(1)(b)” insert “, (2)(c) or (4E)”; 15
(b) for “the sum” substitute “any of the sums”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 28 of the Enterprise Act 2002, which deals with the turnover test. The amendment changes the language from "sum" to "sums", indicating that multiple sums can be considered in the turnover test. It also expands the sections of the Act that are referenced in this section.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This amendment could potentially impact the way the turnover test is applied, potentially affecting the number of mergers that meet the criteria for the test. This could have implications for the regulatory scrutiny of mergers.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 59 (intervention by Secretary of State in special public interest cases)</subject>
   <quote>For subsections (3) and (3A) substitute—
“(3)
25
For the purposes of this Part, a special merger situation has been
created if—
(a) two or more enterprises have ceased to be distinct enterprises
at a time or in circumstances falling within section 24;
(b) no relevant merger situation has been created; and
(c)
30
immediately before the enterprises concerned ceased to be
distinct, one or more of the conditions mentioned in
subsections (3C) to (3F) were satisfied.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 59 of the Enterprise Act 2002, which deals with the intervention by the Secretary of State in special public interest cases. The amendment changes the conditions under which a special merger situation is created.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">This amendment could potentially impact the circumstances under which the Secretary of State can intervene in special public interest cases, potentially changing the balance of power in these situations.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 22 and Section 33 of EA 2002</subject>

   <quote>“(1A) The CMA must make a reference to its chair for the constitution of a group under Schedule 4 to the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Act 2013 if the CMA has decided, under section 34ZF(2), to accept a fast-track reference request.”</quote>
   <quote>“(1A) The CMA must make a reference to its chair for the constitution of a group under Schedule 4 to the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Act 2013 if the CMA has decided, under section 34ZF(3), to accept a fast-track reference request.”</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to Section 22 and Section 33 of the Enterprise Act 2002 (EA 2002). The amendments require the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) to make a reference to its chair for the constitution of a group under Schedule 4 to the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Act 2013 if the CMA has decided to accept a fast-track reference request.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 34ZD, 34ZE, and 34ZF of EA 2002</subject>

   <quote>“34ZD Fast-track reference requests (1) Subsection (2) applies where the following conditions are met— (a) arrangements or proposed arrangements might have resulted or might result in the creation of a relevant merger situation (the “arrangements concerned”), (b) no reference has been made under section 22 or 33 in respect of the arrangements concerned, and (c) the CMA has not informed the persons carrying on the enterprises concerned of a decision that the duty to make a reference under section 22(1) or 33(1) does not apply in respect of those arrangements.”</quote>
   <quote>“34ZE Fast-track reference requests: procedure (1) This section applies where a fast-track reference request is made and not withdrawn. (2) Where the fast-track reference request is made before the beginning of the initial period, the CMA may, at any time before the beginning of that period, reject the request.”</quote>
   <quote>“34ZF Acceptance by the CMA of fast-track reference requests (1) The CMA may accept a fast-track reference request only if the condition in subsection (2) or (3) is met. (2) The condition in this subsection is that, in relation to the arrangements concerned— (a) the CMA believes that it is or may be the case that a relevant merger situation has been created, and (b) the CMA would not be prevented from making a reference under section 22(1) by reason of section 22(3).”</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of new sections 34ZD, 34ZE, and 34ZF into the EA 2002. These new sections outline the conditions, procedure, and acceptance criteria for fast-track reference requests to the CMA.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 131B of EA 2002</subject>

   <quote>In subsection (4), in paragraph (b), after “proposes to take” insert “, or has taken,”.</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (5), in paragraph (a), for “section 154 instead of” substitute “section 154A instead of, or in addition to,”.</quote>

   <summary>The amendment modifies Section 131B of EA 2002 to include actions that have already been taken, not just proposed actions. It also substitutes "section 154" with "section 154A" in certain contexts.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 133A of EA 2002</subject>

   <quote>In subsection (1), after paragraph (b) insert—“(ba) section 154A, so far as relating to undertakings in lieu of a report;”.</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (2), before paragraph (a) insert—“(za) section 154A, so far as relating to undertakings in lieu of a report;”.</quote>

   <summary>The amendment modifies Section 133A of EA 2002 to include references to "section 154A" in relation to undertakings in lieu of a report.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>substitution</type>
   <subject>Section 154 of EA 2002</subject>

   <quote>For section 154 (and the italic heading immediately before it) substitute—“Undertakings in lieu 154A Undertakings fully or partially in lieu of references or reports</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to substitute Section 154 of EA 2002 with a new section titled "Undertakings in lieu 154A Undertakings fully or partially in lieu of references or reports". This new section provides for the acceptance of undertakings in lieu of references or reports, either fully or partially.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 155 of EA 2002</subject>

   <quote>In subsection (1), for “154” substitute “154A”.</quote>
   <quote>For subsection (3) substitute—“(3A) The matters to be included in a notice under subsection (1) by virtue of subsection (2) include, in particular, the adverse effect on competition, and any detrimental effect on customers so far as resulting from the adverse effect on competition, which the CMA has identified.”</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (10), for “154” substitute “154A”.</quote>

   <summary>The amendment modifies Section 155 of EA 2002 to substitute "154" with "154A". It also replaces subsection (3) with a new provision that specifies the matters to be included in a notice under subsection (1).</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 161B to 161E of the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Bill</subject>

   <quote>This section and sections 161C to 161E make provision in relation to the acceptance of undertakings and making of orders by a relevant authority on a trial basis for the purpose of assessing the effectiveness of qualifying remedial action (and the acceptance of undertakings and making of orders on that basis is referred to in this Part as an “implementation trial”).</quote>
   <quote>The CMA may, in relation to a market investigation reference, begin an implementation trial where— (a) subsection (2) of section 138 applies (see subsection (1) of that section), and (b) the CMA has not taken, but is minded to take, qualifying remedial action.</quote>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may, in relation to a restricted PI reference or a full PI reference, begin an implementation trial where— (a) subsection (2) of section 147, or subsection (2) of 147A (as the case may be), applies (see subsection (1) of the section in question), and (b) the Secretary of State has not taken, but is minded to take, qualifying remedial action.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces the concept of "implementation trials" where the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) or the Secretary of State can accept undertakings or make orders on a trial basis to assess the effectiveness of remedial action. This provision applies to market investigation references, restricted PI references, and full PI references.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">The introduction of implementation trials could have significant economic implications, potentially allowing for more effective and efficient remedial action in the digital markets sector.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could impact the justice system by introducing a new mechanism for assessing the effectiveness of remedial action in competition law cases.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 161C</subject>
   <quote>(4) A relevant authority may publish a final implementation trial notice only where— (a) the relevant authority has published a provisional 30 implementation trial notice under subsection (1), (b) the time for the implementation trial participants to make representations to the relevant authority in accordance with the notice has expired, and (c) after considering such representations (if any), it appears to 35 the relevant authority that it is appropriate to begin an implementation trial under section 161C(4).</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes a new process for the publication of a final implementation trial notice by a relevant authority. This can only occur after a provisional notice has been published, the time for participants to make representations has expired, and the authority deems it appropriate to begin an implementation trial.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 161E</subject>
   <quote>(1) The relevant authority may not accept an undertaking from a person 5 under section 161C unless it has provided the person with information about the possible consequences of failing to comply with the undertaking.</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a requirement for the relevant authority to inform a person about the potential consequences of non-compliance before accepting an undertaking from them under section 161C.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 162B</subject>
   <quote>(2) The CMA must keep under review the effectiveness of the implementation trial measures.</quote>
   <summary>The bill mandates the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) to continually review the effectiveness of the implementation trial measures.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 165</subject>
   <quote>(a) after “section 159” insert “or 161C”; (b) for “or 161” substitute “, 161 or 161C”;</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to section 165 to include references to section 161C.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 26 of CA 1998</subject>
   <quote>(2) In the words before paragraph (a) omit “indicate”. (3) In paragraph (a), at the beginning insert “indicate”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes a rewording of section 26 of the Competition Act 1998, moving the word "indicate" from the introductory sentence to the beginning of paragraph (a).</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 26A (investigations: power to ask questions), subsection (5)</subject>
   <quote>In the words before paragraph (a) omit “indicate”.
(3) In paragraph (a), at the beginning insert “indicate”.
(4) For paragraph (b) substitute— 5
“(b) include information about the possible consequences of
failing to comply with the notice.”</quote>
   <summary>The amendment modifies the language used in section 26A, subsection (5) of the Competition Act 1998. The word "indicate" is removed from the beginning of the section and inserted at the beginning of paragraph (a). Paragraph (b) is replaced with a new provision that requires the inclusion of information about the possible consequences of failing to comply with the notice.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The amendment could potentially increase the clarity and understanding of the consequences of non-compliance for those under investigation, which could lead to more effective enforcement of competition law.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Before section 40A</subject>
   <quote>“40ZE Enforcement of requirements: imposition of penalties
(1) The CMA may impose a penalty on a person in accordance with
section 40A where the CMA considers that—
(a)
35
the person has, without reasonable excuse, failed to comply
with a requirement imposed on the person under section 26,
26A, 27, 28, 28A or 40ZD;
(b) the person has, without reasonable excuse, obstructed an
officer acting in the exercise of the officer’s powers under
250 Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Bill
Schedule 8—Civil penalties etc in connection with competition investigations
Part 1—Investigations under Part 1 of CA 1998 (competition) 
section 27 or under a warrant issued under section 28 or
28A;
(c) the person, having been required to produce a document
5
under section 26, 27, 28 or 28A, has, without reasonable
excuse—
(i) destroyed or otherwise disposed of, falsified or
concealed the document, or
(ii) caused or permitted the document’s destruction,
disposal, falsification or concealment;
(d) the person has, without reasonable excuse, provided 10
information that was false or misleading in a material
particular to the CMA in connection with any function of
the CMA under this Part;
(e)
15
the person has, without reasonable excuse, provided
information that was false or misleading in a material
particular to another person knowing that the information
was to be used for the purpose of providing information to
the CMA in connection with any function of the CMA under
this Part.</quote>
   <summary>The insertion introduces a new section (40ZE) that allows the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) to impose penalties on individuals who fail to comply with certain requirements, obstruct officers, destroy or conceal documents, or provide false or misleading information. The penalties can be imposed in accordance with section 40A.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The insertion strengthens the enforcement powers of the CMA, which could lead to more effective regulation of competition in digital markets.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 40A (penalties: failure to comply with requirements)</subject>
   <quote>(2) In the heading, for “failure to comply with requirements” substitute 10
“amount”.
(3) For subsection (1) substitute—
“(1A) A penalty imposed under section 40ZE(1) is to be of such amount
as the CMA considers appropriate.”
(4) In subsection (2), for the words before paragraph (a), substitute “A penalty 15
imposed under section 40ZE(1)(a) may be—”.
(5) After subsection (2) insert—
“(2A) A penalty imposed under any of section 40ZE(1)(b) to (e) must be
a fixed amount.”
(6) In subsection (3)— 20
(a) for the words before paragraph (a) substitute “A penalty imposed
under section 40ZE(1) on a person who is not an undertaking must
not—”;
(b)
25
in paragraph (a), for “such amount as the Secretary of State may
by order specify” substitute “£30,000”;
(c) in paragraph (b), for “such amount per day as the Secretary of State
may so specify” substitute “£15,000 per day”;
(d) in paragraph (c) omit “as the Secretary of State may so specify”.</quote>
   <summary>The amendment changes the heading of section 40A from "failure to comply with requirements" to "amount". It also replaces subsection (1) with a new provision that allows the CMA to determine the appropriate amount for a penalty imposed under section 40ZE(1). The amendment also introduces a new provision (subsection (2A)) that requires penalties imposed under section 40ZE(1)(b) to (e) to be a fixed amount. Furthermore, it modifies subsection (3) to specify that penalties imposed on a person who is not an undertaking must not exceed £30,000 or £15,000 per day.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The amendment provides more clarity on the amount of penalties that can be imposed under section 40A, which could lead to more predictable outcomes for those subject to penalties.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 43 (destroying or falsifying documents)</subject>
   <quote>A person is not guilty of an offence under subsection (1) by reason
of any act or omission in relation to which the CMA has proceeded
against the person under section 40ZE(1).</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to insert a new provision in Section 43, which states that a person is not guilty of destroying or falsifying documents if the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) has already proceeded against the person under section 40ZE(1).</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 44 (false or misleading information)</subject>
   <quote>A person is not guilty of an offence under this section by reason of
any act or omission in relation to which the CMA has proceeded
against the person under section 40ZE(1).</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to insert a new provision in Section 44, which states that a person is not guilty of providing false or misleading information if the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) has already proceeded against the person under section 40ZE(1).</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 110 (enforcement of powers under section 109: general)</subject>
   <quote>In the heading, for “general” substitute “imposition of penalties”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend the heading of Section 110 from "general" to "imposition of penalties".</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>substitution</type>
   <subject>Section 110 (enforcement of powers under section 109: general)</subject>
   <quote>For subsection (1) substitute—
“(1) The CMA may impose a penalty on a person in accordance with
section 111 where the CMA considers that—
(a)
25
the person has, without reasonable excuse, failed to comply
with any requirement of a notice under section 109;
(b) the person has, without reasonable excuse, obstructed or
delayed another person in the exercise of the other person’s
powers under section 109(6);
(c)
30
the person has, without reasonable excuse, altered,
suppressed or destroyed any document which the person
has been required to produce by a notice under section 109.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to substitute subsection (1) of Section 110 to allow the CMA to impose a penalty on a person in accordance with section 111 if the person has failed to comply with any requirement of a notice under section 109, obstructed or delayed another person in the exercise of their powers under section 109(6), or altered, suppressed or destroyed any document which the person has been required to produce by a notice under section 109, without a reasonable excuse.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 113, 114, 115, 116, 117, 174A, 174B, 174D of the Enterprise Act 2002</subject>

   <quote>“(3A) A provisional penalty notice is given by serving a copy of the notice 10
on the person on whom the appropriate authority is minded to
impose the penalty.”</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (3), for “the CMA” substitute “the appropriate authority”.</quote>
   <quote>“(5A) In the case of a penalty imposed on a person by the CMA or 25
OFCOM, in considering what is appropriate for the purposes of
subsection (5) the Competition Appeal Tribunal must have regard
to the relevant guidance.”</quote>
   <quote>“(1) The CMA must prepare and publish a statement of policy in relation
to—
(a) the imposition of penalties under section 110, and 15
(b) the enforcement of notices under section 109.”</quote>
   <quote>“116A Intentional destruction etc of documents
(1) A person (“P”) commits an offence if the person intentionally alters, 25
suppresses or destroys any document which P has been required
to produce by a notice under section 109.”</quote>
   <quote>“(1) The CMA may impose a penalty on a person in accordance with
section 174D where the CMA considers that—
(a) the person has, without reasonable excuse, failed to comply 25
with any requirement of a notice under section 174;</quote>
   <quote>“(1A)
35
The relevant authority may impose a penalty on a person in
accordance with section 174D where the authority considers that—
(a) the person has, without reasonable excuse, supplied
information that is false or misleading in a material respect
to the authority in connection with any of the authority’s
functions under this Part;</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to several sections of the Enterprise Act 2002. These changes include the introduction of a provisional penalty notice, the substitution of "the CMA" with "the appropriate authority" in various sections, the requirement for the Competition Appeal Tribunal to consider relevant guidance when imposing penalties, the obligation of the CMA to prepare and publish a statement of policy regarding penalties and enforcement of notices, the criminalization of intentional alteration, suppression, or destruction of documents required by a notice under section 109, and the ability of the relevant authority to impose penalties for supplying false or misleading information without reasonable excuse.</summary>

   <impact>4</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>subsection (4)</subject>

   <quote>(6) In subsection (4)—
(a) for the words before paragraph (a) substitute “A penalty imposed 15
under section 174A(1) or (1A) on a person who does not own or
control an enterprise must not—”;
(b) in paragraph (a), for “such amount as the Secretary of State may
by order specify” substitute “£30,000”;
(c) in paragraph (b), for “such amount per day as the Secretary of State 20
may so specify” substitute “£15,000 per day”;
(d) in paragraph (c) omit “as the Secretary of State may so specify”.</quote>

   <summary>The amendment changes the conditions for imposing a penalty under section 174A(1) or (1A) on a person who does not own or control an enterprise. The penalty amount is now fixed at £30,000 and £15,000 per day, instead of being specified by the Secretary of State.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially increase the financial burden on individuals who do not own or control an enterprise but are found in violation of the specified sections of the Act.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>subsection (4A)</subject>

   <quote>(7) After subsection (4) insert—
“(4A)
25
A penalty imposed under section 174A(1) or (1A) on any other
person must not—
(a) in the case of a fixed amount, exceed 1% of the total value
of the turnover (both in and outside the United Kingdom)
of the enterprises owned or controlled by the person;
(b)
30
in the case of an amount calculated by reference to a daily
rate, exceed 5% of the total value of the daily turnover (both
in and outside the United Kingdom) of the enterprises owned
or controlled by the person;
(c) in the case of a fixed amount and an amount calculated by
35
reference to a daily rate, exceed such fixed amount and such
amount per day.”</quote>

   <summary>The insertion introduces new limits on the penalties that can be imposed under section 174A(1) or (1A) on any other person. The penalty must not exceed 1% of the total value of the turnover of the enterprises owned or controlled by the person, or 5% of the total value of the daily turnover of the enterprises owned or controlled by the person.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially increase the financial burden on individuals who own or control an enterprise and are found in violation of the specified sections of the Act.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>subsection (7)</subject>

   <quote>(10) In subsection (7), in the words before paragraph (a), for “an order under
subsection (4) or (5)” substitute “regulations under subsection (6A)”.</quote>

   <summary>The amendment changes the reference in subsection (7) from "an order under subsection (4) or (5)" to "regulations under subsection (6A)".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could potentially affect the legal processes related to the enforcement of penalties under the Act.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Enterprise Act 2002, Sections 112 to 115</subject>
   <quote>(6) Sections 112 to 115 of the Enterprise Act 2002 apply in relation to a penalty imposed under section 35A(1) as they apply in relation to a penalty imposed under section 110(1) or (1A) of that Act, with the following modifications—</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to apply sections 112 to 115 of the Enterprise Act 2002 to penalties imposed under section 35A(1) of the same Act, with certain modifications.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Enterprise Act 2002, Section 114</subject>
   <quote>(b) section 114(5A) is to be read as if the words “In the case of a penalty imposed on a person by the CMA or OFCOM,” were omitted;</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend section 114(5A) of the Enterprise Act 2002 by omitting the words "In the case of a penalty imposed on a person by the CMA or OFCOM".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Enterprise Act 2002, Section 35C</subject>
   <quote>35C Statement of policy in relation to functions under sections 31E, 34 and 35A</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to insert a new section 35C into the Enterprise Act 2002, which requires the CMA to prepare and publish a statement of policy in relation to the exercise of functions under sections 31E, 34 and 35A.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Enterprise Act 2002, Section 94</subject>
   <quote>10 In section 94 (rights to enforce undertakings and orders), after subsection 15 (9) insert— “(10) In deciding whether and, if so, how to proceed under this section, the CMA must have regard to the statement of policy which was most recently published by it under section 94B at the time of the failure to comply with the undertaking or (as the case may be) order.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend section 94 of the Enterprise Act 2002 by adding a new subsection (10), which requires the CMA to consider its most recently published statement of policy when deciding how to proceed under this section.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>substitution</type>
   <subject>Enterprise Act 2002, Section 94A</subject>
   <quote>11 For section 94A substitute— “94AA Enforcement of undertakings and orders: imposition of penalties</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to substitute section 94A of the Enterprise Act 2002 with a new section 94AA, which provides for the enforcement of undertakings and orders and the imposition of penalties.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 94B</subject>
   <quote>Section 94B (statement of policy in relation to powers under sections 94 and 94A) is amended as follows.</quote>
   <summary>The amendment modifies the language used in Section 94B, replacing "powers" with "functions" and "94A" with "94AA".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 161A</subject>
   <quote>After section 161 insert— “161A Acceptance of enforcement undertakings: Part 4</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new section, 161A, which stipulates that the relevant authority cannot accept an enforcement undertaking from a person unless they have been informed about the potential consequences of non-compliance.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 167A and 167B</subject>
   <quote>After section 167 insert— “167A Enforcement of undertakings and orders: imposition of penalties</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces new sections, 167A and 167B, which provide the relevant authority with the power to impose penalties on individuals who fail to comply with enforcement undertakings or orders, without a reasonable excuse. The amount of the penalty is to be determined by the relevant authority and can be a fixed amount, a daily rate, or a combination of both.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 167C</subject>
   <quote>After section 167 insert— “167C Statement of policy in relation to functions under sections 167 and 167A</quote>
   <summary>The bill introduces a new section, 167C, which requires the CMA to prepare and publish a statement of policy regarding the exercise of functions under sections 167 and 167A. The statement must include considerations relevant to the determination of penalty amounts under section 167A.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 60 of the Civil Aviation Act 2012</subject>
   <quote>In subsection (2), in the words before paragraph (a), after “166” insert “, 167C”.</quote>
   <summary>The amendment to Section 60 of the Civil Aviation Act 2012 includes the addition of "167C" to subsection (2), expanding the functions of the CAA under Part 4 of EA 2002.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 62 of the Competition Act 1998</subject>
   <quote>(1) Section 62 (functions of the CAA under CA 1998) is amended as follows. 30
(2) In subsection (2), in the words after paragraph (b), after “31D(1) to (6)”
insert “, 35C”.
(3) In subsection (4), after “31D(1) to (6)” insert “, 35C”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 62 of the Competition Act 1998, specifically subsections (2) and (4), to include a reference to "35C" after "31D(1) to (6)".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 86 of the Transport Act 2000</subject>
   <quote>6 Section 86 of the Transport Act 2000 (functions of the CAA with respect
to competition) is amended as follows.
(1)
(2) In subsection (2), in the words before paragraph (a), after “166” insert “,
167C”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 86 of the Transport Act 2000, specifically subsection (2), to include a reference to "167C" after "166".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 234I of the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000</subject>
   <quote>8 Section 234I (functions of the FCA under Part 4 of EA 2002) is amended
as follows.
(1)
(2) In the list in subsection (3)— 15
(a) after the entry for section 166 of EA 2002 insert—
“section 167C (statement of policy in relation to functions
under sections 167 and 167A);”;</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes to amend Section 234I of the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000, specifically subsection (3), to include a reference to "section 167C (statement of policy in relation to functions under sections 167 and 167A)" after the entry for section 166 of EA 2002.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Schedule 10—Civil penalties: amendments relating to sectoral regulators</subject>

   <quote>In subsection (3), in the words before paragraph (a), after “31D(1) to (6)” insert “, 35C”.</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (3A), after “31D(1) to (6)” insert “, 35C”.</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (8), in paragraph (b), after “31D(1) to (6)” insert “, 35C”.</quote>
   <quote>Omit subsection (9).</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to subsections (3), (3A), and (8) of Schedule 10, specifically inserting ", 35C" after "31D(1) to (6)". Additionally, subsection (9) is proposed to be omitted.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013</subject>

   <quote>The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013 is amended as follows.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013, though the specific changes are not detailed in the provided text.</summary>
   <impact>Unknown</impact>
   <clarity>1</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Part 3 of EA 2002 (mergers), in Chapter 5 (supplementary), for section 126 (service of documents)</subject>

   <quote>In Part 3 of EA 2002 (mergers), in Chapter 5 (supplementary), for section 126 (service of documents) substitute— “126 Service of documents by the CMA, OFCOM or the Secretary of State</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to substitute section 126 of Part 3 of EA 2002, which pertains to the service of documents in the context of mergers. The new section 126 will relate to the service of documents by the CMA, OFCOM, or the Secretary of State.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 3 of Part 1 of CA 1998 (investigation and enforcement)</subject>

   <quote>In Chapter 3 of Part 1 of CA 1998 (investigation and enforcement), after section 44A (inserted by paragraph 2) insert— “44B Extra-territorial application of notices under sections 26 and 40ZD</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to insert a new section, 44B, into Chapter 3 of Part 1 of CA 1998. This new section pertains to the extra-territorial application of notices under sections 26 and 40ZD.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 11—Service and extra-territoriality of notices under CA 1998 and EA 2002</subject>

   <quote>The power is exercisable so as to—
(a) give the notice to a person who is outside the United
Kingdom (subject to subsections (3) and (4));
(b)
5
require the production of a specified document, or the
provision of specified information, held outside the United
Kingdom.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a provision that allows the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) to serve notices and require the production of documents or information from individuals or entities outside the United Kingdom.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security">
      This change could potentially enhance the UK's ability to regulate and enforce its competition laws on a global scale, thereby strengthening its national security.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      This change could potentially impact international businesses operating in the digital market, affecting the UK's economic landscape.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 12 Section 139 ORDERS AND REGULATIONS UNDER CA 1998 AND EA 2002</subject>

   <quote>“(4A) Regulations made under section 35B(7) or 40A(7A) are subject to 20
the affirmative procedure.”
(4) In subsection (5)—
(a) in paragraph (a), after “(4)” insert “or (4A)”;
(b)
25
for the words after paragraph (b) substitute “is subject to the
negative procedure”.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a provision that regulations made under section 35B(7) or 40A(7A) are subject to the affirmative procedure, and changes the procedure for regulations under subsection (5) to the negative procedure.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">
      This change could potentially affect the balance of power between the legislative and executive branches, as it alters the procedures for approving certain regulations.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change could potentially impact the legal processes involved in the enforcement and interpretation of competition laws.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Part 4 of EA 2002 (market studies and market investigations), section 181 (orders under Part 4)</subject>

   <quote>In Part 4 of EA 2002 (market studies and market investigations), section 181 (orders under Part 4) is amended as follows.</quote>
   <quote>In the heading, after “Orders” insert “and regulations”.</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (1), after “order” insert “or regulations”.</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (2), after “order” insert “or regulations”.</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (4)—
(a) omit “174D(4) or (5)”;
(b) for “section 174D” substitute “section 174A(10)”;
(c) for “shall be subject to annulment in pursuance of a resolution of 10
either House of Parliament” substitute “is subject to the negative
procedure”.</quote>
   <quote>After subsection (4) insert—
“(4A)
15
Regulations made under section 167B(9) or 174D(11) are subject to
the negative procedure.”</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (5)—
(a) for “No order shall be made” substitute “An order made”;
(b) for “unless a draft of it has been laid before, and approved by a
20
resolution of, each House of Parliament” substitute “is subject to
the affirmative procedure”.</quote>
   <quote>After subsection (5)—
“(5A) Regulations made under paragraph (b) of the definition of
“qualifying remedial action” in section 161B(3), or under section
167B(7) or 174D(6A), are subject to the affirmative procedure.
(5B) Any provision that may be made by order or regulations under this 25
Part subject to the negative procedure may instead be made by
order or regulations subject to the affirmative procedure.”</quote>
   <quote>In subsection (10), for “174D” substitute “174A(10)”.</quote>
   <quote>After subsection (10) insert—
“(11) Where orders or regulations under this Part are subject to “the 30
affirmative procedure”, the orders or regulations may not be made
unless a draft of the statutory instrument containing them has been
laid before, and approved by a resolution of, each House of
Parliament.
(12) Where orders or regulations under this Act are subject to “the 35
negative procedure”, the statutory instrument containing them is
subject to annulment in pursuance of a resolution of either House
of Parliament.”</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes several amendments to Part 4 of the Enterprise Act 2002, specifically section 181. The changes include the addition of "and regulations" to the heading and subsections (1) and (2), the substitution of "section 174D" with "section 174A(10)" and the replacement of the annulment process with a negative procedure. It also introduces new subsections (4A), (5A), (5B), (11), and (12) which detail the procedures for regulations made under various sections and the conditions for orders or regulations under the affirmative and negative procedures.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Designated Enforcers</subject>

   <quote>All public designated enforcers.</quote>
   <quote>All private designated enforcers.</quote>

   <summary>
     The bill introduces the concept of "designated enforcers" which are divided into public and private entities. These enforcers are authorized to enforce various enactments under the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023 and other acts.
   </summary>

   <impact>3</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The introduction of designated enforcers could potentially change the enforcement landscape of digital markets and competition law, affecting how these laws are implemented and enforced.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power">
      The division of enforcement power between public and private entities could shift the balance of power in the enforcement of digital markets and competition law.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 92 of the Trade Marks Act 1994</subject>

   <quote>All public designated enforcers, other than—
(a) the Department of Health in Northern Ireland;
(b) the Department for Infrastructure in Northern Ireland;
(c) an enforcement authority within the meaning of section 120(15) of the Communications Act 2003 (regulation of premium rate services);
(d) the Maritime and Coastguard Agency;
(e) the Office for the Traffic Commissioner;
(f) the Secretary of State.
(2) All private designated enforcers.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a new provision that designates certain public and private entities as enforcers of Section 92 of the Trade Marks Act 1994. The public entities include the Department of Health and the Department for Infrastructure in Northern Ireland, an enforcement authority as defined in the Communications Act 2003, the Maritime and Coastguard Agency, the Office for the Traffic Commissioner, and the Secretary of State. All private designated enforcers are also included.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The proposed change could potentially impact the enforcement of the Trade Marks Act 1994, potentially leading to more effective enforcement and protection of trademark rights.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Consumer Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977</subject>

   <quote>All public designated enforcers, other than—
(a) the Department of Health in Northern Ireland;
(b) the Department for Infrastructure in Northern Ireland;
(c) an enforcement authority within the meaning of section 120(15) of the Communications Act 2003 (regulation of premium rate services);
(d) the Maritime and Coastguard Agency;
(e) the Office for the Traffic Commissioner;
(f) the Secretary of State.
(2) All private designated enforcers.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a new provision that designates certain public and private entities as enforcers of the Consumer Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977. The public entities include the Department of Health and the Department for Infrastructure in Northern Ireland, an enforcement authority as defined in the Communications Act 2003, the Maritime and Coastguard Agency, the Office for the Traffic Commissioner, and the Secretary of State. All private designated enforcers are also included.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The proposed change could potentially impact the enforcement of the Consumer Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977, potentially leading to more effective enforcement and protection of consumer rights.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Designation of Authorised Enforcers</subject>

   <quote>All public designated enforcers, other than—
(a) the Department of Health in Northern Ireland;
(b) the Department for Infrastructure in Northern Ireland;
(c) an enforcement authority within the meaning of section 120(15) of the Communications Act 2003 (regulation of premium rate services);
(d) the Maritime and Coastguard Agency;
(e) the Office for the Traffic Commissioner;
(f) the Secretary of State.
(2) All private designated enforcers.</quote>

   <summary>The bill designates certain entities as authorised enforcers for various enactments, excluding specific entities such as the Department of Health in Northern Ireland, the Department for Infrastructure in Northern Ireland, an enforcement authority within the meaning of section 120(15) of the Communications Act 2003, the Maritime and Coastguard Agency, the Office for the Traffic Commissioner, and the Secretary of State. It also includes all private designated enforcers.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The designation of authorised enforcers can significantly impact the enforcement of the enactments mentioned, potentially leading to more effective regulation and oversight.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 13—Consumer protection enactments</subject>

   <quote>See regulation 2(b) of the Cancellation of Contracts made in a Consumer’s Home or Consumer Place of Work etc. Contracts Regulations 2008 (S.I. 2008/1816) (Information, Cancellation and Additional Charges) Regulations 2013 (S.I. 2013/3134) for provision about the application of the Regulations in connection with their revocation</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a provision about the application of the Cancellation of Contracts made in a Consumer’s Home or Consumer Place of Work etc. Contracts Regulations 2008 and the Information, Cancellation and Additional Charges Regulations 2013 in connection with their revocation.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change could potentially impact consumer rights, as it pertains to the application of regulations related to the cancellation of contracts made in a consumer's home or place of work.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 13—Consumer protection enactments</subject>

   <quote>See regulation 37(2) of the Package Travel, Package Holidays and Package Tours regulations 1992 (S.I. 1992/3288) Package Travel and Linked Travel Arrangements Regulations 2018 (S.I. 2018/634) for provision about the application of the Regulations in connection with their revocation</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a provision about the application of the Package Travel, Package Holidays and Package Tours regulations 1992 and the Package Travel and Linked Travel Arrangements Regulations 2018 in connection with their revocation.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change could potentially impact consumer rights, as it pertains to the application of regulations related to package travel and linked travel arrangements.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 13—Consumer protection enactments</subject>

   <quote>See Article 6 of the Consumer Sale and Supply of Goods to Consumers Regulations 2002 (S.I. 2002/3045) (Commencement No. 3, Transitional Provisions, Savings and Consequential Amendments) Order 2015 (S.I. 2015/1630) for provision about the application of the regulation in connection with its revocation</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a provision about the application of the Consumer Sale and Supply of Goods to Consumers Regulations 2002 in connection with its revocation.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change could potentially impact consumer rights, as it pertains to the application of regulations related to the sale and supply of goods to consumers.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 14—Direct enforcement enactments</subject>

   <quote>Consumer Credit Act 1974 The whole Act Consumer Rights Act 2015 Parts 1 and 2 Chapter 5 of Part 3 Schedules 2 and 3 Part 3 of Schedule 5 Chapters 1, 2 and 3 of Part 4 Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of the Consumer Credit Act 1974, the Consumer Rights Act 2015, and the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023 into the list of Direct Enforcement Enactments.</summary>

   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change could have a significant impact on consumer rights, as it pertains to the enforcement of key consumer protection acts.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Schedule 5 to CRA 2015 (investigatory powers)</subject>

   <quote>1 Schedule 5 to CRA 2015 (investigatory powers) is amended as follows.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to Schedule 5 of the CRA 2015, which pertains to investigatory powers.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Penalties for non-compliance with information notices</subject>

   <quote>2 (1) Paragraph 15 is amended in accordance with sub-paragraphs (2) and (3).
   (2) In sub-paragraph (3)—
   (a) in the opening words for “may” substitute “must”;
   (b) after paragraph (b) insert—
   “(c) the circumstances in which a monetary penalty may 10
   be payable under this Part of this Schedule in relation
   to non-compliance with the notice.”</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the penalties for non-compliance with information notices. The word "may" is substituted with "must", and a new provision is added to specify the circumstances under which a monetary penalty may be payable for non-compliance.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Non-compliance with notice under paragraph 14: power of court to impose monetary penalties</subject>

   <quote>(3) After paragraph 16 insert—
   15
   “Non-compliance with notice under paragraph 14: power of court to impose
   monetary penalties
   16A (1) This paragraph applies where—
   (a) an enforcer or an officer of an enforcer has given a notice
   to a person (“the respondent”) under paragraph 14, and
   (b)
   20
   the enforcer considers that the respondent has, without
   reasonable excuse, failed to comply with the notice.
   (2) The enforcer or an officer of the enforcer may make an application
   under this paragraph to the court.
   (3) If the court finds that the respondent has, without reasonable
   25
   excuse, failed to comply with the notice, the court may make an
   order that requires the respondent to pay a monetary penalty to
   the enforcer.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of a new provision that gives the court the power to impose monetary penalties for non-compliance with a notice under paragraph 14. This applies when an enforcer or an officer of an enforcer has given a notice and considers that the respondent has failed to comply without a reasonable excuse.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Paragraph 16C</subject>

   <quote>The CMA may by notice (a “final enforcement notice”) impose on the respondent a requirement to do either or both of the following— (a) a requirement to pay a monetary penalty; (b) a requirement to comply with such directions as the CMA considers appropriate for the purpose of securing the respondent’s compliance with the notice under paragraph 14.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that allows the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) to issue a final enforcement notice to a respondent who has failed to comply with a provisional enforcement notice. This final notice can require the respondent to pay a monetary penalty and/or comply with directions set by the CMA to ensure compliance with the original notice.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change strengthens the enforcement powers of the CMA, potentially leading to more effective regulation of digital markets.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">The introduction of monetary penalties could have financial implications for businesses operating in digital markets.</pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Paragraph 16D</subject>

   <quote>A person to whom a final enforcement notice is given may appeal to the appropriate court against— (a) a decision to impose a monetary penalty by virtue of the notice, (b) the nature or amount of any such penalty, or (c) the giving of directions by virtue of the notice.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a new provision that allows a person who has been given a final enforcement notice to appeal against the decision to impose a monetary penalty, the nature or amount of the penalty, or the directions given in the notice.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change provides a legal recourse for those who believe they have been unfairly penalized, potentially leading to more fair and balanced enforcement of digital market regulations.</pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Paragraph 16F</subject>

   <quote>The CMA must prepare and publish a statement of policy in relation to the use of its power to impose penalties under paragraph 16C.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a new requirement for the CMA to prepare and publish a statement of policy regarding its use of power to impose penalties under the new enforcement provisions.</summary>

   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change promotes transparency in the enforcement process, potentially leading to more predictable and consistent application of penalties.</pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulations under this paragraph</subject>
   <quote>Regulations under this paragraph may, in particular, make provision as to—
(a) the amounts which are, or which are not, to be treated as comprising a person’s turnover or daily turnover;
(b) the date or dates by references to which a person’s turnover or daily turnover is to be determined.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of regulations that provide for the determination of a person's turnover or daily turnover. This includes the amounts to be treated as turnover and the dates for such determination.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could have significant implications for businesses operating in digital markets, as it could affect how their turnover is calculated and thus potentially their tax liabilities and regulatory obligations.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Extra-territorial application in relation to notices</subject>
   <quote>This paragraph applies to the exercise of a power of an enforcer to give a person a notice under paragraph 14.
(2) The power is exercisable so as to—
(a) give the notice to a person who is outside the United Kingdom;
(b) require the provision of information held outside the United Kingdom.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of provisions that allow for the extra-territorial application of notices under paragraph 14. This means that notices can be given to persons outside the United Kingdom and can require the provision of information held outside the United Kingdom.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security">This change could potentially enhance the UK's ability to regulate and oversee digital markets, even when the relevant parties or information are located outside the UK.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">This change could potentially raise concerns about jurisdiction and the rights of individuals and businesses located outside the UK.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Companies Act 1985 and Enterprise Act 2002</subject>
   <quote>(1) Schedule 15D to the Companies Act 1985 is amended as follows.
(2) In paragraph 20— 
(a) for “Part 8 of the Enterprise Act 2002” substitute “Chapter 3 or 4 of the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023”;
(b) for “that Part” substitute “that Chapter”.</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the Companies Act 1985 and the Enterprise Act 2002, replacing references to these acts with references to the new Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could have significant implications for companies, as it could change the legal framework under which they operate.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">This change could also have implications for the justice system, as it could change the laws that courts apply in cases involving digital markets and competition.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Part 2 of Schedule 2, Schedule 11A, Regulatory Enforcement and Sanctions Act 2008, Consumer Rights Act 2015</subject>

   <quote>In Part 2 of Schedule 2—
(a) in paragraph 28—
(i)
30
for “Part 8 of the Enterprise Act 2002” substitute “Chapter
3 or 4 of Part 3 of the Digital Markets, Competition and
Consumers Act 2023”;
(ii) for “that Part” substitute “that Chapter”;</quote>
   <quote>(3) In Schedule 11A—
330 Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Bill
Schedule 16—Part 3: minor and consequential amendments 
(a) in paragraph 42, for the words after “under” to the end substitute
“Chapter 3 or 4 of Part 3 of the Digital Markets, Competition and
Consumers Act 2023 (enforcement of consumer protection law)”;</quote>
   <quote>8 In Schedule 3 to the Regulatory Enforcement and Sanctions Act 2008, at
the appropriate place insert—
“Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2003, Chapters 3 and 4 10
of Part 3”.</quote>
   <quote>9 (1) Schedule 5 to CRA 2015 (investigatory powers) is amended as follows.
(2) In paragraph 2—
(a) in sub-paragraph (1), omit paragraph (b); 15
(b) in sub-paragraph (2) for paragraph (b) substitute—
“(b) an authorised enforcer for the purposes of that Part
(see paragraph 20(7)).”</quote>

   <summary>The proposed changes involve amendments to various parts of existing legislation, replacing references to the Enterprise Act 2002 with references to the new Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023. This includes changes to Part 2 of Schedule 2, Schedule 11A, the Regulatory Enforcement and Sanctions Act 2008, and the Consumer Rights Act 2015. The changes also involve the insertion of the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2003 into the Regulatory Enforcement and Sanctions Act 2008, and amendments to the Consumer Rights Act 2015's provisions on investigatory powers.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">The changes could have significant economic implications, as they involve the regulation of competition in digital markets, which could affect a wide range of businesses and consumers.</pillar>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The changes could also have implications for the justice system, as they involve amendments to existing legislation and could therefore affect legal processes and enforcement mechanisms.</pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Various sections of the Sale of Goods Act 1979, Supply of Goods and Services Act 1982, and other regulations</subject>

   <quote>Sections 13 to 15, 15B, 20 and 32 of the Sale of Goods Act 1979, to the extent that those sections continue to apply to a contract for a trader to supply goods to a consumer by virtue of the saving made, in connection with their amendment by this Act, by Article 6 of the Consumer Rights Act 2015 (Commencement No. 3, Transitional Provisions, Savings and Consequential Amendments) Order 2015.</quote>
   <quote>Sections 48A to 48F of the Sale of Goods Act 1979, to the extent that those sections remain in force by virtue of the saving made, in connection with their repeal by this Act, by Article 6 of the Consumer Rights Act 2015 (Commencement No. 3, Transitional Provisions, Savings and Consequential Amendments) Order 2015.</quote>
   <quote>Sections 3 to 5, 11C to 11E and 13 of the Supply of Goods and Services Act 1982, and any rule of law in Scotland which provides comparable protection to section 13, to the extent that those sections continue to apply to a contract for a trader to supply goods or, in the case of section 13, a contract for a trader to supply a service, to a consumer by virtue of the saving made, in connection with their amendment by this Act, by Article 6 of the Consumer Rights Act 2015 (Commencement No. 3, Transitional Provisions, Savings and Consequential Amendments) Order 2015.</quote>
   <quote>Sections 11M to 11S of the Supply of Goods and Services Act 1982 to the extent that those sections remain in force by virtue of the saving made, in connection with their repeal by this Act, by Article 6 of the Consumer Rights Act 2015 (Commencement No. 3, Transitional Provisions, Savings and Consequential Amendments) Order 2015.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to various sections of the Sale of Goods Act 1979 and the Supply of Goods and Services Act 1982. These amendments are connected to the saving made by Article 6 of the Consumer Rights Act 2015 (Commencement No. 3, Transitional Provisions, Savings and Consequential Amendments) Order 2015.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Various regulations and directives</subject>

   <quote>The Package Travel, Package Holidays and Package Tours Regulations 1992, to the extent that those Regulations remain in force by virtue of the saving made, in connection with their revocation, by regulation 37(2) of the Package Travel and Linked Travel Arrangements Regulations 2018.</quote>
   <quote>The Unfair Terms in Consumer Contracts Regulations 1999, to the extent that those Regulations remain in force by virtue of the saving made, in connection with their revocation by this Act, by Article 6 of the Consumer Rights Act 2015 (Commencement No. 3, Transitional Provisions, Savings and Consequential Amendments) Order 2015.</quote>
   <quote>Rules made under sections 137A, 137R and 137T of the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 which give effect to Articles 10, 11, 13 to 18 and 21 to 23, Chapter 10 and Annexes I and II of Directive 2014/17/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council of 4 February 2014 on credit agreements for consumers relating to residential immovable property.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to various regulations and directives, including the Package Travel, Package Holidays and Package Tours Regulations 1992, the Unfair Terms in Consumer Contracts Regulations 1999, and rules made under sections 137A, 137R and 137T of the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Paragraph 32, sub-paragraph (3) of the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023</subject>

   <quote>In paragraph 32, in sub-paragraph (3)— (a) in paragraph (b)— (i) for “a Schedule 13 enforcer” substitute “an authorised enforcer”; (ii) for “Schedule 13 infringement” substitute “relevant infringement (as defined by paragraph 20(8))”; (b) in paragraph (c) for “a Schedule 13 enforcer” substitute “an authorised enforcer”.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes to amend paragraph 32, sub-paragraph (3) of the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023, replacing "a Schedule 13 enforcer" with "an authorised enforcer" and "Schedule 13 infringement" with "relevant infringement (as defined by paragraph 20(8))".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 17—Part 3: transitional and saving provisions in relation to Part 3</subject>

   <quote>The old law continues to apply—
(a) in respect of conduct of a person that takes place before the commencement date;
(b) for the purposes of the taking of enforcement action relating to a breach of an order made by, or undertaking given to, the court under the old law;
(c) in a case where proceedings before a court under the old law have been started against a person before the commencement date, for the purposes of the continuation and completion of those proceedings (including any appeals relating to the proceedings).</quote>

   <summary>
     The bill proposes that the old law will continue to apply in cases where conduct took place before the commencement date of the new law, for enforcement action related to breaches of orders or undertakings under the old law, and for proceedings that have already started under the old law before the commencement date of the new law.
   </summary>

   <impact>3</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change ensures that ongoing legal proceedings and enforcement actions under the old law are not disrupted by the introduction of the new law. It provides legal certainty and continuity for those involved in such cases.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 17—Part 3: transitional and saving provisions in relation to Part 3</subject>

   <quote>This paragraph applies where conduct of a person is continuing conduct.
(2) The new law applies in respect of the person’s post-commencement conduct.
(3) The new law also applies in respect of the person’s pre-commencement conduct for the purposes of enabling the taking of enforcement action under Chapter 3 or 4 of Part 3 in relation to that conduct.</quote>

   <summary>
     The bill proposes that the new law will apply to ongoing conduct that continues after the commencement date of the new law. The new law will also apply to pre-commencement conduct for the purpose of enforcement action under certain chapters of Part 3.
   </summary>

   <impact>3</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change provides clarity on how the new law will apply to ongoing conduct that spans the transition from the old law to the new law. It ensures that enforcement action can be taken under the new law even for conduct that began before its commencement.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 18 Section 218</subject>

   <quote>COMMERCIAL PRACTICES WHICH ARE IN ALL CIRCUMSTANCES CONSIDERED UNFAIR
1 Claiming to be a signatory to a code of conduct when the trader is not.
2 Claiming that a code of conduct has an endorsement from a public or private body which it does not have.
3 Displaying a trust mark, quality mark or equivalent without having obtained the necessary authorisation.</quote>

   <summary>
     The bill proposes a list of commercial practices that are considered unfair in all circumstances. These include falsely claiming to be a signatory to a code of conduct, falsely claiming that a code of conduct has an endorsement it does not have, and displaying a trust mark or quality mark without the necessary authorisation.
   </summary>

   <impact>4</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Protection">
      This change provides clear guidelines on what constitutes unfair commercial practices, which will help protect consumers from deceptive or misleading practices.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Commercial practices considered unfair</subject>

   <quote>Falsely claiming or creating the false impression that the trader is not acting for purposes relating to the trader’s business or falsely representing oneself as a consumer.</quote>
   <quote>Creating the impression that the consumer cannot leave the premises until a contract is formed.</quote>
   <quote>Ignoring a request from a consumer to leave or not return to the consumer’s home except in circumstances and to the extent justified to enforce a contractual obligation.</quote>
   <quote>Making persistent and unwanted solicitations by any means, other than by attending at the consumer’s home, except in circumstances and to the extent justified to enforce a contractual obligation.</quote>
   <quote>Requiring a consumer who wishes to claim on an insurance policy to produce documents which could not reasonably be considered relevant as to whether the claim was valid, or failing systematically to respond to correspondence, in order to dissuade a consumer from exercising the consumer’s contractual rights.</quote>
   <quote>Including in an advertisement a direct appeal to children to buy advertised products or persuade their parents or other adults to buy advertised products for them.</quote>
   <quote>Supplying products to a consumer that have not been requested by the consumer and demanding that the consumer— (a) pays for the products, (b) returns the products, or (c) safely stores the products.</quote>
   <quote>Explicitly telling a consumer that if the consumer does not buy the product, the trader’s job or livelihood will be at risk.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a list of commercial practices that are considered unfair. These include falsely representing oneself as a consumer, creating the impression that a consumer cannot leave the premises until a contract is formed, ignoring a consumer's request to leave or not return to their home, making persistent and unwanted solicitations, requiring a consumer to produce irrelevant documents to claim on an insurance policy, including a direct appeal to children in advertisements, supplying products to a consumer that have not been requested, and telling a consumer that the trader's job or livelihood will be at risk if the consumer does not buy the product.</summary>

   <impact>4</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      These changes significantly enhance consumer rights by clearly defining unfair commercial practices and providing consumers with clear protections against such practices.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      These changes could have a significant economic impact by potentially altering the practices of businesses and traders, particularly those in the digital market.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Excluded contracts</subject>

   <quote>A contract between an electricity supplier and a consumer for the supply of electricity to any premises.</quote>
   <quote>A contract between a gas supplier and a consumer for the supply of gas to any premises.</quote>
   <quote>A contract between a heat supplier and a consumer for the supply of heating, cooling or hot water by means of a relevant heat network.</quote>
   <quote>In England and Wales, a contract between a licensed water supplier, or licensed sewerage supplier, and a consumer for the supply of water or sewerage services.</quote>
   <quote>In Scotland, a contract between a licensed water supplier, or licensed sewerage supplier, and a consumer for the supply of water or sewerage services.</quote>
   <quote>In Northern Ireland— (a) a contract between a water undertaker and a consumer for the supply of water pursuant to Article 94 of the Water and Sewerage Services (Northern Ireland) Order 2006 (S.I. 2006/3336 (N.I. 21)); (b) a contract between a sewerage undertaker and a consumer for the supply of sewerage services pursuant to Chapter 3 of Part 6 of that Order.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a list of contracts that are excluded from the regulations. These include contracts between a consumer and an electricity supplier, a gas supplier, a heat supplier, a licensed water supplier, a licensed sewerage supplier, a water undertaker, and a sewerage undertaker.</summary>

   <impact>3</impact>

   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      These changes clarify the types of contracts that are not subject to the regulations, providing consumers with a clear understanding of their rights and protections under different types of contracts.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      These changes could have an economic impact by potentially affecting the practices of businesses and traders in the utilities sector.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>

   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Contracts between unincorporated traders and consumers</subject>

   <quote>A contract between a trader who is not a body corporate and a consumer for the supply of foodstuffs, beverages or other goods intended for current consumption in the household where the condition in sub-paragraph (2) or (3) is met.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces conditions for contracts between unincorporated traders and consumers for the supply of foodstuffs, beverages, or other goods intended for current consumption in the household. The conditions include the goods being supplied by way of frequent or regular delivery to the consumer's home, residence, or workplace, and not being delivered wholly or mainly by a third party.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially impact small businesses and consumers, as it sets out specific conditions for contracts between unincorporated traders and consumers.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Contracts for childcare</subject>

   <quote>A contract for the supply of goods, services or digital content for, or in connection with, the provision of childcare by a relevant childcare provider.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces provisions for contracts related to the supply of goods, services, or digital content in connection with the provision of childcare by a relevant childcare provider. It also provides detailed definitions of who qualifies as a "relevant childcare provider" in different regions of the UK.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Education">This change could impact the childcare sector, as it sets out specific conditions for contracts related to the provision of childcare.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Pre-contract information and reminder notices</subject>

   <quote>The information referred to in section 249(1)(a) is as follows.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a list of key pre-contract information that must be provided to the consumer, including details about the contract's duration, the frequency and amount of payments, and the steps the consumer must take to end the contract.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">This change could potentially enhance consumer rights, as it requires traders to provide clear and comprehensive pre-contract information to consumers.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Pre-contract information and reminder notices</subject>

   <quote>18 The arrangements for payment, delivery, performance, and the time by
which the trader undertakes to deliver the goods, to perform the services
or to supply the digital content.</quote>
   <quote>19 The trader’s complaint handling policy.</quote>
   <quote>20 The following information about the consumer’s right to cancel the 5
subscription contract during the initial cooling-off period—
(a) when that period begins and ends;
(b) how the consumer may exercise the right;
(c)
10
if the consumer may lose the right, the circumstances under which
that will happen;
(d) the consequences of the consumer exercising the right, including—
(i) any refund the consumer may be entitled to,
(ii) any reason that refund might be diminished, and
(iii)
15
in respect of a contract for the supply of goods, whether the
consumer will be responsible for returning those goods to
the trader, including the likely cost of returning the goods
if they cannot normally be returned by post.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of new regulations that require traders to provide detailed pre-contract information to consumers. This includes arrangements for payment, delivery, and performance, the trader's complaint handling policy, and detailed information about the consumer's right to cancel the subscription contract during the initial cooling-off period.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change significantly enhances consumer rights by ensuring they are fully informed before entering into a contract. It also provides clear guidelines on how consumers can exercise their right to cancel a contract, potentially reducing disputes and enhancing consumer protection.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Reminder notices</subject>

   <quote>28
20
The information referred to in section 252(1)(a) (information that must be
contained in a reminder notice) is as follows.</quote>
   <quote>29 That the consumer will become liable for the renewal payment to which
the notice relates unless the consumer takes steps to bring the contract to
an end.</quote>
   <quote>30
25
The date (“the renewal date”) on which the consumer will become liable
for the renewal payment and its amount.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of new regulations that require traders to provide consumers with reminder notices containing specific information. This includes a warning that the consumer will become liable for the renewal payment unless they take steps to end the contract, and the date and amount of the renewal payment.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Consumer Rights">
      This change significantly enhances consumer rights by ensuring they are fully informed about their liabilities under a contract. It also provides clear guidelines on how consumers can avoid becoming liable for renewal payments, potentially reducing disputes and enhancing consumer protection.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 22 Section 288</subject>

   <quote>EXEMPT ADR PROVIDERS
PART 1
LIST OF EXEMPT PERSONS
The Commission for Local Administration in England (also known as the Local 25
Government and Social Care Ombudsman) and each Local Commissioner within
the meaning of section 23(3) of the Local Government Act 1974
The Consumer Council for Water
The Health Service Commissioner for England
The Legal Ombudsman 30
The Northern Ireland Public Services Ombudsman
The Office of the Independent Adjudicator for Higher Education (registered
company number 04823842) in relation to its functions as the designated operator
under section 13 of the Higher Education Act 2004
Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Bill 357
Schedule 22—Exempt ADR providers
Part 1—List of exempt persons 
The Parliamentary Commissioner for Administration
The Pensions Ombudsman
The Public Services Ombudsman for Wales or Ombwdsmon Gwasanaethau
Cyhoeddus Cymru
The Scottish Legal Complaints Commission 5
The Scottish Public Services Ombudsman
PART 2
EXEMPT REDRESS SCHEMES
An approved estate agents redress scheme
An approved postal operators redress scheme 10
An approved social housing ombudsman scheme
Approved public communications provider dispute procedures
The Financial Ombudsman Scheme
A qualifying lettings agency work redress scheme
A qualifying property management work redress scheme 15
A qualifying redress scheme for the gas or electricity sector</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces a list of exempt ADR (Alternative Dispute Resolution) providers and redress schemes. These include various ombudsman services, councils, and schemes related to estate agents, postal operators, social housing, public communications, financial services, lettings agency work, property management work, and the gas or electricity sector.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The exemption of these ADR providers and redress schemes could potentially impact the justice system by altering the mechanisms through which disputes in these areas are resolved.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 23 Section 293</subject>

   <quote>ACCREDITATION CRITERIA
PART 1
THE CRITERIA APPLICABLE TO AN ACCREDITED ADR PROVIDER
Criterion 1: information for consumers
1 The ADR provider provides consumers generally with accessible information 15
about the ADR that it carries out or for which it makes special ADR
arrangements.
(1)
(2) The information provided should include (among other things) information
about—
(a) the kinds of ADR it carries out or for which it makes special ADR 20
arrangements (including the possible outcomes of each kind);
(b) the types of dispute it deals with (whether by carrying out ADR or
making special ADR arrangements);
(c)
25
the procedures adopted in relation to ADR carried out by it or for
which it makes special ADR arrangements;
(d) any fees or costs payable by either party to a dispute that is referred
for ADR.
Criterion 2: readiness to carry out ADR
2
30
The ADR provider does not unreasonably refuse to carry out ADR or, as
the case may be, to make special ADR arrangements, in relation to disputes
referred to it.
Criterion 3: expertise
3 The ADR provider has sufficient expertise for carrying out ADR or, as the
35
case may be, for making special ADR arrangements, in relation to the types
of dispute it deals with.</quote>

   <summary>The bill introduces accreditation criteria for ADR providers. These criteria include providing accessible information to consumers, readiness to carry out ADR, and having sufficient expertise for carrying out ADR.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The introduction of these accreditation criteria could impact the justice system by setting standards for ADR providers, potentially affecting the quality and accessibility of dispute resolution services.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Schedule 24 Section 301</subject>

   <quote>CHAPTER 4 OF PART 4: CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS ETC
Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 20
1 In Schedule 17 to the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 (ombudsman
scheme), omit the following provisions—
(a) in paragraph 1, the definition of “ADR entity”;
(b) paragraph 2(2);
(c) paragraph 14(3A). 25
Consumer Rights Act 2015
2 (1) Schedule 5 to CRA 2015 (investigatory powers etc) is amended as follows.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 and the Consumer Rights Act 2015. In the former, it omits certain provisions related to the ombudsman scheme. In the latter, it amends Schedule 5, although the specific amendments are not provided in the given text.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">The proposed amendments could impact the justice system by altering the ombudsman scheme under the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 and the investigatory powers under the Consumer Rights Act 2015.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Chapter 4 of Part 4 of the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023</subject>
   <quote>“In the table in paragraph 11 (enforcer’s legislation: legislation mentioned in paragraph 9(1)(b)), at the appropriate place insert— Chapter 4 of Part 4 of the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes the insertion of Chapter 4 of Part 4 of the Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2023 into the table in paragraph 11 of the enforcer's legislation.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Part 3 of EA 2002</subject>
   <quote>“Amendments to Part 3 of EA 2002”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to Part 3 of the Enterprise Act 2002.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Part 9 of EA 2002</subject>
   <quote>“Amendment to Part 9 of EA 2002”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes an amendment to Part 9 of the Enterprise Act 2002.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>CA 1998</subject>
   <quote>“Amendments to CA 1998”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the Competition Act 1998.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>The Civil Aviation Act 2012</subject>
   <quote>“The Civil Aviation Act 2012 is amended as follows.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the Civil Aviation Act 2012, specifically requiring the Civil Aviation Authority (CAA) to make decisions or take actions as soon as reasonably practicable.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>The Financial Services and Markets Act 2000</subject>
   <quote>“The Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 is amended as follows.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes amendments to the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000, specifically requiring the Financial Conduct Authority (FCA) to make decisions or take actions as soon as reasonably practicable.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 234J of the Competition Act 1998</subject>
   <quote>In section 234J (functions of the FCA under CA 1998), after subsection (5) insert—
“(6) In making any decision, or otherwise taking action, for the purposes
of any of its functions that—
(a) by virtue of this section, are functions exercisable 5
concurrently with the CMA, and
(b) are functions within Schedule 4A to the Enterprise and
Regulatory Reform Act 2013 by virtue of paragraph 5 of that
Schedule,
the FCA must have regard to the need for making a decision, or 10
taking action, as soon as reasonably practicable.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes an insertion to Section 234J of the Competition Act 1998, requiring the Financial Conduct Authority (FCA) to consider the need for expedient decision-making or action in its functions that are concurrently exercisable with the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) and are within Schedule 4A to the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Act 2013.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially speed up decision-making processes within the FCA, which could have implications for the speed and efficiency of competition regulation in the financial sector.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Article 29 of the Water and Sewerage Services (Northern Ireland) Order 2006</subject>
   <quote>In Article 29 of the Water and Sewerage Services (Northern Ireland) Order
2006 (S.I. 2006/3336 (N.I. 21)) (functions of the Northern Ireland Authority
for Utility Regulation with respect to competition), after paragraph (10)
insert—
“(11) In making any decision, or otherwise taking action, for the purposes
of any of its functions that—
(a)
20
by virtue of this Article, are functions exercisable
concurrently with the CMA, and
(b) in the case of functions under the Competition Act 1998, are
functions within Schedule 4A to the Enterprise and
Regulatory Reform Act 2013 by virtue of paragraph 5 of that
Schedule,
the Authority must have regard to the need for making a decision, 25
or taking action, as soon as reasonably practicable.”</quote>
   <summary>The bill proposes an insertion to Article 29 of the Water and Sewerage Services (Northern Ireland) Order 2006, requiring the Northern Ireland Authority for Utility Regulation to consider the need for expedient decision-making or action in its functions that are concurrently exercisable with the CMA and are within Schedule 4A to the Enterprise and Regulatory Reform Act 2013.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">This change could potentially speed up decision-making processes within the Northern Ireland Authority for Utility Regulation, which could have implications for the speed and efficiency of competition regulation in the utility sector in Northern Ireland.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change></all>