<all><change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 1</subject>

   <quote>(1) For the purposes of section 6(1) of the 2001 Act, this section and section 2
authorise the use of resources in the year ending 31 March 2024.</quote>
   <quote>(2) In that year, the use of resources by the persons mentioned in subsection (3) 5
is authorised up to the amount of £27,403,514,000.</quote>
   <quote>(3) The persons are—
(a) the Northern Ireland departments;
(b) the Food Standards Agency;
(c) the Northern Ireland Assembly Commission; 10
(d) the Northern Ireland Audit Office;
(e) the Northern Ireland Authority for Utility Regulation;
(f) the Northern Ireland Public Services Ombudsman;
(g) the Public Prosecution Service for Northern Ireland.</quote>

   <summary>Section 1 authorizes the use of resources for the year ending 31 March 2024, with a total amount of £27,403,514,000. The authorized persons include the Northern Ireland departments, the Food Standards Agency, the Northern Ireland Assembly Commission, the Northern Ireland Audit Office, the Northern Ireland Authority for Utility Regulation, the Northern Ireland Public Services Ombudsman, and the Public Prosecution Service for Northern Ireland.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 2</subject>

   <quote>(1) The Schedule contains estimates relating to the persons mentioned in section
1(3) for the year ending 31 March 2024 (“Schedule estimates”).</quote>
   <quote>(2)
5
In the year ending 31 March 2024, a person mentioned in section 1(3) may
use resources in accordance with subsections (3) to (7) and the Schedule
estimate relating to that person.</quote>
   <quote>(3) The person may use resources for the purposes specified in Part 2 of the
estimate; but this is subject to subsections (4) to (7).</quote>

   <summary>Section 2 establishes that the Schedule contains estimates for the year ending 31 March 2024. It allows a person mentioned in section 1(3) to use resources in accordance with the Schedule estimate and for the purposes specified in Part 2 of the estimate.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 4</subject>

   <quote>(1)
35
The sum that the Department may issue out of the Consolidated Fund under
section 3 may be used for the year ending 31 March 2024 in accordance with
subsection (2).</quote>
   <quote>(2) The sum specified in Part 1 of a Schedule estimate as a money requirement
may be used by the person to whom the estimate relates for the purposes
specified in Part 2 of the estimate.</quote>

   <summary>Section 4 allows the sum issued out of the Consolidated Fund under section 3 to be used for the year ending 31 March 2024 in accordance with the Schedule estimate. The sum specified in Part 1 of the estimate can be used by the person for the purposes specified in Part 2 of the estimate.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 6</subject>

   <quote>(1)
15
In the year ending 31 March 2024, a person mentioned in section 1(3) may
use income from a source specified in Part 3 of the Schedule estimate relating
to that person for a purpose specified in Part 2 of the estimate; but this is
subject to subsections (2) to (5).</quote>
   <quote>(2) Where the income is received in connection with current purposes, the
person—
(a) may use the income for current purposes; 20
(b) must not use the income for capital purposes.</quote>
   <quote>(3) Where the income is received in connection with capital purposes, the person—
(a) may use the income for capital purposes;
(b) must not use the income for current purposes.</quote>

   <summary>Section 6 allows a person mentioned in section 1(3) to use income from a specified source for a purpose specified in the Schedule estimate. If the income is received in connection with current purposes, it can be used for current purposes only, and if it is received in connection with capital purposes, it can be used for capital purposes only.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Annually managed expenditure</subject>

   <quote>Expenditure arising from:
Take up and maintenance of departmental and ALB’s provisions and associated non-cash
items including but not restricted to: bad debts, impairments, tax and pension costs for the
Department, its ALBs and payment of corporation tax.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the inclusion of expenditure related to the take up and maintenance of departmental and ALB's provisions, including bad debts, impairments, tax and pension costs.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Departmental expenditure limit</subject>

   <quote>Net resources for current purposes 2,579,091,000</quote>
   <quote>Net resources for capital purposes 220,618,000</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes a departmental expenditure limit of £2,579,091,000 for current purposes and £220,618,000 for capital purposes.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Annually managed expenditure</subject>

   <quote>Net resources for current purposes 304,211,000</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes an annually managed expenditure of £304,211,000 for current purposes.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Department of Education – Teachers’ Superannuation Estimate</subject>

   <quote>Annually managed expenditure
Expenditure arising from:
Pensions, allowances, gratuities etc; certain payments to the Northern Ireland National
Insurance Fund; certain payments in respect of premature retirement compensation made
to members of the scheme and on behalf of their employers; expenditure on activities that
are required as a result of the United Kingdom’s exit from the European Union; severance
payments; compensation payments; governmental response to the coronavirus COVID-19
pandemic; UK COVID-19 Inquiry activities; other non-cash items.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the inclusion of expenditure related to pensions, allowances, gratuities, payments to the National Insurance Fund, premature retirement compensation, severance payments, compensation payments, and other non-cash items for the Department of Education.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Education"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Department of Finance Estimate</subject>

   <quote>Departmental expenditure limit
Expenditure arising from:
Finance, procurement and policy including Public Sector Reform; Business Consultancy
Services; Construction and Procurement Delivery; the Departmental Solicitor’s Office;
Internal Audit Services; NICS shared services for personnel, finance, ICT including cyber
security, training, digital transformation and service related administration costs; NICS
Accommodation Services including for the wider public sector; receipt of grants; the
administration of centralised funds; services provided by the Northern Ireland Statistics
and Research Agency and Land and Property Services; grants to district councils; net
operational and programme costs of the Special European Union Programmes Body;
payment and income under the European Union structural funds programmes; operational
costs of the Fiscal Council; the sponsorship and provision of secretariats in respect of other
independent bodies; funding to support the Boardroom Apprentice Programme; other
common services; settlement of NICS equal pay claims; expenditure on activities that are
required as a result of the United Kingdom’s exit from the European Union; governmental
response to the coronavirus COVID-19 pandemic; UK COVID-19 Inquiry activities;
severance payments; compensation payments; other non-cash items.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the inclusion of expenditure related to finance, procurement, policy, public sector reform, business consultancy services, construction and procurement delivery, and other non-cash items for the Department of Finance.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Department of Health Estimate</subject>

   <quote>Departmental expenditure limit
Expenditure arising from:
Central expenditure on hospital, paramedic and ambulance services; community health
services; family health services; social care services; public health and wellbeing
programmes; fire and rescue services; training; European Union programmes; expenditure
on activities that are required as a result of the United Kingdom’s exit from the European
Union; payments under Shared Island Funding; governmental response to the coronavirus
COVID-19 pandemic; response to emerging health issues; grants to voluntary
organisations and other bodies; payments to other government departments; services
provided on behalf of other departments; repayment of grants; repayment of loans; reviews
and inquiries; UK COVID-19 Inquiry activities; compensation, settlement of legal claims
and ex-gratia payments; indemnities; payments from provisions; severance payments;
administration; related services; profit or loss on disposal of assets; depreciation and
impairments; write offs; bad debts; related expenditure; other non-cash items.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the inclusion of expenditure related to hospital services, community health services, social care services, public health programs, and other non-cash items for the Department of Health.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Health and Public Health"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Department of Justice Estimate</subject>

   <quote>Departmental expenditure limit
Expenditure arising from:
Access to Justice services and policy development, including expenditure by Legal
Services Agency NI, NI Courts and Tribunals Service, and costs relating to the Historical
Institutional Abuse Redress Board and associated compensation payments; costs relating
to the Victims' Payments Board and associated payments for the Troubles Permanent
Disablement Payment Scheme; the Parole Commissioners for NI and the NI Law
Commission, net expenditure for the Criminal Justice Inspection. Safer Communities
services and policy development, including expenditure by Forensic Science NI, Youth
Justice Agency, net expenditure for the Probation Board for NI, Police Ombudsman for
NI, NI Policing Board, NI Police Fund, Police Rehabilitation and Retraining Trust and the
RUC George Cross Foundation, also expenditure on state pathology services and the
Prisoner Ombudsman, Independent Monitoring Boards, and search and rescue services.
Reducing Offending services and policy development including expenditure by the NI
Prison Service and Youth Justice Agency. Policing including net expenditure by the Police
Service of NI, and net expenditure of the Independent Assessor of PSNI Recruitment
Vetting. Historical investigations and other legacy costs; implementation of the Stormont
House Agreement and Fresh Start Agreement; Access NI; compensation schemes;
expenditure on activities that are required as a result of the United Kingdom’s exit from
the European Union; administration costs; settlement of equal pay claims, severance
payments, pension scheme payments including pension scheme benefits to or in respect of
persons covered by the Northern Ireland Judicial Pension Scheme, related services;
governmental response to the coronavirus COVID-19 pandemic, UK Covid-19 Inquiry
activities; period products costs; other non-cash items.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the inclusion of expenditure related to access to justice services, policy development, safer communities services, reducing offending services, policing, historical investigations, and other non-cash items for the Department of Justice.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>The Executive Office Estimate</subject>

   <quote>Departmental expenditure limit
Expenditure arising from:
Support to the Executive Committee; the co-ordination of policy; strategic corporate
communications; support to the Head of the NI Civil Service and NICS Board, including
net expenses of NICS Board Non Executive Members; net expenses of the Attorney
General for Northern Ireland and the Commissioner for Public Appointments for Northern
Ireland; public appointments policy and strategy; the skills development and support of
public appointees and potential public appointees and actions to improve broader public
sector governance and capacity; public appointments including the appointment of the
Commissioner for Children and Young People for Northern Ireland, and the
Commissioner for Older People for Northern Ireland; the Irish Language Commissioner,
the Commissioner for the Ulster Scots and the Ulster British tradition and the Office of
Identity and Cultural Expression; support for the Compact Civic Advisory Panel; net
expenses of the Strategic Investment Board Limited; net expenses of the Northern Ireland
Judicial Appointments Commission; the North-South Ministerial Council; the BritishIrish Council; machinery for the conduct of Inter-governmental Relations; civil
contingencies and resilience; maintenance of Regional Headquarters Ballymena as
required under Article 3 of the Historic Monument and Archaeological Objects (NI) Order
1995; policy on standards in public life; the Reinvestment and Reform Initiative; the
regeneration of Ebrington; net expenses of the Maze/Long Kesh Development
Corporation; delivery of a Programme for Government; development of and supporting
the delivery of an Investment Strategy NI, associated plans and governance mechanisms;
promotion of human rights, equality of opportunity and social inclusion and the alleviation
of disadvantage including in situations of severe stress, crisis or emergency; net expenses
of the Equality Commission for Northern Ireland; actions related to the Historical
Institutional Abuse Redress Board and the Commissioner for Survivors of Institutional
Childhood Abuse within the Historical Institutional Abuse (NI) Act 2019 including,
payments to the designated department under that Act for administrative costs of the
Board, awards of compensation and costs and expenses in connection with applications
and appeals; and other implementation-related actions from the Hart Report, including a
memorial, seeking contributions from Institutions towards the costs of redress and services
for victims and survivors; work associated with historical clerical child abuse, Mother and
Baby Homes and Magdalene Laundries and workhouses (covering the work in Truth
Recovery Design Report published in October 21) ; net expenses of the Commissioner for
Survivors of Institutional Childhood Abuse; the actions and commitments contained in the
Executive’s Good Relations Strategy Together: Building a United Community including
the T:BUC Camps Programme, Planned Interventions Programme, the Central Good
Relations Fund and the District Councils Good Relations Programme, the Urban Villages
programme; the policy, funding and legislative implementation of the Racial Equality
Strategy; and actions associated with Refugee and Asylum Seeker support and integration,
including support for those displaced as a result of global conflict or other emergency
situation; net expenses of the Northern Ireland Community Relations Council; the
European Union Programme for Peace and Reconciliation; delivering social change
including the associated Executive Funds; the promotion of Social Value; victims and
survivors including actions and payments associated with the operation of the Victims
Payments Scheme for Permanent Disablement; net expenses of the Victims and Survivors
Service Limited; net expenses of the Commission for Victims and Survivors for Northern
Ireland; implementation of the Stormont House Agreement and the Fresh Start Agreement;
actions associated with the implementation of the New Decade, New Approach Deal; the
Commission on Flags, Identity, Culture and Tradition; net expense of the Irish Language
Commissioner, the Commissioner for the Ulster Scots and the Ulster British Tradition and
the Office of Identity and Cultural Expression; promoting the devolved administration’s
interests internationally by supporting the development of relationships with stakeholders
overseas, inward visitors, and representatives from overseas on devolved matters,
supporting international activities of benefit to NI, including establishing, maintaining and
developing the work of the offices overseas; in particular managing and promoting the
devolved administration’s interests in Europe; policy development in respect of the
devolved administration’s responsibilities and interests in relation to the EU following the
UK’s exit; expenditure on devolved functions that are required as a result of the 
United Kingdom’s exit from the European Union; administration costs; settlement of equal
pay claims, severance payments, pension scheme payments including pension scheme
benefits to or in respect of persons covered by the Northern Ireland Judicial Pension
Scheme, related services; governmental response to the coronavirus COVID-19 pandemic,
UK Covid-19 Inquiry activities; period products costs; other non-cash items.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the inclusion of expenditure related to support to the Executive Committee, policy coordination, strategic corporate communications, public appointments, human rights promotion, victims and survivors support, and other non-cash items for The Executive Office.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Department of Health – Health and Social Care Pension Scheme Estimate</subject>

   <quote>Annually managed expenditure
Expenditure arising from:
Pension payments, allowances, gratuities, transfers to alternative pension arrangements,
refunds of contributions and compensation for early retirement to or in respect of persons
engaged in health and social care or other approved employment; creation and movement
in provisions; expenditure on activities that are required as a result of the United
Kingdom’s exit from the European Union; governmental response to the coronavirus
COVID-19 pandemic; UK Covid-19 Inquiry activities; related costs; other non-cash
items.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the inclusion of expenditure related to pension payments, allowances, gratuities, refunds of contributions, and other non-cash items for the Health and Social Care Pension Scheme.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Health and Public Health"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Department for Infrastructure Estimate</subject>

   <quote>Departmental expenditure limit
Expenditure arising from:
Design, construction and maintenance of roads, bridges, structures, walking and cycling
infrastructure, footpaths, street lighting and car parks; costs associated with the operation
of the Blue Badge Scheme; purchase of land, property, vehicles, ferries, plant, computer
software, equipment and stores; supporting research in the development of new innovative
digital solutions; public liability claims; compensation payments; costs associated with the
decriminalisation of parking enforcement; costs associated with the enforcement of
moving traffic offences; costs associated with residents’ parking improvement; restoration
or promotion of the recreational or navigational use of any waterway; maintenance of
designated watercourses and sea defences; reservoir operational issues including the
maintenance of reservoirs in which the department has an interest; construction and
maintenance of drainage and flood defence structures; protection of drainage function of
all watercourses; implementation of The Water Environment (Floods Directive)
Regulations (Northern Ireland) 2009; emergency response to flooding and Lead
Government Department responsibilities; experimental work under the Drainage
(Northern Ireland) Order 1973; enhancing community resilience to flooding; development
of reservoir safety legislation and support for Drainage Council for Northern Ireland;
Flood Risk Planning consultation advice; protection, restoration and bringing back into
active use the Grade A listed Crumlin Road Gaol and the management of the St Lucia site;
road safety services and promotion; driver licensing, driver and vehicle testing, transport
licensing, enforcement and regulation; rail safety services; train driver licensing, railway
operator licensing, issue of Commercial Bus Service Permits; costs incurred to facilitate
the licensing and regulation of Goods Vehicle Operators; operation and maintenance of
the Strangford Ferry; support for and grants in respect of the Rathlin Island ferry service
and works to Ballycastle and Rathlin Harbours; support for air and sea ports; support for
transport services including grants in respect of rail and road passenger services including
fare concessions, fuel duty rebate, transport for people with disabilities, rural transport,
shopmobility schemes, provision and maintenance of bus shelters, purchase of buses and
rolling stock and capital works; environmentally sustainable transport and related
infrastructure including Active School Travel Programme, grants for greenways and active
travel and grants for Blue-Green infrastructure; Ultra Low Emission Vehicle strategies;
energy matters; planning services, support for strategic planning including grants,
planning legislation and policy, governance and oversight of planning and plan making
within local councils; transport planning and visioning; payments under European Union
programmes; grants in respect of certain inland waterways; net cost of the management,
maintenance, development and restoration of operational waterways of Waterways
Ireland; the shareholder and water, flooding, drainage and reservoirs policy functions;
repayment of loans; consultants’ and other fees; expenditure on activities that are required
as a result of the United Kingdom’s exit from the European Union; governmental response
to the coronavirus COVID-19 pandemic; UK Covid-19 Inquiry activities; administration
costs; payments in relation to the holiday pay case; severance payments; related services
including services to other departments; other non-cash items.</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the inclusion of expenditure related to the design, construction, and maintenance of infrastructure, road safety services, transport services, planning services, and other non-cash items for the Department for Infrastructure.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Infrastructure"></pillar>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>development and delivery of a strategy to tackle violence against women and girls</subject>

   <quote>development and delivery of a strategy to tackle violence against women and girls</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the development and delivery of a strategy to tackle violence against women and girls.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Gender and Sexuality"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>implementation of the Period Products (Free Provision) Act (NI) 2022</subject>

   <quote>implementation of the Period Products (Free Provision) Act (NI) 2022</quote>

   <summary>The bill includes actions associated with the implementation of the Period Products (Free Provision) Act (NI) 2022.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Gender and Sexuality"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>re-establishment of the economic policy unit</subject>

   <quote>re-establishment of the economic policy unit</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the re-establishment of the economic policy unit.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>settlement of the NICS equal pay claims</subject>

   <quote>settlement of the NICS equal pay claims</quote>

   <summary>The bill includes the settlement of the NICS equal pay claims.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Gender and Sexuality"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>development of trauma informed practice across the Department and its ALBs severance payments</subject>

   <quote>development of trauma informed practice across the Department and its ALBs severance payments</quote>

   <summary>The bill proposes the development of trauma informed practice across the Department and its ALBs severance payments.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>liaison with other bodies, persons and authorities (both inside and outside Northern Ireland)</subject>

   <quote>liaison with other bodies, persons and authorities (both inside and outside Northern Ireland)</quote>

   <summary>The bill includes provisions for liaison with other bodies, persons, and authorities both inside and outside Northern Ireland.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>information services</subject>

   <quote>information services</quote>

   <summary>The bill includes provisions for information services.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>the legislative programme</subject>

   <quote>the legislative programme</quote>

   <summary>The bill includes provisions for the legislative programme.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>UK Covid-19 Inquiry activities</subject>

   <quote>UK Covid-19 Inquiry activities</quote>

   <summary>The bill includes provisions for UK Covid-19 Inquiry activities.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Public Health"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>development of actions and policy stemming from the Climate Change Act (Northern Ireland) 2022, to include the establishment of the NI Climate Commissioner’s Office</subject>

   <quote>development of actions and policy stemming from the Climate Change Act (Northern Ireland) 2022, to include the establishment of the NI Climate Commissioner’s Office</quote>

   <summary>The bill includes provisions for the development of actions and policy stemming from the Climate Change Act (Northern Ireland) 2022, including the establishment of the NI Climate Commissioner’s Office.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>2</clarity>

   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Environmental Impact"></pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change></all>