<all><change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 3A: Information relating to an identifiable living individual</subject>
   <quote>“(3A) An individual is identifiable from information “directly” if the individual can be identified without the use of additional information.
(3B) An individual is identifiable from information “indirectly” if the individual can be identified only with the use of additional information.”</quote>
   <summary>This section defines when information is considered to be relating to an identifiable living individual, distinguishing between direct and indirect identification.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      This change provides a clearer definition of when information is considered to be relating to an identifiable living individual, which can help protect individuals' right to privacy.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 3A: Information relating to an identifiable living individual</subject>
   <quote>“(5) For the purposes of this section, an individual is identifiable by a person “by reasonable means” if the individual is identifiable by the person by any means that the person is reasonably likely to use.
(6) For the purposes of subsection (5), whether a person is reasonably likely to use a means of identifying an individual is to be determined taking into account, among other things—
(a) the time, effort and costs involved in identifying the individual by that means, and
(b) the technology and other resources available to the person.”</quote>
   <summary>This section further clarifies the criteria for determining whether an individual is identifiable by a person "by reasonable means". It takes into account factors such as time, effort, costs, and available technology and resources.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      This change provides additional guidance on how to determine whether an individual is identifiable, which can help protect individuals' right to privacy.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 4: Consent to law enforcement processing</subject>
   <quote>“(1A) “Consent” of the data subject to the processing of personal data means a freely given, specific, informed and unambiguous indication of the data subject’s wishes by which the data subject, by a statement or by a clear affirmative action, signifies agreement to the processing of the personal data (and see section 40A).”</quote>
   <summary>This section provides a definition of "consent" in the context of law enforcement processing of personal data.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      This change clarifies the requirements for obtaining consent in the context of law enforcement processing, ensuring that individuals' rights are protected.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 5: Lawfulness of processing</subject>
   <quote>“(ea) processing is necessary for the purposes of a recognised legitimate interest;”</quote>
   <summary>This section adds a new lawful basis for processing personal data, stating that processing is lawful if it is necessary for the purposes of a recognised legitimate interest.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      This change provides a new lawful basis for processing personal data, allowing for the recognition of legitimate interests while still protecting individuals' rights.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 5: Lawfulness of processing</subject>
   <quote>“9. For the purposes of paragraph 1(f), examples of types of processing that may be processing that is necessary for the purposes of a legitimate interest include—
(a) processing that is necessary for the purposes of direct marketing,
(b) intra-group transmission of personal data (whether relating to clients, employees or other individuals) where that is necessary for internal administrative purposes, and
(c) processing that is necessary for the purposes of ensuring the security of network and information systems.”</quote>
   <summary>This section provides examples of types of processing that may be considered necessary for the purposes of a legitimate interest, including direct marketing, intra-group transmission of personal data for internal administrative purposes, and processing for the purposes of ensuring the security of network and information systems.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      This change provides examples of legitimate interests that may justify the processing of personal data, ensuring a balance between privacy rights and other legitimate purposes.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 6: The purpose limitation</subject>
   <quote>“3 For the avoidance of doubt, processing is not lawful by virtue only of being processing in a manner that is compatible with the purposes for which the personal data was collected.”</quote>
   <summary>This section clarifies that processing of personal data is not lawful solely because it is compatible with the purposes for which the data was collected.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      This change emphasizes that processing of personal data must have a lawful basis beyond mere compatibility with the original purposes of collection, ensuring that individuals' rights are protected.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 8A: Purpose limitation: further processing</subject>
   <quote>“3. Processing of personal data for a new purpose is to be treated as processing in a manner compatible with the original purpose where—
(a) the data subject consents to the processing of personal data for the new purpose and the new purpose is specified, explicit and legitimate,
(b) the processing is carried out in accordance with Article 84B—
(i) for the purposes of scientific research or historical research,
(ii) for the purposes of archiving in the public interest, or
(iii) for statistical purposes,
(c) the processing is carried out for the purposes of ensuring that processing of personal data complies with Article 5(1) or demonstrating that it does so,
(d) the processing meets a condition in Annex 2, or
(e) the processing is necessary to safeguard an objective listed in Article 23(1)(c) to (j) and is authorised by an enactment or rule of law.”</quote>
   <summary>This section provides criteria for determining when processing of personal data for a new purpose is considered compatible with the original purpose, including obtaining consent, complying with specific articles of the UK GDPR, meeting conditions in Annex 2, or being necessary to safeguard certain objectives authorized by law.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      This change provides clear criteria for determining when processing of personal data for a new purpose is compatible with the original purpose, ensuring that individuals' rights are protected.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 5</subject>
   <quote>5. The Secretary of State may by regulations amend Annex 2 by—</quote>
   <summary>This change grants the Secretary of State the power to amend Annex 2 through regulations.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change grants the Secretary of State the power to amend Annex 2, which could potentially affect the legal processes and procedures related to data protection and digital information.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 8</subject>
   <quote>(8) In section 36(1) (the second data protection principle)—</quote>
   <summary>This change amends section 36(1) of the 2018 Act, specifically paragraph (a) and (b), which relate to the second data protection principle.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change amends the second data protection principle, which could potentially affect how personal data is processed and protected.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 9</subject>
   <quote>(9) In section 87(1) (the second data protection principle)—</quote>
   <summary>This change amends section 87(1) of the 2018 Act, specifically paragraph (a) and (b), which relate to the second data protection principle.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change amends the second data protection principle, which could potentially affect how personal data is processed and protected.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 10</subject>
   <quote>(10) In paragraph 1 of Schedule 2 (exemptions etc from the UK GDPR: provisions 35 to be adapted or restricted), omit sub-paragraph (b)(ii).</quote>
   <summary>This change amends paragraph 1 of Schedule 2 of the 2018 Act by omitting sub-paragraph (b)(ii).</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change amends the exemptions and provisions from the UK GDPR, which could potentially affect the application and interpretation of the regulations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 7</subject>
   <quote>(7) The UK GDPR is amended in accordance with subsections (2) and (3).</quote>
   <summary>This change amends the UK GDPR in accordance with subsections (2) and (3) of Section 7.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change amends the UK GDPR, which could potentially affect the rights and obligations of data subjects.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 11</subject>
   <quote>(11) For Article 22 of the UK GDPR (automated individual decision-making, including profiling) substitute—</quote>
   <summary>This change substitutes Article 22 of the UK GDPR with a new provision related to automated individual decision-making.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change introduces a new provision related to automated individual decision-making, which could potentially affect how decisions are made based on automated processing.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 50B</subject>
   <quote>50B Restrictions on automated decision-making using sensitive personal data</quote>
   <summary>A new section 50B is inserted, which imposes restrictions on automated decision-making using sensitive personal data.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      The new section 50B introduces restrictions on automated decision-making using sensitive personal data, which aims to protect the rights and freedoms of individuals.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 50C</subject>
   <quote>50C Safeguards for automated decision-making</quote>
   <summary>A new section 50C is inserted, which requires controllers to ensure that safeguards are in place for the rights, freedoms, and legitimate interests of data subjects in relation to automated decision-making.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      The new section 50C introduces safeguards for automated decision-making, which aims to protect the rights and freedoms of individuals.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 50D</subject>
   <quote>50D Further provision about automated decision-making</quote>
   <summary>A new section 50D is inserted, which provides for further provisions about automated decision-making, including regulations on meaningful human involvement and adverse effects on data subjects.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      The new section 50D provides additional provisions to ensure meaningful human involvement in automated decision-making and to address adverse effects on data subjects.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 96</subject>
   <quote>For the purposes of this section and section 97, a decision is based on entirely automated processing if the decision-making process does not include an opportunity for a human being to accept, reject or influence the decision.</quote>
   <summary>A new provision is inserted in section 96, which defines a decision based on entirely automated processing as a decision-making process that does not include an opportunity for human involvement.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      The new provision in section 96 clarifies the definition of a decision based on entirely automated processing, which is relevant to the protection of human rights.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 97</subject>
   <quote>in subsection (1)(a), for “solely on” substitute “on entirely”,</quote>
   <summary>An amendment is made to section 97, which changes the wording from "solely on" to "on entirely" in relation to decisions based on entirely automated processing.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      The amendment in section 97 clarifies the wording in relation to decisions based on entirely automated processing, which is relevant to the protection of human rights.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 103</subject>
   <quote>for “appropriate technical and organisational measures” substitute “appropriate measures, including technical and organisational measures,”.</quote>
   <summary>An amendment is made to section 103, which changes the wording from "appropriate technical and organisational measures" to "appropriate measures, including technical and organisational measures."</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      The amendment in section 103 clarifies the wording in relation to appropriate measures for data protection, which is relevant to the protection of human rights.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 142</subject>
   <quote>in subsection (3), omit “technical and organisational”.</quote>
   <summary>An amendment is made to section 142, which removes the phrase "technical and organisational" in relation to safeguards for sensitive processing.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      The amendment in section 142 clarifies the wording in relation to safeguards for sensitive processing, which is relevant to the protection of human rights.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 206</subject>
   <quote>in paragraph 4 omit “and, where applicable, the controller’s or the processor’s representative,”.</quote>
   <summary>An amendment is made to section 206, which removes the phrase "and, where applicable, the controller's or the processor's representative" in relation to additional safeguards for processing of special categories of personal data.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      The amendment in section 206 clarifies the wording in relation to additional safeguards for processing of special categories of personal data, which is relevant to the protection of human rights.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 58A</subject>
   <quote>Senior responsible individual</quote>
   <summary>A new section 58A is inserted, which introduces the concept of a senior responsible individual for controllers and processors.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      The new section 58A introduces the concept of a senior responsible individual, which aims to ensure accountability and compliance with data protection legislation.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 58B</subject>
   <quote>Tasks of the senior responsible individual</quote>
   <summary>A new section 58B is inserted, which outlines the tasks of the senior responsible individual, including monitoring compliance, providing information and advice, and dealing with complaints and breaches.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      The new section 58B outlines the tasks of the senior responsible individual, which aims to ensure accountability and compliance with data protection legislation and protect the rights and freedoms of individuals.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 61A</subject>
   <quote>Records of processing of personal data</quote>
   <summary>A new section 61A is inserted, which requires controllers to maintain records of processing of personal data and includes information about the personal data, purposes of processing, and data sharing.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      The new section 61A introduces requirements for controllers to maintain records of processing of personal data, which aims to ensure transparency and accountability in data processing.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>subsection 5</subject>
   <quote>The processor’s records must include at least the following information about the personal data in respect of which it is for the time being a processor— (a) the name and contact details of each controller on behalf of which the processor is acting, and (b) where the personal data is (including information about any personal data that is outside the United Kingdom).</quote>
   <summary>A new requirement is added for processors to maintain records that include the name and contact details of each controller they are acting on behalf of, as well as information about the location of the personal data.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change enhances data protection by ensuring that processors maintain accurate records of the controllers they are acting on behalf of and the location of the personal data.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>subsection 6</subject>
   <quote>Where possible, the processor’s records must include information about how it ensures that personal data is secure.</quote>
   <summary>A new requirement is added for processors to include information about the security measures they have in place to protect personal data in their records.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change strengthens data protection by requiring processors to document the security measures they have implemented to protect personal data.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>subsection 7</subject>
   <quote>A controller or processor must make the records maintained under this section available to the Commissioner on request.</quote>
   <summary>Controllers and processors are required to provide the records they maintain to the Commissioner upon request.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change enhances data protection by ensuring that the Commissioner has access to the records maintained by controllers and processors, allowing for better oversight and enforcement of data protection regulations.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>subsection 8</subject>
   <quote>In deciding what is appropriate for the purposes of this section, a controller or processor must take into account, among other things— (a) the nature, scope, context and purposes of processing carried out by or on behalf of the controller or by the processor, (b) the risks for the rights and freedoms of individuals arising from that processing, including the likelihood of risks arising and their severity, and (c) the resources available to the controller or processor.</quote>
   <summary>Controllers and processors are required to consider various factors, including the nature of processing, the risks to individuals' rights and freedoms, and the available resources, when determining what is appropriate for compliance with the section.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change reinforces the importance of considering the nature of processing, risks to individuals, and available resources when determining appropriate measures for compliance with data protection regulations.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>subsection 62(2)(a)</subject>
   <quote>in subsection (2)(a), omit “justification for, and”</quote>
   <summary>The phrase "justification for, and" is removed from subsection 62(2)(a) of the 2018 Act.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change does not have a significant impact on data protection as it is a minor deletion of a phrase.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>subsection 62(3)(a)</subject>
   <quote>in subsection (3)(a), omit “justification for, and”</quote>
   <summary>The phrase "justification for, and" is removed from subsection 62(3)(a) of the 2018 Act.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change does not have a significant impact on data protection as it is a minor deletion of a phrase.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Article 35</subject>
   <quote>in paragraph 1, for “natural persons” substitute “individuals”, omit paragraphs 2 to 5, for paragraph 7 substitute— “7 The controller must produce a document recording compliance with this Article which includes at least— (a) a summary of the purposes of the processing, (b) an assessment of whether the processing is necessary for those purposes, (c) an assessment of the risks to individuals referred to in paragraph 1, and (d) a description of how the controller proposes to mitigate those risks.”, in paragraph 8, for “, in particular for the purposes of a data protection impact assessment” substitute “for the purposes of an assessment required by paragraph 1”</quote>
   <summary>Amendments are made to Article 35 of the UK GDPR, including the substitution of "natural persons" with "individuals" in paragraph 1, the omission of paragraphs 2 to 5, and the substitution of paragraph 7 with a new requirement for controllers to produce a document recording compliance with the article.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">These amendments clarify the requirements for compliance with Article 35 of the UK GDPR, including the need for controllers to assess the necessity of processing, the risks to individuals, and the proposed mitigation measures.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Article 57(1)</subject>
   <quote>for paragraph (k) substitute— “(k) produce and publish a document containing examples of types of processing which the Commissioner considers are likely to result in a high risk to the rights and freedoms of individuals (for the purposes of Articles 27A, 30A and 35);”.</quote>
   <summary>Amendment is made to Article 57(1) of the UK GDPR, replacing paragraph (k) with a new requirement for the Commissioner to produce and publish a document containing examples of types of processing that are likely to result in a high risk to individuals' rights and freedoms.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This amendment enhances data protection by providing guidance to controllers and processors on types of processing that may pose a high risk to individuals' rights and freedoms.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>before section 64</subject>
   <quote>“Risk assessment and prior consultation”.</quote>
   <summary>A new section titled "Risk assessment and prior consultation" is inserted before section 64 of the 2018 Act.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change introduces a new section that addresses risk assessment and prior consultation in relation to data protection.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>section 64</subject>
   <quote>for the heading substitute “Assessment of high risk processing”, in subsection (1), for “a data protection impact assessment” substitute “an assessment of the impact of the envisaged processing operations on the protection of personal data”, omit subsection (2), for subsection (3) substitute— “(3) The controller must produce a document recording compliance with this section which includes at least— (a) a summary of the purposes of the processing, (b) an assessment of whether the processing is necessary for those purposes, (c) an assessment of the risks to the rights and freedoms of individuals referred to in subsection (1), and (d) a description of how the controller proposes to mitigate those risks.”</quote>
   <summary>Amendments are made to section 64 of the 2018 Act, including the substitution of the heading with "Assessment of high risk processing" and the substitution of subsection (1) with a new requirement for controllers to produce a document recording compliance with the section.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">These amendments clarify the requirements for compliance with section 64 of the 2018 Act, including the need for controllers to assess the necessity of processing, the risks to individuals' rights and freedoms, and the proposed mitigation measures.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Article 36 of the UK GDPR</subject>
   <quote>in paragraph 1— (a) for “shall” substitute “may”, for “a data protection impact assessment” substitute “an assessment”, and after “high risk” insert “to the rights and freedoms of individuals”.</quote>
   <summary>Amendment is made to Article 36 of the UK GDPR, including the substitution of "shall" with "may" in paragraph 1 and the substitution of "a data protection impact assessment" with "an assessment".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This amendment provides flexibility for controllers in conducting assessments and removes the requirement for a data protection impact assessment in certain cases.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>section 65 of the 2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>in subsection (2)— (a) for “must” substitute “may”, for “if a data protection impact assessment prepared” substitute “where an assessment”, and for “(in the absence of measures to mitigate the risk)” substitute “in the absence of measures taken by the controller to mitigate the risk”.</quote>
   <summary>Amendment is made to section 65 of the 2018 Act, including the substitution of "must" with "may" in subsection (2) and the substitution of "if a data protection impact assessment prepared" with "where an assessment".</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This amendment provides flexibility for controllers in determining whether to conduct a data protection impact assessment and clarifies the requirement for measures to mitigate risks.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>after section 68</subject>
   <quote>“Codes of conduct 68A Codes of conduct (1) The Commissioner must encourage expert public bodies to produce codes of conduct intended to contribute to compliance with this Part. (2) Under subsection (1), the Commissioner must, among other things, encourage the production of codes which take account of the specific features of the various processing sectors. (3) For the purposes of this section— (a) “public body” means a body or other person whose functions are, or include, functions of a public nature, and (b) a public body is “expert” if, in the Commissioner’s opinion, the body has the knowledge and experience needed to produce a code of conduct described in subsection (1). (4) A code of conduct described in subsection (1) may, for example, make provision with regard to— (a) lawful and fair processing; (b) the collection of personal data; (c) the information provided to the public and to data subjects; (d) the exercise of the rights of data subjects; (e) the measures and procedures referred to in sections 56, 57 and 62; (f) the notification of personal data breaches to the Commissioner and the communication of personal data breaches to data subjects; (g) the transfer of personal data to third countries or international organisations; (h) out-of-court proceedings and other dispute resolution procedures for resolving disputes between controllers and data subjects with regard to processing. (5) Where an expert public body prepares a code of conduct described in subsection (1), it must submit the code to the Commissioner in draft. (6) Where an expert public body submits a draft code to the Commissioner under this section, the Commissioner must— (a) provide the body with an opinion on whether the draft code correctly reflects the requirements of this Part, (b) decide whether to approve the code, and (c) if the code is approved, register and publish the code. (7) Subsections (5) and (6) apply in relation to amendments of a code of conduct described in subsection (1) as they apply in relation to such a code.”</quote>
   <summary>A new section titled "Codes of conduct" is inserted after section 68 of the 2018 Act, outlining the Commissioner's role in encouraging the production of codes of conduct by expert public bodies and the process for approval and registration of such codes.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change promotes compliance with data protection regulations by encouraging the development of codes of conduct that address various aspects of processing and provide guidance for controllers and processors.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 5</subject>
   <quote>Schedule 5 amends Chapter 5 of the UK GDPR (general processing and transfers of personal data to third countries and international organisations).</quote>
   <summary>Schedule 5 of the bill amends Chapter 5 of the UK GDPR, which pertains to general processing and transfers of personal data to third countries and international organisations.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This amendment modifies the regulations related to general processing and transfers of personal data to ensure compliance with data protection requirements.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 6</subject>
   <quote>Schedule 6 amends Chapter 5 of Part 3 of the 2018 Act (law enforcement processing and transfers of personal data to third countries and international organisations).</quote>
   <summary>Schedule 6 of the bill amends Chapter 5 of Part 3 of the 2018 Act, which pertains to law enforcement processing and transfers of personal data to third countries and international organisations.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This amendment modifies the regulations related to law enforcement processing and transfers of personal data to ensure compliance with data protection requirements.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 7</subject>
   <quote>Schedule 7 contains consequential and transitional provision.</quote>
   <summary>Schedule 7 of the bill contains consequential and transitional provisions related to the amendments made in the bill.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This provision ensures that the amendments made in the bill have appropriate consequential and transitional provisions.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>subsection 84A</subject>
   <quote>CHAPTER 8A Safeguards for processing for research, archiving or statistical purposes Article 84A Research, archives and statistics 1. This Chapter makes provision about the processing of personal data— (a) for the purposes of scientific research or historical research, (b) for the purposes of archiving in the public interest, or (c) for statistical purposes. 2. Those purposes are referred to in this Chapter as “RAS purposes”.</quote>
   <summary>A new chapter titled "Safeguards for processing for research, archiving or statistical purposes" is inserted, which provides provisions for the processing of personal data for scientific research, historical research, archiving, and statistical purposes.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change introduces specific safeguards for the processing of personal data for research, archiving, and statistical purposes, ensuring compliance with data protection regulations.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>subsection 84B</subject>
   <quote>Additional requirements when processing for RAS purposes 1. Processing of personal data for RAS purposes must be carried out subject to appropriate safeguards for the rights and freedoms of the data subject. 2. Processing of personal data for RAS purposes must be carried out in a manner which does not permit the identification of a living individual. 3. Paragraph 2 does not apply— (a) to the collection of personal data (whether from the data subject or otherwise), or (b) to cases in which the RAS purposes cannot be fulfilled by further processing in the manner described in that paragraph. 4. For the purposes of paragraph 2, processing permits the identification of a living individual only in cases described in section 3A(2) and (3) of the 2018 Act (information relating to an identifiable living individual).</quote>
   <summary>A new section titled "Additional requirements when processing for RAS purposes" is inserted, which outlines the requirements for processing personal data for research, archiving, and statistical purposes, including the need for appropriate safeguards and the prohibition of identification of living individuals.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change establishes specific requirements for the processing of personal data for research, archiving, and statistical purposes, ensuring the protection of individuals' rights and freedoms.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>subsection 84C</subject>
   <quote>Appropriate safeguards 1. This Article makes provision about when the requirement under Article 84B(1) for processing of personal data to be carried out subject to appropriate safeguards is satisfied. 2. The requirement is not satisfied if the processing is likely to cause substantial damage or substantial distress to a data subject to whom the personal data relates. 3. The requirement is not satisfied if the processing is carried out for the purposes of measures or decisions with respect to a particular data subject to whom the personal data relates, except where the purposes for which the processing is carried out include the purposes of approved medical research. 4. The requirement is only satisfied if the safeguards include technical and organisational measures for the purpose of ensuring respect for the principle of data minimisation (see Article 5(1)(c)), such as, for example, pseudonymisation. 5. In this Article— “approved medical research” means medical research carried out by a person who has approval to carry out that research from— (a) a research ethics committee recognised or established by the Health Research Authority under Chapter 2 of Part 3 of the Care Act 2014, or (b) a body appointed by any of the following for the purpose of assessing the ethics of research involving individuals— (i) the Secretary of State, the Scottish Ministers, the Welsh Ministers or a Northern Ireland department; (ii) a relevant NHS body; (iii) United Kingdom Research and Innovation or a body that is a Research Council for the purposes of the Science and Technology Act 1965; (iv) an institution that is a research institution for the purposes of Chapter 4A of Part 7 of the Income Tax (Earnings and Pensions) Act 2003 (see section 457 of that Act); “relevant NHS body” means— (a) an NHS trust or NHS foundation trust in England, (b) an NHS trust or Local Health Board in Wales, (c) a Health Board or Special Health Board constituted under section 2 of the National Health Service (Scotland) Act 1978, (d) the Common Services Agency for the Scottish Health Service, or (e) any of the health and social care bodies in Northern Ireland falling within paragraphs (b) to (e) of section 1(5) of the Health and Social Care (Reform) Act (Northern Ireland) 2009 (c. 1 (N.I.)).</quote>
   <summary>A new section titled "Appropriate safeguards" is inserted, which provides provisions for determining when the requirement for processing personal data to be carried out subject to appropriate safeguards is satisfied, including the conditions for approved medical research and the inclusion of technical and organisational measures for data minimisation.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change establishes specific requirements for the implementation of appropriate safeguards when processing personal data for research, archiving, and statistical purposes, ensuring the protection of individuals' rights and freedoms.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>subsection 78A</subject>
   <quote>National security exemption (1) A provision mentioned in subsection (2) does not apply to personal data processed for law enforcement purposes if exemption from the provision is required for the purposes of safeguarding national security. (2) The provisions are— (a) Chapter 2 of this Part (principles), except for the provisions listed in subsection (3); (b) Chapter 3 of this Part (rights of the data subject); (c) in Chapter 4 of this Part— (i) section 67 (notification of personal data breach to the Commissioner); (ii) section 68 (communication of personal data breach to the data subject); (d) Chapter 5 of this Part (transfers of personal data to third countries etc), except for the provisions listed in subsection (4); (e) in Part 5— (i) section 119 (inspection in accordance with international obligations); (ii) in Schedule 13 (other general functions of the Commissioner), paragraphs 1(1)(a) and (g) and 2; (f) in Part 6— (i) sections 142 to 154 and Schedule 15 (Commissioner’s notices and powers of entry and inspection); (ii) sections 170 to 173 (offences relating to personal data); (g) in Part 7, section 187 (representation of data subjects).</quote>
   <summary>A new section titled "National security exemption" is inserted, which provides exemptions for certain provisions of the 2018 Act for personal data processed for law enforcement purposes if exemption is required for the purposes of safeguarding national security.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This change introduces exemptions for certain provisions of the 2018 Act for personal data processed for law enforcement purposes in order to safeguard national security.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>subsection 78A</subject>
   <quote>A certificate signed by a Minister of the Crown certifying that exemption from all or any of the provisions listed in section 78A(2) is, or at any time was, required in relation to any personal data for the purposes of safeguarding national security is conclusive evidence of that fact.</quote>
   <summary>A provision is added to section 79 of the 2018 Act, stating that a certificate signed by a Minister of the Crown certifying the requirement for exemption from certain provisions for the purposes of safeguarding national security is conclusive evidence of that fact.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Data Protection">This provision provides a mechanism for certifying the requirement for exemption from certain provisions for the purposes of safeguarding national security, ensuring clarity and legal certainty.</pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>section 40 of the Freedom of Information Act 2000</subject>
   <quote>in subsection (4A)(b), for “subsection (4) of that section” substitute “section 45(4) or 78A of that Act”, and</quote>
   <quote>in subsection (5B)(d), for “subsection (4) of that section” substitute “section 45(4) or 78A of that Act”.</quote>
   <summary>Section 40 of the Freedom of Information Act 2000 is being amended to replace "subsection (4) of that section" with "section 45(4) or 78A of that Act" in subsections (4A)(b) and (5B)(d).</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment clarifies the specific sections of the Act that are being referred to, ensuring accuracy and precision in the legislation.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 4 of the 2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>Part 4 of the 2018 Act (intelligence services processing) is amended as follows.</quote>
   <summary>A new part, Part 4, is being added to the 2018 Act to address intelligence services processing.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security">
      The addition of Part 4 specifically addresses intelligence services processing, indicating a focus on national security concerns.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>section 82 of the 2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>in section 82 (processing to which Part 4 applies)—</quote>
   <summary>A new section, section 82, is being added to the 2018 Act to address processing to which Part 4 applies.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security">
      The addition of section 82 specifically addresses processing related to intelligence services, indicating a focus on national security concerns.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>section 82A of the 2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>After section 82 insert—
“82A Designation of processing by a qualifying competent authority
(1) For the purposes of this Part, the Secretary of State may give a notice 15
designating processing of personal data by a qualifying competent
authority (a “designation notice”) where—
(a) an application for designation of the processing is made in
accordance with this section, and
(b) the Secretary of State considers that designation of the 20
processing is required for the purposes of safeguarding national
security.</quote>
   <summary>A new section, section 82A, is being added to the 2018 Act to address the designation of processing by a qualifying competent authority for the purposes of safeguarding national security.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security">
      The addition of section 82A specifically addresses the designation of processing by a qualifying competent authority for the purposes of safeguarding national security.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>section 120A of the 2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>After section 120 insert—
“Duties in carrying out functions
120A Principal objective
25
It is the principal objective of the Commissioner, in carrying out functions under the data protection legislation—
(a) to secure an appropriate level of protection for personal data,
having regard to the interests of data subjects, controllers and
others and matters of general public interest, and
(b)
30
to promote public trust and confidence in the processing of
personal data.</quote>
   <summary>A new section, section 120A, is being added to the 2018 Act to outline the principal objective of the Commissioner in carrying out functions under the data protection legislation.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      The addition of section 120A emphasizes the importance of securing an appropriate level of protection for personal data and promoting public trust and confidence in data processing, which aligns with the pillar of human rights.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>section 120C of the 2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>After section 120A insert—
“120C Strategy 10
(1) The Commissioner must prepare a strategy for carrying out the
Commissioner’s functions under the data protection legislation in
accordance with the Commissioner’s duties under—
(a) sections 120A and 120B,
(b) section 108 of the Deregulation Act 2015 (exercise of regulatory 15
functions: economic growth), and
(c) section 21 of the Legislative and Regulatory Reform Act 2006
(exercise of regulatory functions: principles).
(2) The Commissioner must—
(a) review the strategy from time to time, and 20
(b) revise the strategy as appropriate.
(3) The Commissioner must publish the strategy and any revised strategy.</quote>
   <summary>A new section, section 120C, is being added to the 2018 Act to require the Commissioner to prepare a strategy for carrying out their functions under the data protection legislation, review and revise the strategy as appropriate, and publish the strategy and any revised strategy.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The addition of section 120C outlines the requirement for the Commissioner to prepare a strategy for carrying out their functions, which promotes transparency and accountability in the justice system.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>section 120E of the 2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>After section 120D (inserted by section 27 of this Act) insert—
“Strategic priorities
120E Designation of statement of strategic priorities
(1)
20
The Secretary of State may designate a statement as the statement of
strategic priorities for the purposes of this Part if the requirements set
out in section 120H are satisfied.
(2) The statement of strategic priorities is a statement prepared by the
Secretary of State that sets out the strategic priorities of His Majesty’s
government relating to data protection.</quote>
   <summary>A new section, section 120E, is being added to the 2018 Act to allow the Secretary of State to designate a statement as the statement of strategic priorities for the purposes of the Act, which sets out the strategic priorities of the government relating to data protection.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The addition of section 120E highlights the government's strategic priorities relating to data protection, which can impact the justice system.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>section 124A of the 2018 Act</subject>
   <quote>After section 124 insert—
“124A Other codes of practice
(1) The Commissioner must prepare appropriate codes of practice giving
35
guidance as to good practice in the processing of personal data if
required to do so by regulations made by the Secretary of State.</quote>
   <summary>A new section, section 124A, is being added to the 2018 Act to require the Commissioner to prepare codes of practice giving guidance on good practice in the processing of personal data if required to do so by regulations made by the Secretary of State.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      The addition of section 124A emphasizes the importance of good practice in the processing of personal data, which aligns with the pillar of human rights.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>subsection 43(13)</subject>
   <quote>for “128” substitute “124A”</quote>
   <summary>The amendment changes the reference from "128" to "124A" in subsection 43(13) of the Digital Economy Act 2017.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment clarifies the reference in the subsection, ensuring accuracy and precision in the legislation.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>subsection 52(13)</subject>
   <quote>for “128” substitute “124A”</quote>
   <summary>The amendment changes the reference from "128" to "124A" in subsection 52(13) of the Digital Economy Act 2017.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment clarifies the reference in the subsection, ensuring accuracy and precision in the legislation.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>subsection 60(13)</subject>
   <quote>for “128” substitute “124A”</quote>
   <summary>The amendment changes the reference from "128" to "124A" in subsection 60(13) of the Digital Economy Act 2017.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment clarifies the reference in the subsection, ensuring accuracy and precision in the legislation.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>subsection 70(15)</subject>
   <quote>for “128” substitute “124A”</quote>
   <summary>The amendment changes the reference from "128" to "124A" in subsection 70(15) of the Digital Economy Act 2017.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment clarifies the reference in the subsection, ensuring accuracy and precision in the legislation.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>section 124B</subject>
   <quote>After section 124A (inserted by section 29 of this Act) insert—
“124B Panels to consider codes of practice
(1) This section applies where a code is prepared under section 121, 122, 20
123, 124 or 124A, subject to subsection (11).
(2) The Commissioner must establish a panel of individuals to consider
the code.
(3) The panel must consist of—
(a) individuals the Commissioner considers have expertise in the 25
subject matter of the code, and
(b) individuals the Commissioner considers—
(i) are likely to be affected by the code, or
(ii) represent persons likely to be affected by the code.
(4) Before the panel begins to consider the code, the Commissioner must— 30
(a) publish the code in draft, and
(b) publish a statement that—
(i) states that a panel has been establish to consider the
code,
(ii) identifies the members of the panel, 35
(iii) explains the process by which they were selected, and
(iv) explains the reasons for their selection.
(5) Where at any time it appears to the Commissioner that a member of
the panel is not willing or able to serve as a member of the panel, the
54 Data Protection and Digital Information (No. 2) Bill
Part 1—Data protection 
Commissioner may select another individual to be a member of the
panel.
(6) Where the Commissioner selects an individual to be a member of the
5
panel under subsection (5), the Commissioner must publish a statement
that—
(a) identifies the member of the panel,
(b) explains the process by which the member was selected, and
(c) explains the reasons for the member’s selection.
(7) The Commissioner must make arrangements—
(a) for the members of the panel to consider the code with one 10
another (whether in person or otherwise), and
(b) for the panel to prepare and submit to the Commissioner a
report on the code within such reasonable period as is
determined by the Commissioner.
(8) If the panel submits to the Commissioner a report on the code within 15
the period determined by the Commissioner, the Commissioner must
as soon as reasonably practicable—
(a) make any alterations to the code that the Commissioner
considers appropriate in the light of the report, and
(b) publish— 20
(i) the code in draft,
(ii) the report or a summary of it, and
(iii) in a case where a recommendation in the report to alter
25
the code has not been accepted by the Commissioner,
an explanation of why it has not been accepted.
(9) The Commissioner may pay remuneration and expenses to the
members of the panel.
(10) This section applies in relation to amendments prepared under section
30
121, 122, 123, 124 or 124A as it applies in relation to codes prepared
under those sections, subject to subsection (11).
(11) The Secretary of State may by regulations provide that this section
does not apply, or applies with modifications, in the case of a code
or amendments of a code that—
(a) is prepared under section 124A, and
(b) is specified in the regulations. 35
(12) Regulations under this section are subject to the negative resolution
procedure."</quote>
   <summary>The insertion of section 124B establishes a panel of individuals to consider codes of practice prepared under sections 121, 122, 123, 124, or 124A. The panel consists of individuals with expertise in the subject matter of the code and individuals likely to be affected by the code. The Commissioner must publish the code in draft and a statement explaining the panel's establishment, members, selection process, and reasons for their selection. The panel will prepare and submit a report on the code, and the Commissioner will make any appropriate alterations based on the report. The Commissioner may pay remuneration and expenses to the panel members. The section also allows for regulations to specify codes or amendments that are exempt from this section.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The establishment of a panel ensures a more comprehensive and expert consideration of codes of practice, enhancing the effectiveness and fairness of the legislation.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>section 124C</subject>
   <quote>After section 124B (inserted by section 30 of this Act) insert—
“124C Impact assessments for codes of practice
(1)
40
Where a code is prepared under section 121, 122, 123, 124 or 124A,
the Commissioner must carry out and publish an assessment of—
(a) who would be likely to be affected by the code, and
(b) the effect the code would be likely to have on them.
(2) This section applies in relation to amendments prepared under section
121, 122, 123, 124 or 124A as it applies in relation to codes prepared
under those sections.”</quote>
   <summary>The insertion of section 124C requires the Commissioner to carry out and publish an assessment of who would be affected by a code of practice prepared under sections 121, 122, 123, 124, or 124A, and the likely effect of the code on them. This section also applies to amendments prepared under these sections.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The assessment requirement ensures a thorough understanding of the potential impact of codes of practice, promoting fairness and accountability in the legislation.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>section 124D</subject>
   <quote>After section 124C (inserted by section 30 of this Act) insert—
“124D Approval by Secretary of State of codes of practice
(1)
10
Where a code is prepared under section 121, 122, 123, 124 or 124A,
the Commissioner must submit the final version to the Secretary of
State.
(2) Within the period of 40 days beginning with the day on which the
code is submitted to the Secretary of State, the Secretary of State must
decide whether to approve the code.
(3) If the Secretary of State approves the code, the Secretary of State must 15
lay the code before Parliament.
(4) If the Secretary of State does not approve the code, the Secretary of
State must—
(a) give a statement to the Commissioner that—
(i) states that the Secretary of State does not approve the 20
code, and
(ii) explains the reasons why the Secretary of State does
not approve the code, and
(b) publish the statement.
(5) If the Secretary of State does not approve the code, the Commissioner 25
must—
(a) revise the code in the light of the statement given by the
Secretary of State, and
(b) submit the revised code to the Secretary of State.
(6) If the Commissioner submits a revised code to the Secretary of State, 30
subsections (2) to (5) and this subsection apply again.
(7) This section applies in relation to amendments prepared under section
121, 122, 123, 124 or 124A as it applies in relation to codes prepared
under those sections.
(8) In calculating the period of 40 days mentioned in subsection (2), no 35
account is to be taken of—
(a) Saturdays or Sundays,
(b) Christmas Day or Good Friday, or
(c) a day which is a bank holiday under the Banking and Financial
Dealings Act 1971 in any part of the United Kingdom.”</quote>
   <summary>The insertion of section 124D requires the Commissioner to submit the final version of a code of practice prepared under sections 121, 122, 123, 124, or 124A to the Secretary of State for approval. The Secretary of State must decide whether to approve the code within 40 days and, if approved, lay the code before Parliament. If the Secretary of State does not approve the code, they must provide a statement explaining the reasons for the decision. The Commissioner must revise the code based on the statement and resubmit it to the Secretary of State. This section also applies to amendments prepared under these sections.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The approval process ensures that codes of practice undergo scrutiny and evaluation by the Secretary of State, promoting transparency and accountability in the legislation.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>section 148A</subject>
   <quote>After section 148 insert—
“Interview notices
148A Interview notices 15
(1) This section applies where the Commissioner suspects that a controller
or processor—
(a) has failed or is failing as described in section 149(2), or
(b) has committed or is committing an offence under this Act.
(2) For the purpose of investigating the suspected failure or offence, the 20
Commissioner may, by written notice (an “interview notice”), require
an individual within subsection (3) to—
(a) attend at a place specified in the notice, and
(b)
25
answer questions with respect to any matter relevant to the
investigation.
(3) An individual is within this subsection if the individual—
(a) is the controller or processor,
(b) is or was at any time employed by, or otherwise working for,
the controller or processor, or
(c) is or was at any time concerned in the management or control 30
of the controller or processor.
(4) An interview notice must specify the time at which the individual
must attend at the specified place and answer questions (but see the
restrictions in subsections (6) and (7)).
(5) An interview notice must— 35
(a) indicate the nature of the suspected failure or offence that is
the subject of the investigation,
(b) provide information about the consequences of failure to
comply with the notice, and
(c) provide information about the rights under sections 162 and
164 (appeals etc).</quote>
   <summary>The insertion of section 148A allows the Commissioner to issue interview notices to individuals suspected of failing or committing an offense under the Act. The notice requires the individual, who may be the controller, processor, or someone employed or involved in the management or control of the controller or processor, to attend a specified place and answer questions relevant to the investigation. The notice must indicate the nature of the suspected failure or offense, provide information about the consequences of non-compliance, and inform the individual of their rights to appeal.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The provision of interview notices enhances the Commissioner's investigative powers, allowing for more effective enforcement of the Act and ensuring accountability.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 181</subject>
   <quote>““interview notice” has the meaning given in section 148A;”.</quote>
   <summary>A new definition for "interview notice" is inserted into Section 181.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change introduces a new definition for "interview notice" which may have implications for legal processes and procedures.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 196</subject>
   <quote>in subsection (2), after “148,” insert “148C,”.</quote>
   <summary>An amendment is made to Section 196, adding "148C" after "148" in subsection (2).</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment adds a new provision to Section 196, potentially affecting penalties for offenses.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 206</subject>
   <quote>“interview notice (in Part 6) section 181”.</quote>
   <summary>A new definition for "interview notice" is inserted into Section 206.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change introduces a new definition for "interview notice" which may have implications for legal processes and procedures.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 17</subject>
   <quote>after paragraph 3 insert—
“Interview notices 5
3A (1) Sub-paragraph (2) applies where the Commissioner gives an
interview notice to an individual during a relevant period.
(2) If the interview notice—
(a)
10
states that, in the Commissioner’s opinion, it is
necessary for the individual to comply with a
requirement in the notice for the purposes of the
relevant review, and
(b) gives the Commissioner’s reasons for reaching that
opinion,
subsections (6) and (7) of section 148A do not apply but the 15
notice must not require the individual to comply with the
requirement before the end of the period of 24 hours
beginning when the notice is given.
(3)
20
During a relevant period, section 148B has effect as if for
subsection (8) there were substituted—
“(8) The Commissioner may not give an individual an
interview notice with respect to the processing of
personal data for the special purposes unless a
25
determination under section 174 with respect to the
data or the processing has taken effect.””</quote>
   <summary>New provisions are added to Schedule 17 regarding interview notices.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The changes introduce new provisions regarding interview notices, potentially affecting the rights and obligations of individuals during relevant reviews.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Schedule 17</subject>
   <quote>in paragraph 4 (applications in respect of urgent notices)—
(i) for “or assessment notice” substitute “, assessment notice or
interview notice”,
(ii) for “or 3(2)(a)” substitute “, 3(2)(a) or 3A(2)(a)”, and
(iii) for “or 146(8)(a)” substitute “, 146(8)(a) or 148A(8)(a)”.</quote>
   <summary>An amendment is made to paragraph 4 of Schedule 17, adding "interview notice" to the list of applications in respect of urgent notices.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment expands the scope of applications in respect of urgent notices to include "interview notice".
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 37</subject>
   <quote>(2) In paragraph 2 of Schedule 16 (notice of intent to impose penalty), omit
sub-paragraphs (2) and (3).</quote>
   <summary>Sub-paragraphs (2) and (3) are omitted from paragraph 2 of Schedule 16.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment removes sub-paragraphs (2) and (3) from Schedule 16, potentially affecting the process of imposing penalties.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 38</subject>
   <quote>(A1) This paragraph applies where the Commissioner gives a notice
of intent to a person.
(B1) Within the period of 6 months beginning with the day the
notice is given, or as soon as reasonably practicable thereafter,
the Commission must give to the person—
(a) a penalty notice, or
(b) written notice that the Commissioner has decided not 5
to give a penalty notice to the person.”,</quote>
   <summary>New provisions are added to Section 38 regarding penalty notices.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The changes introduce new provisions regarding penalty notices, potentially affecting the process of imposing penalties.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 160</subject>
   <quote>in subsection (7), after
paragraph (d) insert—
“(e) provision about the circumstances in which the Commissioner
15
would consider it necessary to comply with the duty in
paragraph 4(B1) of Schedule 16 after the period of 6 months
mentioned in that paragraph.”</quote>
   <summary>An amendment is made to Section 160, adding provision about the circumstances in which the Commissioner would consider it necessary to comply with the duty in paragraph 4(B1) of Schedule 16 after the period of 6 months mentioned in that paragraph.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment adds provision regarding the duty of the Commissioner in relation to paragraph 4(B1) of Schedule 16, potentially affecting the enforcement of penalties.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 139</subject>
   <quote>“(2A) The report under this section may include the annual report under 20
section 161A.”</quote>
   <summary>A new provision is added to Section 139, allowing the report under this section to include the annual report under section 161A.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change allows for the inclusion of the annual report under section 161A in the report under section 139, potentially affecting reporting requirements.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 161</subject>
   <quote>“161A Annual report on regulatory action
(1) The Commissioner must produce and publish an annual report 25
containing the information described in subsections (2) to (5).
(2) The report must include the following information about UK GDPR
investigations—
(a)
30
the number of investigations begun, continued or completed
by the Commissioner during the reporting period,
(b) the different types of act and omission that were the subject
matter of the investigations,
(c) the enforcement powers exercised by the Commissioner in the
reporting period in connection with the investigations,
(d) the duration of investigations that ended in the reporting 35
period, and
(e) the different types of outcome in investigations that ended in
that period.</quote>
   <summary>A new provision is added to Section 161, requiring the Commissioner to produce and publish an annual report containing information about UK GDPR investigations.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change introduces a new requirement for the Commissioner to produce an annual report on UK GDPR investigations, potentially affecting reporting and transparency.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 164A</subject>
   <quote>“(1) A data subject may make a complaint to the controller if the data 35
subject considers that, in connection with personal data relating to the
data subject, there is an infringement of the UK GDPR or Part 3 of
this Act.
(2)
40
A controller must facilitate the making of complaints under this section
by taking steps such as providing a complaint form which can be
completed electronically and by other means.</quote>
   <summary>New provisions are added to Section 164A, allowing data subjects to make complaints to controllers and requiring controllers to facilitate the making of complaints.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The changes introduce new provisions regarding complaints by data subjects, potentially affecting the process of making and handling complaints.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 164B</subject>
   <quote>“(1)
15
The Secretary of State may by regulations require a controller to notify
the Commissioner of the number of complaints made to the controller
under section 164A in periods specified or described in the regulations.
(2) Regulations under this section may provide that a controller is required
to make a notification to the Commissioner in respect of a period only
in circumstances specified in the regulations.
(3) Regulations under this section may include— 20
(a) provision about a matter listed in subsection (4), or
(b) provision conferring power on the Commissioner to determine
those matters.
(4) The matters are—
(a) the form and manner in which a notification must be made, 25
(b) the time at which, or period within which, a notification must
be made, and
(c) how the number of complaints made to a controller during a
period is to be calculated.
(5) Regulations under this section are subject to the negative resolution 30
procedure.”</quote>
   <summary>New provisions are added to Section 164B, allowing the Secretary of State to require controllers to notify the Commissioner of the number of complaints made to the controller under section 164A.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The changes introduce new provisions regarding the notification of complaints made to controllers, potentially affecting reporting requirements.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 165</subject>
   <quote>“(5A) Subsection (4) does not apply if the Commissioner refuses to
act on the complaint in reliance on section 165A.”</quote>
   <summary>An amendment is made to Section 165, adding a provision that subsection (4) does not apply if the Commissioner refuses to act on the complaint in reliance on section 165A.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment adds a provision regarding the refusal of the Commissioner to act on a complaint, potentially affecting the handling of complaints.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 165A</subject>
   <quote>“(1) The Commissioner may refuse to act on a complaint under section
165 if condition A, B or C is met.
(2) Condition A is that—
(a)
10
the complaint concerns an infringement of the UK GDPR or
Part 3 of this Act, and
(b) the complaint has not been made to the controller under section
164A.
(3) Condition B is that—
(a)
15
the complaint has been made to the controller under section
164A,
(b) the controller has not finished handling the complaint in
accordance with subsection (4) of that section, and
(c) the period of 45 days beginning with the day the complaint
was made to the controller under that section has not expired.
(4) Condition C is that the complaint is vexatious or excessive (see section 20
204A).
(5) In any proceedings where there is an issue as to whether a complaint
is vexatious or excessive, it is for the Commissioner to show that it is.
(6)
25
If the Commissioner refuses to act on a complaint under section 165,
the Commissioner must inform the complainant of—
(a) the refusal and the reasons for it, and
(b) the right under section 166A.
(7) If the Commissioner refuses to act on a complaint under section 165
that does not prevent the complainant making the complaint again.</quote>
   <summary>New provisions are added to Section 165A, allowing the Commissioner to refuse to act on a complaint under section 165 under certain conditions and requiring the Commissioner to inform the complainant of the refusal and the right to appeal.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The changes introduce new provisions regarding the refusal of the Commissioner to act on a complaint, potentially affecting the handling of complaints and the rights of complainants.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 166A</subject>
   <quote>“(1) Where the Commissioner refuses to act on a complaint in reliance on
section 165A, the person who made the complaint may appeal to the
Tribunal.
(2) The Tribunal may review any determination of fact on which the
refusal to act was based.
(3) If the Tribunal considers—
(a) that the refusal to act is not in accordance with the law, or
(b) that the Commissioner ought not to have exercised the 20
discretion to refuse to act,
the Tribunal must allow the appeal.
(4) Otherwise, the Tribunal must dismiss the appeal.”</quote>
   <summary>New provisions are added to Section 166A, allowing a person who made a complaint to appeal to the Tribunal and specifying the powers of the Tribunal in reviewing the refusal to act on the complaint.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The changes introduce new provisions regarding the appeal of a refusal to act on a complaint, potentially affecting the rights of complainants and the review process.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 165B</subject>
   <quote>“(1) The Commissioner must produce and publish guidance about—
(a) how the Commissioner proposes to respond to complaints
made under section 165, and
(b)
35
how the Commissioner proposes to exercise the discretion
conferred by section 165A to refuse to act on a complaint.
(2) The Commissioner—
(a) may alter or replace guidance produced under this section,
and
(b) must publish any altered or replacement guidance.</quote>
   <summary>New provisions are added to Section 165B, requiring the Commissioner to produce and publish guidance on how to respond to complaints made under section 165 and how to exercise the discretion to refuse to act on a complaint.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The changes introduce new provisions regarding the production and publication of guidance on responding to complaints, potentially affecting the handling of complaints.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 183A</subject>
   <quote>“(1) A relevant enactment or rule of law which imposes a duty, or confers a power, to process personal data does not override a requirement under the main data protection legislation relating to the processing of personal data.
(2) Subsection (1) does not apply—
(a) to a relevant enactment forming part of the main data 30
protection legislation, or
(b) to the extent that an enactment makes express provision to the contrary referring to this section or to the main data protection legislation (or a provision of that legislation).
(3) Subsection (1) does not prevent a duty or power to process personal 35
data from being taken into account for the purpose of determining whether it is possible to rely on an exception to a requirement under the main data protection legislation that is available where there is such a duty or power.
(4) In this section—
“the main data protection legislation” means the data protection legislation other than provision of or made under—
(a) Chapter 6 or 8 of the UK GDPR, or
(b) Parts 5 to 7 of this Act; 5
“relevant enactment” means an enactment so far as passed or made on or after the day on which section 43 of the Data Protection and Digital Information Act 2023 comes into force;
“requirement” includes a prohibition or restriction.
(5) The reference in subsection (1) to an enactment or rule of law which 10
imposes a duty, or confers a power, to process personal data is a reference to an enactment or rule of law which, directly or indirectly, requires or authorises the processing of personal data, including (for example)—
(a) by authorising one person to require another person to process 15
personal data, or
(b) by removing restrictions on processing personal data,
and the references in subsection (3) to a duty or power are to be read accordingly.”</quote>
   <summary>New provisions are added to Section 183A, clarifying that a relevant enactment or rule of law does not override a requirement under the main data protection legislation and specifying exceptions to this rule.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The changes introduce new provisions regarding the relationship between relevant enactments or rules of law and the main data protection legislation, potentially affecting the processing of personal data.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 186</subject>
   <quote>“(2A) Subsection (1) does not apply—
(a) to an enactment contained in, or made under, a provision falling within subsection (2) or (3), or
(b) to the extent that an enactment makes express provision to the contrary referring to this section or to a provision falling within subsection (2).”</quote>
   <summary>New provisions are added to Section 186, specifying exceptions to the application of subsection (1).</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The changes introduce new provisions regarding the application of subsection (1) of Section 186, potentially affecting the protection of data subject's rights.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 44</subject>
   <quote>“CHAPTER 9A
Regulations 5
Article 91A
Regulations made by Secretary of State
1. This Article makes provision about regulations made by the Secretary
of State under this Regulation (“UK GDPR regulations”).
2. Before making UK GDPR regulations, the Secretary of State must 10
consult—
(a) the Commissioner, and
(b) such other persons as the Secretary of State considers appropriate.
3.
15
Paragraph 2 does not apply to regulations made under Article 49 or
49A where the Secretary of State has made an urgency statement in
respect of them.
4. UK GDPR regulations may—
(a) make different provision for different purposes;
(b)
20
include consequential, supplementary, incidental, transitional,
transitory or saving provision.
5. UK GDPR regulations are to be made by statutory instrument.
6. For the purposes of this Regulation, where regulations are subject to
“the negative resolution procedure”, the statutory instrument containing
25
the regulations is subject to annulment in pursuance of a resolution
of either House of Parliament.
7. For the purposes of this Regulation, where regulations are subject to
“the affirmative resolution procedure”, the regulations may not be
made unless a draft of the statutory instrument containing them has
30
been laid before Parliament and approved by a resolution of each
House of Parliament.
8. For the purposes of this Regulation, where regulations are subject to
“the made affirmative resolution procedure”—
(a) the statutory instrument containing the regulations must be laid
35
before Parliament after being made, together with the urgency
statement in respect of them, and
(b) the regulations cease to have effect at the end of the period of
120 days beginning with the day on which the instrument is
made, unless within that period the instrument is approved by
40
a resolution of each House of Parliament.
9. In calculating the period of 120 days, no account is to be taken of any
whole days that fall within a period during which—
(a) Parliament is dissolved or prorogued, or 5
(b) both Houses of Parliament are adjourned for more than 4 days.
10. Where regulations cease to have effect as a result of paragraph 8, that
does not—
(a) affect anything previously done under the regulations, or
(b) prevent the making of new regulations. 10
11. Any provision that may be included in UK GDPR regulations subject
to the negative resolution procedure may be made by regulations
made under this Regulation or another enactment that are subject to
the affirmative resolution procedure or the made affirmative resolution
procedure.
12. A requirement under this Article to consult may be satisfied by
consultation before, as well as by consultation after, the provision
conferring the power to make regulations comes into force.
13.
20
In this Article, “urgency statement”, in relation to regulations, means
a reasoned statement that the Secretary of State considers it desirable
for the regulations to come into force without delay.”</quote>
   <summary>New provisions are added to Section 44, making provision about regulations made by the Secretary of State under the UK GDPR.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The changes introduce new provisions regarding the making of regulations under the UK GDPR, potentially affecting the regulatory framework.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 9</subject>
   <quote>contains minor amendments of the UK GDPR and the 2018 Act.</quote>
   <summary>Schedule 9 contains minor amendments of the UK GDPR and the 2018 Act.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The changes introduce minor amendments to the UK GDPR and the 2018 Act, potentially affecting various aspects of data protection and digital information.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Part 2—Digital verification services</subject>
   <quote>Part 2—Digital verification services</quote>
   <summary>A new part titled "Digital verification services" is being inserted into the bill.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The establishment of a new part on digital verification services could potentially affect legal processes significantly, particularly in terms of verifying individuals' identities and the use of digital information for verification purposes.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>47 DVS trust framework</subject>
   <quote>47 DVS trust framework</quote>
   <summary>A new section titled "DVS trust framework" is being inserted into Part 2.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The establishment of a trust framework for digital verification services could potentially affect legal processes by setting rules and standards for the provision of these services.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>48 DVS register</subject>
   <quote>48 DVS register</quote>
   <summary>A new section titled "DVS register" is being inserted into Part 2.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The establishment of a register for persons providing digital verification services could potentially affect legal processes by ensuring that only registered individuals or entities can provide these services.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>49 Applications for registration</subject>
   <quote>49 Applications for registration</quote>
   <summary>A new section titled "Applications for registration" is being inserted into Part 2.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The establishment of a process for applications for registration in the DVS register could potentially affect legal processes by setting requirements and procedures for individuals or entities seeking registration.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>54 Power of public authority to disclose information to registered person</subject>
   <quote>54 Power of public authority to disclose information to registered person</quote>
   <summary>A new section titled "Power of public authority to disclose information to registered person" is being inserted into Part 2.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The provision for public authorities to disclose information to registered persons for the purpose of providing digital verification services could potentially affect legal processes by allowing for the exchange of relevant information.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>56 Code of practice about the disclosure of information</subject>
   <quote>56 Code of practice about the disclosure of information</quote>
   <summary>A new section titled "Code of practice about the disclosure of information" is being inserted into Part 2.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The establishment of a code of practice about the disclosure of information could potentially affect legal processes by providing guidelines and standards for the disclosure of information in the context of digital verification services.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>57 Trust mark for use by registered persons</subject>
   <quote>57 Trust mark for use by registered persons</quote>
   <summary>A new section titled "Trust mark for use by registered persons" is being inserted into Part 2.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The provision for a trust mark to be used by registered persons providing digital verification services could potentially affect legal processes by establishing a recognizable symbol of trust and credibility for these services.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>61 Customer data and business data</subject>
   <quote>61 Customer data and business data</quote>
   <summary>A new section titled "Customer data and business data" is being inserted into the bill.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The provision for powers to make provision in connection with access to customer data and business data could potentially affect legal processes by regulating the access and use of such data in the context of digital services.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>62 Power to make provision in connection with customer data</subject>
   <quote>62 Power to make provision in connection with customer data</quote>
   <summary>A new section titled "Power to make provision in connection with customer data" is being inserted into Part 3.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The provision for powers to make regulations requiring the provision of customer data could potentially affect legal processes by setting requirements and procedures for the access and provision of such data.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 35</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State or the Treasury may by regulations make provision enabling or requiring a data holder—
(a) to produce, collect or retain, or arrange for the production, collection or retention of, customer data;
(b) to make changes to customer data, including to require rectification of inaccurate customer data, at the request of a customer or authorised person.</quote>
   <summary>This section grants the Secretary of State or the Treasury the power to make regulations that enable or require data holders to produce, collect, retain, or make changes to customer data, including rectification of inaccurate data, at the request of a customer or authorized person.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      This change could potentially affect small businesses and micro businesses, as well as innovation in the supply or provision of goods, services, and digital content affected by the regulations.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Competition">
      The change may have an impact on competition in markets for goods, services, and digital content affected by the regulations or other markets.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 63</subject>
   <quote>The regulations may make provision about requests relating to customer data, including provision about the circumstances in which a data holder may or must refuse to act on a request.</quote>
   <summary>This section allows the regulations to include provisions regarding requests for customer data, including circumstances in which a data holder may or must refuse to act on a request.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      The regulations may have an impact on data holders and the effects for existing and future customers.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 64</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State or the Treasury may by regulations make provision requiring a data holder to publish business data or to provide business data on request—
(a) to a customer of the trader, or
(b) to another person of a specified description (a “third party recipient”).</quote>
   <summary>This section grants the Secretary of State or the Treasury the power to make regulations that require a data holder to publish or provide business data to customers or other specified persons upon request.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      The change may have effects for existing and future customers, data holders, small businesses, micro businesses, and innovation in the supply or provision of goods, services, and digital content affected by the regulations.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Competition">
      The change may have an impact on competition in markets for goods, services, and digital content affected by the regulations or other markets.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 66</subject>
   <quote>This section is about the provision about decision-makers that regulations under section 62 or 64 must or may (among other things) contain.</quote>
   <summary>This section addresses the provision about decision-makers that must or may be included in regulations under section 62 or 64.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The provision about decision-makers may have an impact on the resolution of disputes and appeals to a court or tribunal.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 67</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State or the Treasury may by regulations make provision for the enforcement of data regulations, and for the enforcement of requirements imposed in exercise of a power conferred by regulations under this Part, including provision for enforcement by a specified public body (an “enforcer”).</quote>
   <summary>This section grants the Secretary of State or the Treasury the power to make regulations for the enforcement of data regulations and requirements imposed by regulations under this Part, including enforcement by a specified public body.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The provision about enforcement may have an impact on the enforcement of data regulations and requirements.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 69</subject>
   <quote>This section is about provision that regulations under this Part conferring power on an enforcer to impose a financial penalty may or must (among other things) contain.</quote>
   <summary>This section addresses the provision that regulations under this Part must or may contain when conferring power on an enforcer to impose a financial penalty.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The provision about financial penalties may have an impact on the enforcement of data regulations and the rights of persons affected by the exercise of an enforcer's functions.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 70</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State or the Treasury may by regulations make provision enabling a person listed in subsection (2), or a person acting on their behalf, to require other persons to pay fees for the purpose of meeting expenses incurred, or to be incurred, in performing duties, or exercising powers, imposed or conferred by regulations under this Part, and make provision about how amounts paid as fees must or may be used.</quote>
   <summary>This section grants the Secretary of State or the Treasury the power to make regulations that enable certain persons to require other persons to pay fees for the purpose of meeting expenses incurred in performing duties or exercising powers imposed or conferred by regulations under this Part.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      The provision about fees may have an impact on the expenses incurred by persons performing duties or exercising powers under the regulations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulations under subsection (1)</subject>
   <quote>Regulations under subsection (1) enabling a person to determine the amount
of a fee must require the person to publish information about the amount
and how it is determined.</quote>
   <summary>Regulations under subsection (1) must require the person to publish information about the amount and how it is determined.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      The change ensures transparency in the determination of fees, which could have an impact on businesses and individuals who are subject to these fees.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulations under subsection (1)</subject>
   <quote>Regulations under subsection (1) may (among other things) make provision
about—
(a) interest on any unpaid amounts;
(b) the recovery of unpaid amounts.</quote>
   <summary>Regulations under subsection (1) may make provision about interest on unpaid amounts and the recovery of unpaid amounts.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      The change provides regulations for the interest on unpaid amounts and the recovery of unpaid amounts, which could have an impact on businesses and individuals who owe these amounts.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulations under subsection (1)</subject>
   <quote>Regulations under subsection (1) may only provide for a levy in respect of
expenses of decision-makers or enforcers to be imposed on data holders that
appear to the Secretary of State or the Treasury to be capable of being directly
affected by the exercise of some or all of the functions conferred on the
decision-makers or enforcers by regulations under this Part.</quote>
   <summary>Regulations under subsection (1) may impose a levy on data holders that are directly affected by the functions conferred on decision-makers or enforcers.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      The change allows for the imposition of a levy on data holders that are directly affected by the functions of decision-makers or enforcers, which could have an impact on businesses and individuals who are data holders.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulations under subsection (1)</subject>
   <quote>Regulations under subsection (1) providing for a specified public body to
impose a levy must—
(a) make provision about how the rate of the levy is to be determined;
(b) make provision about how the period in respect of which the levy is
payable is to be determined;
(c) require the body to publish information about the rate, the period and
how they are determined.</quote>
   <summary>Regulations under subsection (1) must make provision about the determination of the rate and period of the levy imposed by a specified public body, and require the body to publish information about the rate, the period, and how they are determined.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      The change ensures transparency in the determination of the rate and period of the levy imposed by a specified public body, which could have an impact on businesses and individuals who are subject to this levy.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulations under subsection (1)</subject>
   <quote>Regulations under subsection (1) may (among other things) make provision
about—
(a) interest on any unpaid amounts payable by way of a levy;
(b) the recovery of such unpaid amounts.</quote>
   <summary>Regulations under subsection (1) may make provision about interest on unpaid amounts payable by way of a levy and the recovery of such unpaid amounts.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      The change provides regulations for the interest on unpaid amounts payable by way of a levy and the recovery of such unpaid amounts, which could have an impact on businesses and individuals who owe these amounts.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulations under this Part</subject>
   <quote>Regulations under this Part may (among other things)—
(a) make provision generally or in relation to particular cases;
(b) make different provision for different purposes or areas;
(c) make provision about the form and manner in which things must or 5
may be done;
(d) make provision about the content of requests, notices or other
documents;
(e)
10
make provision about the time by which, or period within which,
things must or may be done;
(f) make provision by reference to specifications or technical requirements
published from time to time by a specified person;
(g) confer functions on a person, including functions involving the exercise
of a discretion;
(h) make incidental, supplementary, consequential, transitory, transitional 15
or saving provision.</quote>
   <summary>Regulations under this Part may make various provisions, including general or specific provisions, provisions for different purposes or areas, provisions about the form and manner of doing things, provisions about the content of requests or notices, provisions about timeframes, provisions by reference to specifications or technical requirements, provisions conferring functions on a person, and incidental or supplementary provisions.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      The change provides flexibility in making regulations under this Part, which could have an impact on businesses and individuals who are subject to these regulations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulations under this Part</subject>
   <quote>Regulations under this Part making the following types of provision may
amend or repeal primary legislation—
(a) provision about the handling of complaints;
(b) provision about the resolution of disputes;
(c) provision about appeals;
(d) provision described in subsection (1)(h).</quote>
   <summary>Regulations under this Part may amend or repeal primary legislation in relation to the handling of complaints, the resolution of disputes, appeals, and provision described in subsection (1)(h).</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change allows for the amendment or repeal of primary legislation in relation to the handling of complaints, the resolution of disputes, appeals, and other provisions, which could have an impact on the justice system.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulations under this Part</subject>
   <quote>The following regulations under this Part are subject to the affirmative
resolution procedure—
(a) the first regulations under each of section 62(1), (2) and (3) making 25
provision about a particular description of customer data,
(b) the first regulations under each of section 64(1) and (2) making
provision about a particular description of business data,
(c)
30
regulations under section 62 or 64 which make the requirements of
regulations under this Part more onerous for data holders,
(d) regulations under section 66(4), 67, 70 or 71, and
(e) regulations which amend or repeal primary legislation.</quote>
   <summary>The first regulations under section 62(1), (2), and (3) making provision about a particular description of customer data, the first regulations under section 64(1) and (2) making provision about a particular description of business data, regulations under section 62 or 64 that make the requirements of regulations under this Part more onerous for data holders, regulations under section 66(4), 67, 70, or 71, and regulations that amend or repeal primary legislation are subject to the affirmative resolution procedure.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change requires the affirmative resolution procedure for certain regulations under this Part, which could have an impact on the justice system.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulations under this Part</subject>
   <quote>Other regulations under this Part are subject to the negative resolution
procedure.</quote>
   <summary>Other regulations under this Part are subject to the negative resolution procedure.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change requires the negative resolution procedure for other regulations under this Part, which could have an impact on the justice system.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>The relevant person</subject>
   <quote>The relevant person must review data regulations for the time being in force—
(a) before the end of the period of 5 years beginning with the day on
which the regulations come into force, and
(b) at subsequent intervals not exceeding 5 years.</quote>
   <summary>The relevant person must review data regulations in force within 5 years of their enactment and at subsequent intervals not exceeding 5 years.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change requires the relevant person to review data regulations periodically, which could have an impact on the justice system.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>The relevant person</subject>
   <quote>The relevant person must prepare and publish a report setting out the findings
of the review.</quote>
   <summary>The relevant person must prepare and publish a report setting out the findings of the review.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change requires the relevant person to prepare and publish a report on the findings of the review, which could have an impact on the justice system.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>The relevant person</subject>
   <quote>The relevant person may omit material from a report under this section before 15
publication if the relevant person thinks the publication of that material—
(a) would contravene the data protection legislation, or
(b) might harm the commercial interests of any person.</quote>
   <summary>The relevant person may omit material from a report if its publication would contravene the data protection legislation or might harm the commercial interests of any person.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change allows the relevant person to omit material from a report under certain circumstances, which could have an impact on the justice system.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>The relevant person</subject>
   <quote>The relevant person must lay a copy of any report published under this
section before Parliament.</quote>
   <summary>The relevant person must lay a copy of any published report before Parliament.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change requires the relevant person to lay a copy of any published report before Parliament, which could have an impact on the justice system.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulation 6 of the PEC Regulations</subject>
   <quote>Regulation 6 of the PEC Regulations is amended as follows.
(2) In paragraph (2), after “paragraph (3)” insert “or (3A)”.
(3) After paragraph (3) insert—
“(3A)
30
A person may send or instigate the sending of electronic mail for the
purposes of direct marketing where—
(a) the direct marketing is solely for the purpose of furthering a
charitable, political or other non-commercial objective of that
person;
(b)
35
that person obtained the contact details of the recipient of the
electronic mail in the course of the recipient expressing an
interest in or offering or providing support for the furtherance
of that objective or a similar objective; and
(c) the recipient has been given a simple means of refusing (free
40
of charge except for the costs of the transmission of the refusal)
the use of their contact details for the purposes of such direct
marketing, at the time that the details were initially collected,
and, where the recipient did not initially refuse the use of the
details, at the time of each subsequent communication.”</quote>
   <summary>Regulation 6 of the PEC Regulations is amended to allow a person to send or instigate the sending of electronic mail for the purposes of direct marketing if the marketing is solely for the purpose of furthering a non-commercial objective, the contact details were obtained in the course of the recipient expressing an interest or providing support for that objective, and the recipient has been given a simple means of refusing the use of their contact details for direct marketing.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change amends the regulations regarding the sending of electronic mail for direct marketing purposes, which could have an impact on the justice system.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Regulation 22 of the PEC Regulations</subject>
   <quote>Regulation 22 of the PEC Regulations (use of electronic mail for direct marketing purposes) is amended as follows.
(2) In paragraph (2), after “paragraph (3)” insert “or (3A)”.
(3) After paragraph (3) insert—
“(3A)
30
A person may send or instigate the sending of electronic mail for the
purposes of direct marketing where—
(a) the direct marketing is solely for the purpose of furthering a
charitable, political or other non-commercial objective of that
person;
(b)
35
that person obtained the contact details of the recipient of the
electronic mail in the course of the recipient expressing an
interest in or offering or providing support for the furtherance
of that objective or a similar objective; and
(c) the recipient has been given a simple means of refusing (free
40
of charge except for the costs of the transmission of the refusal)
the use of their contact details for the purposes of such direct
marketing, at the time that the details were initially collected,
and, where the recipient did not initially refuse the use of the
details, at the time of each subsequent communication.”</quote>
   <summary>Regulation 22 of the PEC Regulations is amended to allow a person to send or instigate the sending of electronic mail for the purposes of direct marketing if the marketing is solely for the purpose of furthering a non-commercial objective, the contact details were obtained in the course of the recipient expressing an interest or providing support for that objective, and the recipient has been given a simple means of refusing the use of their contact details for direct marketing.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change amends the regulations regarding the use of electronic mail for direct marketing purposes, which could have an impact on the justice system.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>The Secretary of State</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may by regulations provide an exception from a direct 5
marketing provision for a case where communications activity—
(a) is carried out for the purposes of democratic engagement, and
(b) is not directed to individuals under the age of 14.</quote>
   <summary>The Secretary of State may provide an exception from a direct marketing provision for communications activity carried out for the purposes of democratic engagement and not directed to individuals under the age of 14.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change allows for an exception from a direct marketing provision for communications activity related to democratic engagement, which could have an impact on the justice system.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Part 4—Other provision about digital information</subject>
   <quote>(5) Before making regulations under this section, the Secretary of State must consult—
(a) the Information Commissioner, and
(b) such other persons as the Secretary of State considers appropriate.
(6) Before making regulations under this section, the Secretary of State must 5
consider the effect the regulations may have on the privacy of individuals.
(7) Regulations under this section are subject to the affirmative resolution
procedure.</quote>
   <summary>The Secretary of State must consult the Information Commissioner and consider the effect on privacy before making regulations under this section. Regulations under this section are subject to the affirmative resolution procedure.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Human Rights">
      The amendment ensures that the Secretary of State consults the Information Commissioner and considers the privacy of individuals before making regulations, which protects human rights and privacy.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>84 Meaning of expressions in section 83</subject>
   <quote>“accredited campaigner” has the meaning given in Part 5 of Schedule 3
to the Recall of MPs Act 2015;
“candidate”, in relation to election as an elected representative, has the
meaning given by the provision listed in the relevant entry in the
second column of the table in subsection (3);
“communications activity” means—
(a) transmitting, or instigating the transmission of, a
communication, or
(b)
using, or instigating the use of, a public electronic
communications service to make a call;
“democratic engagement activities” means activities whose purpose is
to support or promote democratic engagement;
“direct marketing” means the communication (by whatever means) of
advertising or marketing material which is directed to particular
individuals;
“direct marketing provision” means any provision of regulations 19 to
24 of the PEC Regulations;
“elected representative” means a person listed in the first column of the
table in subsection (3) and see also subsections (4) and (5);
“permitted participant” has the same meaning as in Part 7 of the Political
Parties, Elections and Referendums Act 2000 (referendums) (see section
105 of that Act);
“recall petition” has the same meaning as in the Recall of MPs Act 2015
(see section 1(2) of that Act);
“referendum” means a referendum or other poll held on one or more
questions specified in, or in accordance with, an enactment.</quote>
   <summary>The meanings of various expressions in section 83 are provided, including "accredited campaigner," "candidate," "communications activity," "democratic engagement activities," "direct marketing," "direct marketing provision," "elected representative," "permitted participant," "recall petition," and "referendum."</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">
      The insertion provides clarity on the meanings of various expressions used in section 83, which helps in understanding the legislation and its implications for political power.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>85 Duty to notify the Commissioner of unlawful direct marketing</subject>
   <quote>“26A Duty to notify Commissioner of unlawful direct marketing
(1) A provider of a public electronic communications service must notify
the Commissioner of any reasonable grounds the provider has for
suspecting that a person is contravening or has contravened any of
the direct marketing regulations in the course of using the service.
(2) A provider of a public electronic communications network must notify
the Commissioner of any reasonable grounds the provider has for
suspecting that a person is contravening or has contravened any of
the direct marketing regulations in the course of using the network
or using a public electronic communication service provided by means
of the network.
(3) A notification under this regulation must be given within the period
of 28 days beginning with the day on which the reasonable grounds
for suspicion come to the attention of the provider.
(4) “Direct marketing regulations” means regulations 19 to 22.
26B Fixed penalty for failure to comply with regulation 26A
(1) If a provider of a public electronic communications service or public
electronic communications network fails to comply with regulation
26A, the Commissioner may issue a fixed monetary penalty notice in
respect of the failure.
(2) The amount of a fixed monetary penalty under this regulation shall
be £1,000.
(3)
Before serving a fixed monetary penalty notice, the Commissioner
must serve the provider with a notice of intent.
(4) The notice of intent must—
(a) state the name and address of the provider;
(b) state the nature of the failure;
(c) state the amount of the fixed monetary penalty;
(d) include a statement informing the provider of the opportunity
to discharge liability for the fixed monetary penalty;
(e) indicate the date on which the Commissioner proposes to serve
the fixed monetary penalty notice; and
(f)
inform the provider that the provider may make written
representations in relation to the proposal to serve a fixed
monetary penalty notice within the period of 21 days beginning
with the day the notice of intent is served.
(5) A provider may discharge liability for the fixed monetary penalty if
the provider pays to the Commissioner the amount of £800 within the
period of 21 days beginning with the day the notice of intent is served.
(6) The Commissioner may not serve a fixed monetary penalty notice
until the period within which representations may be made has
expired.
(7) The fixed monetary penalty notice must state—
(a) the name and address of the provider;
(b) details of the notice of intent served on the provider;
(c) whether there have been any written representations;
(d) details of any early payment discounts;
(e)
the grounds on which the Commissioner imposes the fixed
monetary penalty;
(f) the date by which the fixed monetary penalty is to be paid;
and
(g) details of, including the time limit for, the provider’s right of
appeal against the imposition of the fixed monetary penalty.</quote>
   <summary>Providers of public electronic communications services and networks must notify the Commissioner of any reasonable grounds for suspecting direct marketing violations. The Commissioner may issue a fixed monetary penalty for non-compliance, and providers have the opportunity to discharge liability by paying a reduced amount within a specified period.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Privacy">
      The insertion establishes a duty for providers of public electronic communications services and networks to notify the Commissioner of direct marketing violations, which helps protect privacy rights.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>GREEN</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>86 Commissioner’s enforcement powers</subject>
   <quote>(1) Schedule 1 provides for certain provisions of Parts 5 to 7 of the Data
Protection Act 2018 to apply with modifications for the purposes of
enforcing these Regulations.
(2)
In regulations 32 and 33, “enforcement functions” means the functions
of the Information Commissioner under those provisions, as applied
by that Schedule.”</quote>
   <summary>Provisions of the Data Protection Act 2018 apply with modifications for the purposes of enforcing these Regulations. "Enforcement functions" refer to the functions of the Information Commissioner under those provisions.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment ensures that provisions of the Data Protection Act 2018 apply with modifications for the enforcement of these Regulations, which helps maintain the integrity of the justice system.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>88 Recognition of EU conformity assessment bodies</subject>
   <quote>“Article 24B
Recognition of EU conformity assessment bodies
For the purposes of Articles 20(1), 21 and 24(1)(d), a body is to
be treated as if it were a conformity assessment body in relation
to a description of trust services provider (and trust service) if
it is a conformity assessment body in relation to that description
of provider (and service) for the purposes of the equivalent EU
law.”</quote>
   <summary>A body is treated as a conformity assessment body in relation to a description of trust services provider and trust service for the purposes of Articles 20(1), 21, and 24(1)(d) if it is a conformity assessment body for that description of provider and service under the equivalent EU law.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      The insertion ensures the recognition of EU conformity assessment bodies for trust services providers, which helps facilitate economic cooperation and impact.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>89 Removal of recognition of EU standards etc</subject>
   <quote>(1) The Secretary of State may by regulations—
(a) amend Article 24A of the eIDAS Regulation (recognition of EU
standards etc for qualified trust services) so as to remove circumstances
in which something is to be treated as qualified under that Regulation
for the purposes of a provision or measure specified in paragraph 1
of that Article;
(b) revoke that Article;
(c) revoke Article 24B of the eIDAS Regulation (recognition of EU
conformity assessment bodies);
(d) revoke Article 51 of the eIDAS Regulation (transitional measures for
electronic signatures);
(e) amend a provision listed in subsection (3) so as to remove a reference
to a trust service provider established in the EU;
(f) amend a provision listed in subsection (4) so as to remove a reference
to European standards or provisions of equivalent EU law.</quote>
   <summary>The Secretary of State is granted the power to amend or revoke certain articles of the eIDAS Regulation, remove references to EU trust service providers, and remove references to European standards or provisions of equivalent EU law.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">
      The amendment grants the Secretary of State the power to amend or revoke certain articles of the eIDAS Regulation, which impacts political power and decision-making.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>90 Recognition of overseas trust products</subject>
   <quote>“Article 45A
Legal effects of overseas electronic signatures etc 5
1. The Secretary of State may by regulations provide that, for the
purposes of Articles 25(2), 35(2), 41(2) and 43(2), an overseas trust
product of a specified description is to be treated as qualified.
2. In this Article—
“overseas”, in relation to a trust product, means provided by a 10
person established in a country or territory outside the United
Kingdom;
“specified” means specified by regulations under this Article;
15
“trust product” means an electronic signature, an electronic seal,
an electronic time stamp or an electronic registered delivery
service.
3. The Secretary of State may not make regulations under this Article
specifying a description of overseas trust product unless satisfied that
20
the reliability of such a product is at least equivalent to the reliability
of a comparable trust product that is qualified.
4. When making regulations under this Article in relation to a description
of overseas trust product, the Secretary of State must have regard to
(among other things) the law in the other country or territory relevant
to that description of product and related trust services.</quote>
   <summary>The Secretary of State may provide that an overseas trust product of a specified description is treated as qualified for certain purposes. The reliability of the overseas trust product must be at least equivalent to that of a comparable qualified trust product.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      The insertion allows for the recognition of overseas trust products, which can have economic impacts by facilitating international transactions and cooperation.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>91 Co-operation between supervisory authority and overseas authorities</subject>
   <quote>“(3) In this Article—
“designated” means designated by regulations made by the
Secretary of State that are in force;
“overseas authority” means a person, or description of person, 20
with functions relating to the regulation or supervision of trust
services outside the United Kingdom.
4. Before making regulations under this Article, the Secretary of State
must consult the supervisory body.
5. Regulations under this Article may include transitional or transitory 25
provision or savings.
6. Regulations under this Article are to be made by statutory instrument.
7. A statutory instrument containing regulations under this Article is
subject to annulment in pursuance of either House of Parliament.”</quote>
   <summary>The Secretary of State may designate overseas authorities with functions relating to the regulation or supervision of trust services. Regulations under this Article must be made after consultation with the supervisory body and are subject to annulment in Parliament.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">
      The insertion allows for the designation of overseas authorities for the regulation and supervision of trust services, impacting political power and decision-making.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>92 Disclosure of information to improve public service delivery to undertakings</subject>
   <quote>(2) In subsection (9)—
(a) in paragraph (a), for “or households” substitute “, households or 35
undertakings”, and
(b) in paragraph (b), for “or households” substitute “, households or
undertakings”.
(3) In subsection (10)—
(a) the words after “its purpose” become paragraph (a), and
(b) at the end of that paragraph, insert “, or 5
(b) the assisting of undertakings in connection with any
trade, business or charitable purpose.”</quote>
   <summary>The disclosure of information to improve public service delivery can now include undertakings in addition to households. The purpose of the disclosure can also include assisting undertakings in connection with trade, business, or charitable purposes.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Social Welfare">
      The amendment expands the scope of information disclosure to include undertakings, which can benefit social welfare by improving public service delivery to businesses and charitable organizations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 93</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may by regulations make such provision as the Secretary of State considers appropriate for the purpose of, or in connection with, implementing an international agreement so far as relating to the sharing of information for law enforcement purposes, as it has effect from time to time.</quote>
   <summary>This change grants the Secretary of State the power to make regulations to implement international agreements regarding the sharing of information for law enforcement purposes.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="National Security">
      This change enhances national security by allowing the sharing of information for law enforcement purposes as part of international agreements.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 94</subject>
   <quote>For section 25 (provision of registers, etc, by Registrar General) substitute— “25 Form in which registers are to be kept, etc (1) Registers of live-births, still-births and deaths must be kept in such form as the Registrar General may reasonably require.</quote>
   <summary>This change amends the provision of registers of live-births, still-births, and deaths by requiring them to be kept in a form determined by the Registrar General.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change improves the efficiency and accuracy of record-keeping for births, still-births, and deaths by allowing the Registrar General to determine the form in which registers are kept.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Section 95</subject>
   <quote>In the Registration Service Act 1953, after section 11 insert— “11A Provision of equipment and facilities by local authorities (1) At each register office provided for the superintendent registrar of a district, the council which employs the superintendent registrar shall, subject to the provisions of the local scheme, provide and maintain such equipment or facilities as the Registrar General reasonably considers to be necessary for the performance of the superintendent registrar’s functions.</quote>
   <summary>This change removes the provision for local authorities to provide equipment and facilities for register offices.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change may impact the efficiency and effectiveness of register offices as local authorities are no longer required to provide necessary equipment and facilities.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>YELLOW</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 96</subject>
   <quote>“38B Requirements to sign register (1) Where any register of births or register of deaths is required to be kept under this Act otherwise than in hard copy form, the Minister may by regulations provide that— (a) a person’s duty under this Act to sign the register at any time is to have effect as a duty to comply with specified requirements at that time, and (b) a person who complies with those requirements is to be treated for the purposes of this Act as having signed the register at that time and, in the case of a duty to sign the register in the presence of the registrar, to have done so in the presence of the registrar, and accordingly, in such a case, the entry in the register is to be taken for the purposes of this Act to have been signed by the person.</quote>
   <summary>This change allows for the Minister to make regulations regarding the signing of registers of births or deaths, including the use of specified requirements instead of physical signatures.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change modernizes the process of signing registers of births or deaths by allowing for the use of specified requirements instead of physical signatures.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Section 97</subject>
   <quote>The repeal of section 28 of the Births and Deaths Registration Act 1953 by section 94 above does not affect— (a) the requirement under section 28(2) of that Act for every superintendent registrar (“S”) to keep with the records of S’s office any registers of live-births or of deaths which are in S’s custody immediately before the coming into force of that repeal, or (b) the requirement under section 28(4) of that Act for the Registrar General to keep in the General Register Office— (i) any certified copies or information sent or provided under section 27 of that Act (quarterly returns by superintendent registrar to Registrar General), or (ii) any registers of still-births that were forwarded to the Registrar General before the coming into force of that repeal.</quote>
   <summary>This change clarifies that the repeal of section 28 of the Births and Deaths Registration Act 1953 does not affect the requirements for superintendent registrars and the Registrar General to keep certain registers and records.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change ensures that the requirements for keeping registers and records of births, deaths, and still-births are not affected by the repeal of section 28.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 100</subject>
   <quote>The 2018 Act is amended as follows. (2) After section 114 insert— “The Information Commission 114A The Information Commission (1) A body corporate called the Information Commission is established. (2) Schedule 12A makes further provision about the Commission.”</quote>
   <summary>This change establishes the Information Commission as a body corporate and provides for further provisions about the Commission in Schedule 12A.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change establishes a new institution, the Information Commission, which will have significant impact on the regulation and oversight of data protection and digital information.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Section 101</subject>
   <quote>The office of Information Commissioner is abolished.</quote>
   <summary>This change abolishes the office of Information Commissioner.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change has a significant impact on the regulation and oversight of data protection and digital information as it abolishes the office of Information Commissioner.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>RED</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 104</subject>
   <quote>The office of Commissioner for the Retention and Use of Biometric Material is abolished.</quote>
   <summary>This change abolishes the office of Commissioner for the Retention and Use of Biometric Material.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change has a significant impact on the oversight of biometric data as it abolishes the office of Commissioner for the Retention and Use of Biometric Material.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>RED</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 106</subject>
   <quote>Section 63AB of the Police and Criminal Evidence Act 1984 (National DNA Database Strategy Board) is amended as follows. (2) For the heading substitute “Oversight of biometrics databases”. (3) In subsection (1)— (a) for “National DNA Database Strategy Board” substitute “Strategy Board (“the Board”)”, (b) after “of” insert “— (a) ”, and (c) at the end insert “, and (b) a database of fingerprints— (i) taken from a person under a power conferred by this Part of this Act, or (ii) taken by the police, with the consent of the person from whom they were taken, in connection with the investigation of an offence by the police.”</quote>
   <summary>This change amends the heading and provisions of Section 63AB of the Police and Criminal Evidence Act 1984 to reflect the oversight of biometrics databases.</summary>
   <impact>3</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change enhances the oversight of biometrics databases by amending the provisions of Section 63AB of the Police and Criminal Evidence Act 1984.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Section 105</subject>
   <quote>The office of Surveillance Camera Commissioner is abolished. (2) In the Protection of Freedoms Act 2012, omit Chapter 1 of Part 2 (regulation of CCTV and other surveillance technology).</quote>
   <summary>This change abolishes the office of Surveillance Camera Commissioner and removes the regulation of CCTV and other surveillance technology from the Protection of Freedoms Act 2012.</summary>
   <impact>4</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change has a significant impact on the regulation and oversight of surveillance technology as it abolishes the office of Surveillance Camera Commissioner and removes the relevant provisions from the Protection of Freedoms Act 2012.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>RED</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 107</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may by regulations make provision that is consequential on any provision made by this Act.</quote>
   <summary>This change grants the Secretary of State the power to make regulations that are consequential on any provision made by this Act.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change allows for the Secretary of State to make consequential amendments to other legislation in response to the provisions made by this Act.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 108</subject>
   <quote>Regulations under this Act are to be made by statutory instrument.</quote>
   <summary>This section establishes that regulations under this Act will be made by statutory instrument.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change establishes the process for making regulations under this Act, ensuring transparency and accountability in the regulatory process.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 108</subject>
   <quote>Where regulations under this Act are subject to “the affirmative resolution procedure” the regulations may not be made unless a draft of the statutory instrument containing them has been laid before Parliament and approved by a resolution of each House of Parliament.</quote>
   <summary>This section specifies that regulations under this Act that are subject to the "affirmative resolution procedure" must be approved by both Houses of Parliament before they can be made.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">
      This change ensures that regulations under this Act that have a significant impact must be approved by Parliament, providing a check on the power of the government.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 108</subject>
   <quote>Where regulations under this Act are subject to “the negative resolution procedure” the statutory instrument containing the regulations is subject to annulment in pursuance of a resolution of either House of Parliament.</quote>
   <summary>This section states that regulations under this Act that are subject to the "negative resolution procedure" can be annulled by either House of Parliament.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">
      This change provides a mechanism for Parliament to challenge and potentially overturn regulations under this Act that are deemed inappropriate or excessive.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 109</subject>
   <quote>“the 2018 Act” means the Data Protection Act 2018 (see section 1);</quote>
   <summary>This section defines "the 2018 Act" as the Data Protection Act 2018.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change provides clarity on the reference to the Data Protection Act 2018 in the bill.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 109</subject>
   <quote>“the UK GDPR” means Regulation (EU) 2016/679 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 27 April on the protection of natural persons with regard to the processing of personal data and on the free movement of such data.</quote>
   <summary>This section defines "the UK GDPR" as Regulation (EU) 2016/679, which pertains to the protection of personal data.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change provides clarity on the reference to the UK GDPR in the bill.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 110</subject>
   <quote>There is to be paid out of money provided by Parliament— (a) any expenditure incurred under or by virtue of this Act by the Secretary of State, the Treasury or a government department, and (b) any increase attributable to this Act in the sums payable under any other Act out of money so provided.</quote>
   <summary>This section states that any expenditure incurred under this Act by the Secretary of State, the Treasury, or a government department will be paid out of money provided by Parliament.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Economic Impact">
      This change ensures that the necessary funds are allocated for the implementation and operation of this Act, potentially impacting the government's budget.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 111</subject>
   <quote>This Act extends to England and Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland, subject to subsections (2) to (4).</quote>
   <summary>This section states that this Act extends to England and Wales, Scotland, and Northern Ireland, with some exceptions specified in subsections (2) to (4).</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">
      This change ensures that the provisions of this Act apply to all parts of the UK, subject to specific exceptions.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 112</subject>
   <quote>Except as provided by subsections (2) and (3), this Act comes into force on such day as the Secretary of State may by regulations appoint.</quote>
   <summary>This section states that this Act will come into force on a day appointed by the Secretary of State, with some exceptions specified in subsections (2) and (3).</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">
      This change provides flexibility in determining the effective date of this Act, allowing for proper preparation and implementation.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 113</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may by regulations make transitional, transitory or saving provision in connection with the coming into force of any provision of this Act.</quote>
   <summary>This section grants the Secretary of State the power to make transitional, transitory, or saving provisions in relation to the coming into force of any provision of this Act.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Political Power">
      This change allows for the smooth transition and implementation of this Act, ensuring that any necessary provisions are made.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 1</subject>
   <quote>In the UK GDPR, at the end insert— “ANNEX 1 LAWFULNESS OF PROCESSING: RECOGNISED LEGITIMATE INTERESTS"</quote>
   <summary>This schedule inserts an annex into the UK GDPR that pertains to the lawful processing of personal data based on recognized legitimate interests.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change provides additional guidance on the lawful processing of personal data based on recognized legitimate interests, ensuring clarity and compliance with data protection regulations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 2</subject>
   <quote>In the UK GDPR, after Annex 1 (inserted by Schedule 1 to this Act) insert— “ANNEX 2 PURPOSE LIMITATION: PROCESSING TO BE TREATED AS COMPATIBLE WITH ORIGINAL PURPOSE”</quote>
   <summary>This schedule inserts an additional annex into the UK GDPR that pertains to the processing of personal data to be treated as compatible with the original purpose.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change provides additional guidance on the processing of personal data to ensure compatibility with the original purpose, promoting transparency and accountability.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 3</subject>
   <quote>The UK GDPR</quote>
   <summary>This schedule amends the UK GDPR by making consequential amendments to various articles and sections.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change ensures that the UK GDPR is aligned with the provisions of this Act, promoting consistency and coherence in data protection regulations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 4</subject>
   <quote>The UK GDPR</quote>
   <summary>This schedule amends the UK GDPR by making consequential amendments to various articles and sections.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change ensures that the UK GDPR is aligned with the provisions of this Act, promoting consistency and coherence in data protection regulations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 33 (other definitions for Part 3)</subject>
   <quote>“(6A) “Senior responsible individual” means an individual designated as the senior responsible individual of a controller or processor under section 58A.”</quote>
   <summary>A new definition for "Senior responsible individual" is added to Section 33.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The addition of a definition for "Senior responsible individual" may improve accountability and responsibility within organizations that process personal data.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 44(1)(b) (controller’s duty to provide information)</subject>
   <quote>for “data protection officer (see sections 69 to 71)” substitute “senior responsible individual”.</quote>
   <summary>The term "data protection officer" is replaced with "senior responsible individual" in Section 44(1)(b).</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change aligns the terminology with the new definition of "Senior responsible individual" and clarifies the duty to provide information.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 55(1) (overview of provisions in Part 3 about controllers and processors)</subject>
   <quote>in paragraph (a), for “and processors (see sections 56 to 65)” substitute “(see sections 56 to 58)”,</quote>
   <summary>The reference to "processors" is removed from Section 55(1)(a).</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change clarifies the scope of the provisions in Part 3 related to controllers and processors.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 55(1) (overview of provisions in Part 3 about controllers and processors)</subject>
   <quote>“(aa) makes provision for the designation, tasks and position of senior responsible individuals (see sections 58A to 58C);</quote>
   <summary>A new provision is added to Section 55(1) to make provision for the designation, tasks, and position of senior responsible individuals.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change recognizes the importance of senior responsible individuals and their role in data protection.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Section 55(1) (overview of provisions in Part 3 about controllers and processors)</subject>
   <quote>omit paragraph (d).</quote>
   <summary>Paragraph (d) is removed from Section 55(1).</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change removes a paragraph that is no longer necessary in the overview of provisions in Part 3.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 67(4)(b) (notification of a personal data breach to the Commissioner)</subject>
   <quote>for “data protection officer” substitute “senior responsible individual”.</quote>
   <summary>The term "data protection officer" is replaced with "senior responsible individual" in Section 67(4)(b).</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change aligns the terminology with the new definition of "Senior responsible individual" and clarifies the duty to notify the Commissioner of a personal data breach.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 68(2)(b) (communication of a personal data breach to the data subject)</subject>
   <quote>for “data protection officer” substitute “senior responsible individual”.</quote>
   <summary>The term "data protection officer" is replaced with "senior responsible individual" in Section 68(2)(b).</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change aligns the terminology with the new definition of "Senior responsible individual" and clarifies the duty to communicate a personal data breach to the data subject.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 134 (Commissioner’s power to charge fees for services)</subject>
   <quote>In that subsection, for “data protection officer” substitute “senior responsible individual”.</quote>
   <summary>The term "data protection officer" is replaced with "senior responsible individual" in Section 134.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change aligns the terminology with the new definition of "Senior responsible individual" and clarifies the power of the Commissioner to charge fees for services.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 134 (Commissioner’s power to charge fees for services)</subject>
   <quote>After that subsection insert—“(2) In this section and section 135, “senior responsible individual” means an individual designated as the senior responsible individual of a controller or processor under Article 27A of the UK GDPR or section 58A of this Act.”</quote>
   <summary>A new subsection is added to Section 134 to define the term "senior responsible individual" for the purposes of this section and Section 135.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change provides a clear definition of the term "senior responsible individual" for the purposes of the Commissioner's power to charge fees for services.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 135(1) (manifestly unfounded or excessive requests by data subject etc)</subject>
   <quote>for “data protection officer” substitute “senior responsible individual”.</quote>
   <summary>The term "data protection officer" is replaced with "senior responsible individual" in Section 135(1).</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change aligns the terminology with the new definition of "Senior responsible individual" and clarifies the handling of manifestly unfounded or excessive requests by data subjects.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 149(2)(c) (enforcement notices)</subject>
   <quote>for “39” substitute “35”, and</quote>
   <summary>The reference to "39" is replaced with "35" in Section 149(2)(c).</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change corrects a reference to the relevant section number in the context of enforcement notices.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Section 149(2)(c) (enforcement notices)</subject>
   <quote>omit “or 65”.</quote>
   <summary>The reference to "or 65" is removed from Section 149(2)(c).</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change removes a reference that is no longer necessary in the context of enforcement notices.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 155(3) (penalty notices)</subject>
   <quote>in paragraph (c), at the end insert “, including any consultation under section 65”, and</quote>
   <summary>A new clause is added to Section 155(3)(c) to include any consultation under section 65 in the penalty notices.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change ensures that any consultation under section 65 is considered in the context of penalty notices.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Section 155(3) (penalty notices)</subject>
   <quote>in paragraph (d), omit “technical and organisational”.</quote>
   <summary>The term "technical and organisational" is removed from Section 155(3)(d).</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change removes a term that is no longer necessary in the context of penalty notices.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 206 (index of defined expressions)</subject>
   <quote>in the Table, at the appropriate place insert—“senior responsible individual (in Part 3) section 33”.</quote>
   <summary>A new entry for "senior responsible individual" is added to the index of defined expressions in Section 206.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change adds a reference to the index of defined expressions for the term "senior responsible individual".
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Paragraph 41 of Schedule 1 (additional safeguards for processing of special categories of personal data etc: record of processing)</subject>
   <quote>for “30” substitute “30A”.</quote>
   <summary>The reference to "30" is replaced with "30A" in Paragraph 41 of Schedule 1.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change corrects a reference to the relevant paragraph number in the context of additional safeguards for processing special categories of personal data.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Paragraph 26(9)(c) of Schedule 2 (exemptions etc from the UK GDPR: journalistic, academic, artistic and literary purposes)</subject>
   <quote>omit sub-paragraph (ii).</quote>
   <summary>Sub-paragraph (ii) is removed from Paragraph 26(9)(c) of Schedule 2.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change removes a sub-paragraph that is no longer necessary in the context of exemptions for journalistic, academic, artistic, and literary purposes.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 72 (overview and interpretation)</subject>
   <quote>“(2) In this Chapter—
“relevant authority”, in relation to a third country, means any person based in a third country that has (in that country) functions comparable to those of a competent authority;
“relevant international organisation” means an international organisation that carries out functions for any of the law enforcement purposes;
“relevant restricted transfer case” means (subject to subsection (3)) a case in which the personal data was originally made available to a competent authority (whether the current controller or a previous controller)—
(a) by a relevant authority in a third country or by a relevant international organisation, and
(b) subject to a condition (however imposed) that the data is not to be transferred to a third country or international organisation without authorisation from that authority or organisation or another such authority or organisation;
“overseas authoriser”, in connection with a relevant restricted transfer case, means the person whose authorisation is required.
(3) In a case in which the personal data was originally made available to a competent authority subject to a condition that only requires authorisation for further transfers in certain circumstances, the case is a relevant restricted transfer case only in those circumstances.”</quote>
   <summary>A new subsection is added to Section 72 to provide definitions for "relevant authority," "relevant international organisation," "relevant restricted transfer case," and "overseas authoriser."</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change provides clear definitions for terms used in the context of transfers of personal data to third countries in law enforcement processing.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 73 (general principles for transfers)</subject>
   <quote>for “may not” substitute “may”,</quote>
   <summary>The term "may not" is replaced with "may" in Section 73(1).</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change clarifies that transfers of personal data to third countries for law enforcement purposes are allowed under certain conditions.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 73 (general principles for transfers)</subject>
   <quote>for “unless” substitute “for a law enforcement purpose only if”,</quote>
   <summary>The term "unless" is replaced with "for a law enforcement purpose only if" in Section 73(1).</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change clarifies that transfers of personal data to third countries for law enforcement purposes are only allowed if they serve a law enforcement purpose.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Section 73 (general principles for transfers)</subject>
   <quote>omit paragraph (b) (and the “and” before it),</quote>
   <summary>Paragraph (b) is removed from Section 73(1).</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change removes a paragraph that is no longer necessary in the context of general principles for transfers of personal data to third countries for law enforcement purposes.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 73 (general principles for transfers)</subject>
   <quote>“(c) the transfer is carried out in accordance with the other provisions of this Part, and
(d) in a relevant restricted transfer case, the overseas authoriser has authorised the transfer or subsection (5) applies.”</quote>
   <summary>Two new clauses are added to Section 73(1) to require that the transfer is carried out in accordance with the other provisions of this Part and that the overseas authoriser has authorized the transfer in a relevant restricted transfer case.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      These changes ensure that transfers of personal data to third countries for law enforcement purposes comply with the relevant provisions and are authorized in relevant restricted transfer cases.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 73 (general principles for transfers)</subject>
   <quote>for “is made subject to” substitute “is based on”,</quote>
   <summary>The term "is made subject to" is replaced with "is based on" in Section 73(3)(b).</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change clarifies that transfers of personal data to third countries for law enforcement purposes are based on appropriate safeguards.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 73 (general principles for transfers)</subject>
   <quote>“(c) is based on special circumstances (see section 76).”</quote>
   <summary>A new clause is added to Section 73(3) to allow transfers of personal data to third countries for law enforcement purposes based on special circumstances.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change provides flexibility for transfers of personal data to third countries for law enforcement purposes in special circumstances.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 73 (general principles for transfers)</subject>
   <quote>for “without the authorisation” substitute “in a relevant restricted transfer case without the authorisation from the overseas authoriser”,</quote>
   <summary>The term "without the authorisation" is replaced with "in a relevant restricted transfer case without the authorisation from the overseas authoriser" in Section 73(6)(a).</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change clarifies that transfers of personal data to third countries without the required authorization from the overseas authorizer are only applicable in relevant restricted transfer cases.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 73 (general principles for transfers)</subject>
   <quote>for the words from “(1)(b)” to “the transfer” substitute “(1)(d), the overseas authoriser”.</quote>
   <summary>The reference to "(1)(b)" is replaced with "(1)(d), the overseas authoriser" in Section 73(6)(b).</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change corrects a reference to the relevant paragraph number in the context of general principles for transfers of personal data to third countries for law enforcement purposes.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 74AA (transfers approved by regulations)</subject>
   <quote>“(1) For the purposes of section 73, the Secretary of State may by regulations approve transfers of personal data to—
(a) a third country, or
(b) an international organisation.
(2) The Secretary of State may only make regulations under this section approving transfers to a third country or international organisation if the Secretary of State considers that the data protection test is met in relation to the transfers (see section 74AB).
(3) In making regulations under this section, the Secretary of State may have regard to any matter which the Secretary of State considers relevant, including the desirability of facilitating transfers of personal data to and from the United Kingdom.
(4) Regulations under this section may, among other things—
(a) make provision by reference to a third country or international organisation specified in the regulations or a description of country or organisation;
(b) approve all transfers of personal data to a third country or international organisation or only transfers specified or described in the regulations;
(c) identify a transfer of personal data by any means, including by reference to—
(i) a sector or geographic area within a third country,
(ii) the controller or processor,
(iii) the recipient of the personal data,
(iv) the personal data transferred,
(v) the means by which the transfer is made, or
(vi) relevant legislation, schemes, lists or other arrangements or documents, as they have effect from time to time;
(d) confer a discretion on a person.
(5) Regulations under this section are subject to the negative resolution procedure.</quote>
   <summary>A new section is added to provide for the approval of transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations by regulations.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change establishes a framework for the approval of transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations, providing flexibility and ensuring compliance with the data protection test.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 74AB (the data protection test)</subject>
   <quote>for “by or under—” substitute “by or under—
(a) this Regulation,
(b) Part 2 of the 2018 Act, and
(c) Parts 5 to 7 of that Act, so far as relevant to general processing.”</quote>
   <summary>The reference to "by or under" is replaced with a list of relevant regulations in Section 74AB.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change clarifies the standards for the protection of data subjects in relation to transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 74AA (transfers approved by regulations)</subject>
   <quote>“(3) In making regulations under this section, the Secretary of State may have regard to any matter which the Secretary of State considers relevant, including the desirability of facilitating transfers of personal data to and from the United Kingdom.”</quote>
   <summary>A new clause is added to Section 74AA to allow the Secretary of State to consider any relevant matter, including the facilitation of transfers of personal data to and from the United Kingdom, when making regulations for the approval of transfers.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change provides flexibility for the Secretary of State to consider various factors when making regulations for the approval of transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 74AA (transfers approved by regulations)</subject>
   <quote>for “make provision by reference to” substitute “make provision by reference to a third country or international organisation specified in the regulations or a description of country or organisation;”</quote>
   <summary>The term "make provision by reference to" is replaced with a more specific phrase in Section 74AA(4)(a).</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change clarifies the provision-making power of the Secretary of State in relation to transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 74AA (transfers approved by regulations)</subject>
   <quote>“(d) confer a discretion on a person.”</quote>
   <summary>A new clause is added to Section 74AA(4) to confer a discretion on a person when making regulations for the approval of transfers.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change provides flexibility for the Secretary of State to confer discretion on a person when making regulations for the approval of transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 74AB (the data protection test)</subject>
   <quote>for “by or under—” substitute “by or under—
(a) this Regulation,
(b) Part 2 of the 2018 Act, and
(c) Parts 5 to 7 of that Act, so far as relevant to general processing.”</quote>
   <summary>The reference to "by or under" is replaced with a list of relevant regulations in Section 74AB.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change clarifies the standards for the protection of data subjects in relation to transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 74AB (the data protection test)</subject>
   <quote>“(3) In considering whether the data protection test is met in relation to transfers of personal data to a third country or international organisation, the Secretary of State must consider, among other things—
(a) respect for the rule of law and for human rights in the country or by the organisation,
(b) the existence, and powers, of an authority responsible for enforcing the protection of data subjects with regard to the processing of personal data in the country or by the organisation,
(c) arrangements for judicial or non-judicial redress for data subjects in connection with such processing,
(d) rules about the transfer of personal data from the country or by the organisation to other countries or international organisations,
(e) relevant international obligations of the country or organisation, and
(f) the constitution, traditions and culture of the country or organisation.
(4) In paragraphs 1 and 2—
(a) the references to the protection provided for data subjects are to that protection taken as a whole,
(b) the references to general processing are to processing to which this Regulation applies or equivalent types of processing in the third country or by the international organisation (as appropriate), and
(c) the references to processing of personal data in the third country or by the international organisation are references only to the processing of personal data transferred from the United Kingdom.
(5) When the data protection test is applied only to certain transfers to a third country or international organisation that are specified or described, or to be specified or described, in regulations (in accordance with section 74AA(4)(b))—
(a) the references in paragraphs 1 to 3 to personal data are to be read as references only to personal data likely to be the subject of such transfers, and
(b) the reference in paragraph 2(d) to the transfer of personal data to other countries or international organisations is to be read as including the transfer of personal data within the third country or international organisation.”</quote>
   <summary>New subsections are added to Section 74AB to provide guidance on the factors to be considered when applying the data protection test for transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change provides clear guidance on the factors to be considered when applying the data protection test for transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations, ensuring compliance with relevant standards and obligations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 74AA (transfers approved by regulations)</subject>
   <quote>“(5) Regulations under this section are subject to the negative resolution procedure.”</quote>
   <summary>A new clause is added to Section 74AA to specify that regulations made under this section are subject to the negative resolution procedure.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change clarifies the procedure for the approval of transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations by regulations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Section 74A (transfers based on adequacy regulations)</subject>
   <quote>Omit section 74A (transfers based on adequacy regulations).</quote>
   <summary>Section 74A, which relates to transfers based on adequacy regulations, is removed.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change removes a section that is no longer necessary in the context of transfers of personal data to third countries for law enforcement purposes.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 74AA (transfers approved by regulations)</subject>
   <quote>“74AA Transfers approved by regulations
(1) For the purposes of section 73, the Secretary of State may by regulations approve transfers of personal data to—
(a) a third country, or
(b) an international organisation.
(2) The Secretary of State may only make regulations under this section approving transfers to a third country or international organisation if the Secretary of State considers that the data protection test is met in relation to the transfers (see section 74AB).
(3) In making regulations under this section, the Secretary of State may have regard to any matter which the Secretary of State considers relevant, including the desirability of facilitating transfers of personal data to and from the United Kingdom.
(4) Regulations under this section may, among other things—
(a) make provision by reference to a third country or international organisation specified in the regulations or a description of country or organisation;
(b) approve all transfers of personal data to a third country or international organisation or only transfers specified or described in the regulations;
(c) identify a transfer of personal data by any means, including by reference to—
(i) a sector or geographic area within a third country,
(ii) the controller or processor,
(iii) the recipient of the personal data,
(iv) the personal data transferred,
(v) the means by which the transfer is made, or
(vi) relevant legislation, schemes, lists or other arrangements or documents, as they have effect from time to time;
(d) confer a discretion on a person.
(5) Regulations under this section are subject to the negative resolution procedure.”</quote>
   <summary>A new section is added to provide for the approval of transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations by regulations.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change establishes a framework for the approval of transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations, providing flexibility and ensuring compliance with the data protection test.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 74AB (the data protection test)</subject>
   <quote>for “by or under—” substitute “by or under—
(a) this Regulation,
(b) Part 2 of the 2018 Act, and
(c) Parts 5 to 7 of that Act, so far as relevant to general processing.”</quote>
   <summary>The reference to "by or under" is replaced with a list of relevant regulations in Section 74AB.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change clarifies the standards for the protection of data subjects in relation to transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 74AB (the data protection test)</subject>
   <quote>“(3) In considering whether the data protection test is met in relation to transfers of personal data to a third country or international organisation, the Secretary of State must consider, among other things—
(a) respect for the rule of law and for human rights in the country or by the organisation,
(b) the existence, and powers, of an authority responsible for enforcing the protection of data subjects with regard to the processing of personal data in the country or by the organisation,
(c) arrangements for judicial or non-judicial redress for data subjects in connection with such processing,
(d) rules about the transfer of personal data from the country or by the organisation to other countries or international organisations,
(e) relevant international obligations of the country or organisation, and
(f) the constitution, traditions and culture of the country or organisation.
(4) In paragraphs 1 and 2—
(a) the references to the protection provided for data subjects are to that protection taken as a whole,
(b) the references to general processing are to processing to which this Regulation applies or equivalent types of processing in the third country or by the international organisation (as appropriate), and
(c) the references to processing of personal data in the third country or by the international organisation are references only to the processing of personal data transferred from the United Kingdom.
(5) When the data protection test is applied only to certain transfers to a third country or international organisation that are specified or described, or to be specified or described, in regulations (in accordance with section 74AA(4)(b))—
(a) the references in paragraphs 1 to 3 to personal data are to be read as references only to personal data likely to be the subject of such transfers, and
(b) the reference in paragraph 2(d) to the transfer of personal data to other countries or international organisations is to be read as including the transfer of personal data within the third country or international organisation.”</quote>
   <summary>New subsections are added to Section 74AB to provide guidance on the factors to be considered when applying the data protection test for transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change provides clear guidance on the factors to be considered when applying the data protection test for transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations, ensuring compliance with relevant standards and obligations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 74AB (the data protection test)</subject>
   <quote>“(5) When the data protection test is applied only to certain transfers to a third country or international organisation that are specified or described, or to be specified or described, in regulations (in accordance with section 74AA(4)(b))—
(a) the references in paragraphs 1 to 3 to personal data are to be read as references only to personal data likely to be the subject of such transfers, and
(b) the reference in paragraph 2(d) to the transfer of personal data to other countries or international organisations is to be read as including the transfer of personal data within the third country or international organisation.”</quote>
   <summary>A new subsection is added to Section 74AB to clarify the scope of the data protection test when applied to certain transfers specified or described in regulations.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change clarifies the scope of the data protection test when applied to certain transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations specified or described in regulations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Section 74AB (the data protection test)</subject>
   <quote>omit subsection (7).</quote>
   <summary>Subsection (7) is removed from Section 74AB.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change removes a subsection that is no longer necessary in the context of the data protection test for transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Section 74AA (transfers approved by regulations)</subject>
   <quote>“(5) Regulations under this section are subject to the negative resolution procedure.”</quote>
   <summary>A new clause is added to Section 74AA to specify that regulations made under this section are subject to the negative resolution procedure.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change clarifies the procedure for the approval of transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations by regulations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 6—Transfers of personal data to third countries etc: law enforcement processing</subject>
   <quote>74AB The data protection test</quote>
   <summary>A new section 74AB is inserted, which establishes the data protection test for transfers of personal data to third countries or international organizations for law enforcement processing.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The establishment of the data protection test ensures that transfers of personal data for law enforcement purposes meet a certain standard of protection, which is important for upholding justice and protecting individuals' rights.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 74B (transfers based on adequacy regulations: review etc)</subject>
   <quote>For the heading substitute “Transfers approved by regulations: monitoring”.</quote>
   <summary>The heading of Section 74B is amended to "Transfers approved by regulations: monitoring".</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment clarifies the purpose of Section 74B, which is to monitor transfers approved by regulations, ensuring transparency and accountability in the process.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Section 17A (transfers based on adequacy decisions)</subject>
   <summary>Section 17A, which pertains to transfers based on adequacy decisions, is deleted.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The deletion of Section 17A indicates a change in the approach to transfers based on adequacy decisions, potentially introducing new mechanisms or requirements for such transfers.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Article 13(1)(f) of the UK GDPR</subject>
   <quote>for “adequacy regulations under section 17A of the 2018 Act” substitute “regulations under Article 45A”</quote>
   <summary>Amendment to Article 13(1)(f) of the UK GDPR, replacing the reference to adequacy regulations under section 17A of the 2018 Act with regulations under Article 45A.</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment ensures consistency and alignment between the UK GDPR and the regulations under Article 45A, providing clarity in the information to be provided to data subjects.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>deletion</type>
   <subject>Section 17C (standard data protection clauses)</subject>
   <summary>Section 17C, which pertains to standard data protection clauses, is deleted.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The deletion of Section 17C suggests a change in the approach to standard data protection clauses, potentially introducing new mechanisms or requirements for such clauses.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>BLUE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Paragraph 26</subject>
   <quote>This paragraph applies to a requirement for safeguards to be provided 5 under—</quote>
   <summary>A new paragraph is inserted that applies to a requirement for safeguards to be provided.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change introduces a requirement for safeguards, which could potentially affect legal processes.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Paragraph 27</subject>
   <quote>Regulations made under section 18(1) of the 2018 Act (transfers necessary for important reasons of public interest) and in force immediately before the relevant day are to be treated, on and after that day, as if made under Article 49(4A) of the UK GDPR (inserted by Schedule 5 to this Act).</quote>
   <summary>A new paragraph is inserted that treats regulations made under section 18(1) of the 2018 Act as if made under Article 49(4A) of the UK GDPR.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change affects the regulations regarding transfers necessary for important reasons of public interest.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Paragraph 28</subject>
   <quote>Regulations made under section 18(2) of the 2018 Act (restrictions on transfers of personal data to third countries and international organisations) and in force immediately before the relevant day are to be treated, on and after that day, as if made under Article 49A of the UK GDPR (inserted by Schedule 5 to this Act).</quote>
   <summary>A new paragraph is inserted that treats regulations made under section 18(2) of the 2018 Act as if made under Article 49A of the UK GDPR.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change affects the regulations regarding restrictions on transfers of personal data to third countries and international organisations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Paragraph 29</subject>
   <quote>Regulations made under section 74A of the 2018 Act (transfers based on adequacy regulations) and in force immediately before the relevant day are to be treated, on and after that day, as if made under section 74AA of that Act (inserted by Schedule 6 to this Act).</quote>
   <summary>A new paragraph is inserted that treats regulations made under section 74A of the 2018 Act as if made under section 74AA of that Act.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change affects the regulations regarding transfers based on adequacy regulations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Paragraph 30</subject>
   <quote>For the purposes of section 73(3) of the 2018 Act (general principles for transfers of personal data), a transfer of personal data to a third country or an international organisation made on or after the relevant day is a transfer made subject to appropriate safeguards where—</quote>
   <summary>A new paragraph is inserted that defines the conditions for a transfer of personal data to a third country or an international organisation to be considered subject to appropriate safeguards.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change affects the regulations regarding transfers of personal data to third countries and international organisations.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 8</subject>
   <quote>The UK GDPR is amended as follows.</quote>
   <summary>A new schedule is inserted that amends the UK GDPR.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change affects the regulations regarding complaints under the UK GDPR.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 9</subject>
   <quote>The UK GDPR is amended as follows.</quote>
   <summary>A new schedule is inserted that amends the UK GDPR.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change affects the regulations regarding data protection.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Schedule 10</subject>
   <quote>“SCHEDULE 1 Regulation 31 INFORMATION COMMISSIONER’S ENFORCEMENT POWERS</quote>
   <summary>A new schedule is inserted that outlines the Information Commissioner's enforcement powers.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change affects the regulations regarding the enforcement powers of the Information Commissioner.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>subsection (2)(a)</subject>
   <quote>for “(b)(i) or (b)(ii)” there were substituted “(b) or (c)”</quote>
   <summary>Substituted "b(i) or (b)(ii)" with "b or c"</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment clarifies the substitution of options for subsection (2)(a).
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>subsection (8A)</subject>
   <quote>after subsection (8) there were inserted—“(8A) Subsections (8B) and (8C) apply if an information notice 30 given to a person under subsection (1)(b) or (c) contains— (a) a statement that a duty of confidentiality applies in relation to the notice, and (b) an explanation of the effects of subsections (8B) and (8C). (8B) The person to whom the information notice is given, and any person employed or engaged for the purpose of that person’s business, must not disclose the existence of the notice without reasonable excuse. (8C) Subsection (8B) does not prevent— 40 Data Protection and Digital Information (No. 2) Bill 175 Schedule 10—Privacy and electronic communications: Commissioner’s enforcement powers (a) a disclosure to a person employed or engaged for the purpose of the business of the person to whom the notice is given, (b) a disclosure made with the permission of the Commissioner (whether the permission is contained in the information notice or otherwise), or (c) a disclosure made for the purpose of obtaining legal advice.”;</quote>
   <summary>Inserted subsections (8A), (8B), and (8C) regarding the disclosure of information notices</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The insertion of subsections (8A), (8B), and (8C) provides guidelines for the disclosure of information notices.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>omission</type>
   <subject>subsection (10)</subject>
   <quote>subsection (10) were omitted.</quote>
   <summary>Omitted subsection (10)</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The omission of subsection (10) removes a specific provision.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 143</subject>
   <quote>Section 143 has effect as if subsection (1) were omitted.</quote>
   <summary>Substituted subsection (1)</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment substitutes subsection (1) of Section 143.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 145(2)(b)</subject>
   <quote>Section 145(2)(b) has effect as if for “section 142(2)(b)” there were substituted “section 142(2)”.</quote>
   <summary>Substituted "section 142(2)(b)" with "section 142(2)"</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment substitutes "section 142(2)(b)" with "section 142(2)" in Section 145(2)(b).
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 146</subject>
   <quote>Section 146 has effect as if— (a) in subsection (1)— (i) for “a controller or processor” there were substituted “a person within subsection (1A)”; (ii) for “the controller or processor” there were substituted “the person”; (iii) for “the data protection legislation” there were substituted “the requirements of the PEC Regulations”; (b) after subsection (1) there were inserted— “(1A) A person is within this subsection if the person— (a) is a communications provider, or (b) is engaged in any activity regulated by the PEC 35 Regulations.”;</quote>
   <summary>Amended Section 146 regarding the definition of a person within subsection (1A)</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment provides a definition for a person within subsection (1A) of Section 146.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 148A</subject>
   <quote>Section 148A has effect as if— (a) in subsection (1)— (i) for “a controller or processor” there were substituted “a person”;</quote>
   <summary>Amended Section 148A regarding the definition of a person</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment provides a definition for a person in Section 148A.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 149</subject>
   <quote>Section 149 has effect as if subsections (2) to (5A) and (7) to (9) were omitted.</quote>
   <summary>Substituted subsections (2) to (5A) and (7) to (9)</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment substitutes subsections (2) to (5A) and (7) to (9) of Section 149.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 155</subject>
   <quote>Section 155 has effect as if— (a) in subsection (1)— (i) in paragraph (a), for “as described in section 149(2), (3), (4), (5) or (5A)” there were substituted “to comply with a requirement of the PEC Regulations”;</quote>
   <summary>Substituted paragraph (a) in subsection (1) of Section 155</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment substitutes paragraph (a) in subsection (1) of Section 155.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>omission</type>
   <subject>subsection (3)</subject>
   <quote>subsection (3) were omitted.</quote>
   <summary>Omitted subsection (3)</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The omission of subsection (3) removes a specific provision.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 157</subject>
   <quote>Section 157 has effect as if— (a) subsection (1) were omitted;</quote>
   <summary>Substituted subsection (1) of Section 157</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment substitutes subsection (1) of Section 157.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 159</subject>
   <quote>Section 159 has effect as if— (a) in subsection (1), the words “Article 83 of the UK GDPR and” were omitted;</quote>
   <summary>Substituted subsection (1) of Section 159</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment substitutes subsection (1) of Section 159.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 182</subject>
   <quote>Section 182 has effect as if subsections (3), (4), (6), (8) to (12) and (14) were omitted.</quote>
   <summary>Substituted subsections (3), (4), (6), (8) to (12), and (14) of Section 182</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment substitutes subsections (3), (4), (6), (8) to (12), and (14) of Section 182.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>omission</type>
   <subject>subsection (13)</subject>
   <quote>subsection (13) of that section has effect as if for “provision comes into force” there were substituted “coming into force of section 86 of the Data Protection and Digital Information Act 2023”.</quote>
   <summary>Substituted subsection (13) of Section 182</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment substitutes subsection (13) of Section 182.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>omission</type>
   <subject>subsection (3) to (5)</subject>
   <quote>Section 196 has effect as if subsections (3) to (5) were omitted.</quote>
   <summary>Omitted subsections (3) to (5) of Section 196</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The omission of subsections (3) to (5) removes specific provisions.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 200</subject>
   <quote>Section 200 has effect as if, in subsection (1), for “this Act” there were substituted “section 144, 148 and 148C and paragraph 15 of Schedule”.</quote>
   <summary>Substituted subsection (1) of Section 200</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment substitutes subsection (1) of Section 200.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 202</subject>
   <quote>Section 202 has effect as if, in subsection (1)(a), for sub-paragraphs (i) and (ii) there were substituted “on an appeal under section 162”.</quote>
   <summary>Substituted subsection (1)(a) of Section 202</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment substitutes subsection (1)(a) of Section 202.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>amendment</type>
   <subject>Section 203</subject>
   <quote>Section 203 has effect as if— (a) in subsection (1), for paragraphs (a) and (b) there were substituted “the exercise of the rights of appeal conferred by section 162”;</quote>
   <summary>Substituted subsection (1) of Section 203</summary>
   <impact>1</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The amendment substitutes subsection (1) of Section 203.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>subsection (1ZA)</subject>
   <quote>“(1ZA) The Registrar General shall cause the following indexes to be made
and kept in the General Register Office—
(a) an index of the entries in the registers kept under section 1
of this Act;
(b) an index of the entries in the registers kept under section 15 20
of this Act.”</quote>
   <summary>This change establishes the requirement for the Registrar General to create and maintain indexes of entries in the registers kept under sections 1 and 15 of the Act.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change improves the efficiency and accessibility of the register system, making it easier to search for and verify information.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>subsection (2)</subject>
   <quote>“(1A) In subsection (1) the “appropriate registration officer” means— 15
(a) in the case of a live-birth, the Registrar General, a
superintendent registrar or a registrar;
(b) in the case of a still-birth—
(i) the Registrar General, or
(ii) a registrar acting at the time of the registration of the 20
still-birth or with the consent of the Registrar
General.”</quote>
   <summary>This change defines the "appropriate registration officer" for live-births and still-births, specifying the Registrar General, superintendent registrar, or registrar depending on the circumstances.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change clarifies the roles and responsibilities of registration officers in the context of live-births and still-births.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>section 250A</subject>
   <quote>“(2) An information standard relating to information technology or IT services may, among other things, make provision about—
(a) the design, quality, capabilities or other characteristics of such technology or services;
(b) contracts or other arrangements under which such technology or services are marketed, supplied, provided or otherwise made available.
(3) An information standard may include technical provision about information technology or IT services, including provision about—
(a) functionality;
(b) connectivity;
(c) interoperability;
(d) portability;
(e) storage of, and access to, information;
(f) security of information.
(4) An information standard may make provision by reference to open standards or proprietary standards.”</quote>
   <summary>This change allows for the creation of information standards related to information technology (IT) and IT services, including provisions for design, quality, contracts, functionality, connectivity, interoperability, portability, storage, access, and security.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change provides a framework for regulating and standardizing information technology and IT services, ensuring their quality, security, and interoperability.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Technology">
      This change promotes the development and use of standardized and secure information technology and IT services.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>section 251ZB</subject>
   <quote>“251ZB Notice requesting compliance by relevant IT providers
(1) If the Secretary of State has reasonable grounds to suspect that a relevant IT provider is not complying with an information standard which applies to the provider, the Secretary of State may give the provider a written notice which—
(a) identifies the standard in question,
(b) sets out the Secretary of State’s grounds for suspecting that the provider is not complying with the standard,
(c) asks the provider to comply with the standard within a period specified in the notice,
(d) asks the provider, within a period specified in the notice, to provide evidence to the Secretary of State’s satisfaction that the provider is complying with the standard, and
(e) if the Secretary of State considers it appropriate, sets out the steps that the Secretary of State considers the provider must take, within a period specified in the notice, in order to comply with the standard.
(2) A period specified for the purposes of subsection (1)(c), (d) or (e) must be a period of at least 28 days beginning with the day on which the notice is given.
(3) The Secretary of State may, by giving the relevant IT provider a further written notice, vary or revoke a notice given under subsection (1).
251ZC Public censure of relevant IT providers
(1) If the Secretary of State has reasonable grounds to suspect that a relevant IT provider is not complying with an information standard which applies to the provider, the Secretary of State may publish a statement to that effect.
(2) The statement may include the text of a notice given to the provider under section 251ZB.
(3) Before publishing a statement under this section, the Secretary of State must give the relevant IT provider—
(a) a copy of the terms of the proposed statement, and
(b) an opportunity to make representations about the decision to publish a statement and the terms of the statement.
(4) If, after considering any representations, the Secretary of State decides to publish the statement, the Secretary of State must inform the relevant IT provider before publishing it.</quote>
   <summary>This change empowers the Secretary of State to issue notices to relevant IT providers suspected of non-compliance with information standards, request compliance within a specified period, and take necessary steps to ensure compliance. It also allows the Secretary of State to publicly censure non-compliant providers by publishing a statement.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      This change strengthens the enforcement of information standards for IT providers, ensuring compliance and accountability.
     </pillar>
     <pillar type="Technology">
      This change promotes the adherence to information standards in the development and provision of IT services.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>
<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Tenure of the chair</subject>
   <quote>The chair must be appointed for a term of not more than 7 years.</quote>
   <summary>The chair of the Commission is now appointed for a maximum term of 7 years.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change in the tenure of the chair of the Commission may impact the stability and continuity of the leadership of the Commission, potentially affecting the effectiveness of its functions.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Tenure of the other non-executive members</subject>
   <quote>The member must be appointed for a term of not more than 7 years.</quote>
   <summary>Non-executive members of the Commission are now appointed for a maximum term of 7 years.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change in the tenure of non-executive members may impact the stability and continuity of the Commission, potentially affecting its ability to carry out its functions effectively.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Remuneration and pensions of non-executive members</subject>
   <quote>The Commission may pay to the non-executive members of the Commission such remuneration and allowances as the Secretary of State may determine.</quote>
   <summary>The Commission now has the authority to determine the remuneration and allowances of non-executive members.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change in remuneration and allowances may impact the attractiveness of non-executive positions in the Commission, potentially affecting the quality and diversity of individuals willing to serve in these roles.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Executive members: terms and conditions</subject>
   <quote>The executive members are to be employed by the Commission on such terms and conditions, including those as to remuneration, as the non-executive members of the Commission may determine.</quote>
   <summary>The terms and conditions, including remuneration, of executive members are now determined by the non-executive members of the Commission.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change in the determination of terms and conditions for executive members may impact the attractiveness of these positions, potentially affecting the recruitment and retention of qualified individuals.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Committees</subject>
   <quote>The Commission may establish committees.</quote>
   <summary>The Commission now has the authority to establish committees.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The establishment of committees may impact the efficiency and effectiveness of the Commission's work, potentially allowing for more specialized focus and expertise in specific areas.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Delegation of functions</subject>
   <quote>The Commission may delegate any of its functions to a member of the Commission, an employee of the Commission, or a committee of the Commission.</quote>
   <summary>The Commission now has the authority to delegate its functions to members, employees, or committees.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The delegation of functions may impact the efficiency and effectiveness of the Commission's work, potentially allowing for more specialized focus and expertise in specific areas.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Money</subject>
   <quote>The Secretary of State may make payments to the Commission.</quote>
   <summary>The Secretary of State now has the authority to make payments to the Commission.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change in funding may impact the financial stability and independence of the Commission, potentially affecting its ability to carry out its functions effectively.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change>

<change>
   <type>insertion</type>
   <subject>Fees etc and other sums</subject>
   <quote>All fees, charges, penalties and other sums received by the Commission in carrying out its functions are to be paid to the Secretary of State.</quote>
   <summary>All fees, charges, penalties, and other sums received by the Commission are now to be paid to the Secretary of State.</summary>
   <impact>2</impact>
   <clarity>3</clarity>
   <pillars>
     <pillar type="Justice System">
      The change in the payment of fees and other sums may impact the financial stability and independence of the Commission, potentially affecting its ability to carry out its functions effectively.
     </pillar>
   </pillars>
   <flag>WHITE</flag>
</change></all>